<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-02-01T19:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Sustainability of Lamar Jackson’s Production</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sustainability of Lamar Jackson's Production" /><published>2020-02-01T17:44:24-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-01T17:44:24-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: miro.medium.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When tasked with winning football games, every head coach in the NFL talks about establishing an identity, as all the best teams have one. The 49ers are winning off of a multi-dimensional running game and a ferocious defense that gets to the opposing quarterback. The Saints are winning off a dink-and-dunk quick-hitter offense. The Chiefs are winning with speed on the outside and a lethal deep-ball passer. The Patriots have been &quot;doing their job&quot; for the last 2 decades. But out of all the teams in football, there's one team's identity which stands out as the most established, physical, and against-the-grain in all of football&amp;colon; the 14-2 Baltimore Ravens, the best team in the league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all starts with their stifling defense which, once again, is a contender for the league's best. While they have a good defensive line, where they really shine is at defensive-back, where they have the league's deepest and most dangerous group. Headlined by the elite ball-hawking Earl Thomas and suffocating Marlon Humphry, the Ravens also have three other feisty cornerbacks in Brandon Carr, Jimmy Smith and Marcus Peters. On the other side of the ball, the Ravens run the rock up the opposition's throat, with a rock-solid offensive-line anchored by Ronnie Stanley and the ageless Marshal Yanda, premier blocking tight-ends in Mark Andrews and Nick Boyle, and one of the league's angriest runners in Mark Ingram. But these assets aren't what makes the Ravens special; they've been this type of team for a long time.  The addition of one piece has made their offense go from byzantine to innovative, from stagnant to electric. This one piece is arguably the best mobile quarterback in NFL history: Lamar Jackson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2013, the last time the Ravens won the Super Bowl, the NFL was a very different place. For starters, the team they faced in the Super Bowl, the 49ers, had Colin Kaepernick installed as their starting quarterback following an electric run to the big game. Kaepernick was one of the hottest young quarterbacks in the game because of his legs, having gashed the Packers in that very same playoff run for 181 yards and 2 touchdowns on an 11.3 yards per carry clip. This performance set the record for most single-game rushing yards by a quarterback not only in the playoffs, but in any game in NFL history, a record that still stands today. On top of that, the Rookie of the Year that season was none other than current Ravens back-up, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap1000000134287/article/robert-griffin-iii-wins-offensive-rookie-of-the-year&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robert Griffin III&lt;/a&gt; (RG3), who capped off a historic rookie season with 815 yards on the ground, a number that ranks 7th all time for quarterbacks. Another rookie that season was Russell Wilson, a player whose best rushing season ranks one rung above RG3's, at 849 yards. All of this is to say that the last time the Ravens were dominant, rushing quarterbacks were a trend. Since then, mobile quarterbacks like RG3, Kaepernick, Marcus Mariota, Tim Tebow and Johnny Manziel have flamed out, while remaining players with this skillset like Russell Wilson and the younger Deshaun Watson rely more heavily on their passing ability than their legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this trend slowly dying out, Lamar Jackson was a polarizing prospect when he finally hit the NFL draft in 2018. Michael Vick, the consensus greatest mobile quarterback of all-time before Lamar Jackson, endorsed him as a better runner than himself, but due to the decline of this skill's usage, many teams didn't even view Jackson as a quarterback prospect. Hall of Fame General Manager Bill Polian referred to Jackson as &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2760372-bill-polian-says-lamar-jackson-is-short-should-move-to-wr-in-the-nfl?source=post_page---------------------------&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;too slight for the position&lt;/a&gt;, not enough of a thrower, and stated that he should switch to a position such as wide-receiver, which is more reliant on speed. Jackson ended up being selected 32nd overall in the NFL draft, and is currently revitalizing speed for his position. His 1206 rushing yards through 15 games this season is an NFL record, shattering Michael Vick's previous high of 1039, and making him a surefire bet to win the MVP. After seeing this historical production, I wanted to measure Jackson's improvement since his rookie season, see how he stacks up to past quarterbacks in this department, and decide how sustainable his current level of production is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, through 7 starts in his rookie season, Lamar Jackson had 556 yards on the ground, an average of 79.4 yards and 17 attempts per game. Despite the excellent production, 17 rushing attempts is an unsustainable number for a quarterback. To make this number tangible, look no further than this year's leading rusher Derrick Henry. Henry is &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.redd.it/fq9o7krtz9d11.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;built like a truck&lt;/a&gt; and led the league in rushing this season. Despite all this, Henry averaged a hair under 19 carries a game (18.93), less than 2 carries per game more than Jackson in his 2018 season. The Ravens knew this had to change too, and hired Kaepernick's former offensive coordinator, Greg Roman, to run the offense. This season, Jackson averaged an even better 80.4 yards per game over a 15 game sample, but averaged under 12 attempts (11.7) per game on the ground, a much more sustainable number. To put Jackson's production in context, Ezekiel Elliott, who had the 4th most rushing yards in the league this season, rushed for 1357 yards in 16 games, which averages out to 84.8 yards per game. He did this in 125 more attempts than Jackson. Obviously, Jackson has the element of surprise on his side, and defenses crowd the box on Zeke, but still, a quarterback rushing for close to the same yardage per game as the highest paid running-back in the league is just absurd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph displayed below shows Lamar Jackson's per-game stats as a rookie compared to other notable running-backs' in 2018. This dot-plot includes every single 2018 pro-bowler at the position, as well as a few other notable players, such as Mark Ingram, Leonard Fournette and Jordan Howard. Despite the smaller sample size, the fact that he ranked 3rd in carries and 4th in yardage per game from the quarterback position over his last 7 games is eye opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jackson's development as a passer has been the key difference that has allowed him to drastically improve his production on a per-carry basis, as it doesn't allow defenses to blitz and key off on his running ability. At the end of last season, many were calling Lamar Jackson more of a running back than a quarterback. NFL.com's QB Index wrote that while Jackson arguably added more value as a runner in half a season than any quarterback in NFL history, his errant throws and league-leading 12 fumbles (in 7 games) kept his value in check, ranking Lamar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001007337/article/qb-index-patrick-mahomes-leads-yearend-rankings&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;23rd in the league&lt;/a&gt; out of 32 starting quarterbacks. At the end of this season, he was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001091708/article/qb-index-week-17-patrick-mahomes-vaults-russell-wilson&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;consensus number 1&lt;/a&gt; and an MVP shoo-in. What parts of his passing game improved? According to Pro Football Reference (PFR), his ANY/A (Adjusted Net Yards per pass Attempt) has gone up from 5.99 to 8.19, his completion percentage has gone up from a terrible 58.2% to a much better 66.1%, and his sack percentage has gone down from 8.6% to 5.4%. To rationalize this data, when analyzing PFR's passing index, where a score of 100 is league average and anything higher is better, Jackson has gone from below average values hovering in the 90s range to above average values in the early 100s in every notable passing stat, among them ANY/A, Touchdown Percentage (TD%), Interception Percentage (INT%) and Completion Percentage (CMP%). His touchdown percentage, in particular, was tops in the league, as he had a league-leading 36 passing touchdowns on the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stats show his increased mastery of the passing game, which increases the opportunity to make misdirection plays and establish a dominant running-game for the Ravens. The opposing defense must respect the pass and can no longer crowd up the line-of-scrimmage to stuff the run. The ANY/A in particular is telling, as this statistic has a strong correlation with offensive production. It is essentially a formula which takes passing yards, adds the number of touchdowns times a multiplier, subtracts the yardage lost due to sacks and the number of interceptions times a multiplier, then divides the total by the sum of the passing attempts and number of sacks taken. While this sounds like complicated jargon, it's essentially just calculating the average yards per play with touchdowns and interceptions thrown factored in. Thus, the ANY/A is an effective way to see how well a quarterback is able to lead his offense to points. This and the rest of Jackson's passing statistics help explain why his yards-per-attempt while rushing the football was substantially higher this season, sitting at 6.9 yards-per-attempt this year compared to last season's 4.7 average. It also helps explain how the Ravens as a team set the NFL's all time record for rushing yards in a season, with their 3296 yards on the ground breaking a mark that stood for 41 years prior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Lamar Jackson's improvement as a passer has fueled his and his team's improved statistical performance, I wanted to see just how sustainable this improvement truly is. Visually, Jackson's uniqueness is obvious. Lamar is just built different. He has unreal speed, better shiftiness than most running-backs, and touch on his passes. But, we've seen players like Kaepernick and RG3 take the league by storm in the past, just to regress to league average or worse in their next season. In order to gain statistical insight on what level of regression to expect, I recorded the statistics of a group of mobile quarterbacks in their first full season as a starter, and compared this to their statistics in their next full season accrued as a starter, attempting to see whether defenses figured them out. Players like Lamar Jackson and Colin Kaepernick had seasons where they started 7 games before their first full season, so I set the threshold of a full season as a starter to be a Week 1 starter who played at least 14 games. In order for me to consider the quarterback mobile, I wanted them to average at least 3 carries per game in their first season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to conduct this experiment, I gathered the statistics in major passing and rushing metrics for 10 mobile quarterbacks in the 2000s. This group consisted of Colin Kaepernick, Robert Griffin III, Marcus Mariota, Mitchell Trubisky, Russell Wilson, Cam Newton, Michael Vick, Daunte Culpepper, Dak Prescott and Deshaun Watson. While many of these players obviously play differently from Lamar, I believe most of these players are more than capable of running the football. Mitchell Trubisky and Marcus Mariota have shown commendable speed rushing the football, while Vick, Culpepper, Griffin and Kaepernick have had huge games on the ground. Newton, Wilson, Watson and Prescott have all had spurts of MVP play and have shown the ability to run and pass effectively throughout their careers. When collecting data, I once again started off by focusing on the Pro-Football-Reference metrics for ANY/A, Completion Percentage, Touchdown Percentage and Interception Percentage, four of the most important statistics for a quarterback. I found the Pro-Football-Reference metric valuable because it measured a quarterback's statistics in these categories relative to their peers in that given year, providing a standardized metric that adjusts for the changes in the passing game from Vick and Culpepper's eras to the present. Regardless, I found that all the players in the sample, on average, had above average statistics in their first full season as a starter. In their next full season, after an entire offseason of defenses keying in on their tendencies, this population of quarterbacks, on average, was slightly below league-average. Considering that the list contains a handful of MVP level talents, the observation that these quarterbacks went from close to the top 10 players at their positions to barely average is shocking. Obviously, there were some exceptions, but almost all the quarterbacks showed a slight regression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, wanting to also look at raw statistical change, I compared the raw values of each of these quarterback's rushing attempts, yards, ANY/A, TD% and INT% to see the noticeable per-player changes in each statistic. To do this, I found each of these quarterback's statistics in their first full year, and either found a proportional change (ANY/A), percentage change (TD%, INT%), or the raw change (rushing yards and attempts per game) in their statistics the next-season. This thus calculates the average individual performance decrease, regardless of a player's talent, as the player is now only being compared with himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings proved to be insightful. Firstly, most quarterbacks kept rushing the football the same amount, with around the same number of production. Exceptions included Trubisky and RG3, who both saw their number of rushing attempts decrease by over 1 attempt per game, as well as Culpepper, who saw an uptick in usage and production. The rushing attempts and yards per game of the average player remained almost the same, decreasing by a miniscule 0.16 attempts and 0.95 yards per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the Adjusted Net Yards per Attempt (ANY/A), the ANY/A value in the following year was 0.84 times the value in the first year. Thus, the regression was 0.16 multiplied by the ANY/A in the first year, with the proportional decrease displayed. Essentially, all that means is that these players were 16% less efficient in using their arm to gain yards and lead their offense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the touchdown percentage dipped by 1.1%, meaning 1.1% less of these quarterbacks' throws resulted in touchdowns. Culpepper had the most jarring drop in touchdown percentage, with 3.2% less of his passes ending in paydirt. Only two players had their touchdown percentages go up: Deshaun Watson and Michael Vick. On the flipside, the interception percentage went up, with these quarterbacks throwing picks, on average, on 0.58% more of their throws. Watson and Dak Prescott had the most sizeable increase in picks thrown, with 1.8% more of their passes winding up in the opposition's hands. That adds up to almost an extra 1 out of 50 passes ending up in a turnover. The average quarterback throws over 30 passes per game, so this number is significant over an entire season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does all this mean in-terms of Lamar? If we go by the raw average changes calculated, Lamar's ANY/A will go down to 6.88, his league-leading touchdown rate will go down to 7.9%, and his interception rate will go up to close to 2.1%. The data also indicates that his rushing attempts and yardage per game would remain somewhat similar. But, as we all know, all players are different, and even with these statistics factoring in an expected regression, Lamar Jackson would still be a player capable of wrecking games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Lamar Jackson is still going to be a game-changer, and the Raven's defense is still going to be suffocating. Regardless, I would expect defenses to catch on to Jackson to a certain extent, and I expect his statistics next season to hover closer to the numbers listed above than to those he recorded in his 2019 MVP campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking for a team to compare this Ravens group to, it's hard not to go back to the last time the Ravens hoisted the Lombardi Trophy and see parallels to the team they beat that fateful day. Both the 2019 Ravens and the 2013 49ers had a dynamic quarterback who took the league by storm, a stifling defense stacked with difference-makers, and most importantly, a Harbaugh at head coach.  Regardless of the similarities between Lamar's and Kaepernick's supporting casts, one of these players is the presumptive league MVP, and one of them has never made a Pro-Bowl. Despite this season's disappointing end, I expect Lamar Jackson and the Ravens to keep on flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: pro-football-reference.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vishal Sundaram</name></author><summary type="html">When tasked with winning football games, every head coach in the NFL talks about establishing an identity, as all the best teams have one. The 49ers are winning off of a multi-dimensional running game and a ferocious defense that gets to the opposing quarterback. The Saints are winning off a dink-and-dunk quick-hitter offense. The Chiefs are winning with speed on the outside and a lethal deep-ball passer. The Patriots have been &quot;doing their job&quot; for the last 2 decades. But out of all the teams in football, there's one team's identity which stands out as the most established, physical, and against-the-grain in all of football&amp;colon; the 14-2 Baltimore Ravens, the best team in the league.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Brief History of MLB Postseason Format Changes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Brief History of MLB Postseason Format Changes" /><published>2020-01-25T13:53:48-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-25T13:53:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: cnycentral.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many baseball fans, the MLB postseason&amp;mdash;the World Series in particular&amp;mdash;is the ultimate test of skill and teamwork. Over the course of a month, the best teams battle it out to become the World Series champion. Dating back to the first MLB postseason in 1884, the title of World Series champion has been the highest achievement that a professional baseball team can attain. Thus, the importance of the postseason to MLB teams and baseball enthusiasts alike cannot be understated. This, however, has not kept the MLB from changing the postseason format every 10 to 20 years. As expected, these changes are met with criticism and controversy, roster and strategy changes, and&amp;mdash;in rare cases&amp;mdash;MLB dynasties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the MLB postseason was first introduced to the professional league in 1884, it was very simple. After a few years of simple exhibition matches, the MLB decided on a postseason format that consisted of only one series&amp;mdash;later to be called the World Series. In this format, the top-seeded teams from the American League and the National League would face off in a single best-of-seven series (in 1903, 1919, 1920, and 1921 a best-of-nine was played). This oversimplified version was used for nearly a hundred years before it was modified. In 1969, when each of the MLB leagues were split into two regions, the postseason was extended to become a two round best-of-seven series. In this format, the top teams of each league would compete against one another in the ALCS and the NLCS before advancing to the World Series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: britannica.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a new region was again added to each MLB league in 1995, a third round, this time a best-of-five was added to the postseason. To accomodate for the odd numbers, a wild card team was added to each league; the wild card team would play the divisional champion in the best-of-five Division Series. Finally, in 2012 a second wild card was added to each league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you have probably concluded, the MLB's postseason format quickly became one of the most variable in all of American sports history. The ramifications of these changes were felt far and wide among the baseball community. One of the most direct impacts of these changes was on match variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before 1969, when the MLB postseason was comprised of a single series, match variation was nonexistent. At the end of each season, the top-seeded of the American League or the National League was guaranteed to win the World Series. However, as the MLB postseason was extended to accommodate for internal league changes, more and more teams gained access to the once elite MLB postseason. Resultantly, the World Series became unpredictable. As of 2019, ten teams participate in the MLB postseason, each fighting for the title of World Series champion. No teams are guaranteed a spot in the World Series, or even the ALCS and NLCS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any advantage that top-seeded teams once had in the MLB postseason is slowly diminishing. Let's take a look at how the probability of a top team winning the World Series has changed since 1969.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, these results are fairly straightforward. As the leagues split into more distinct regions and wild card teams were added to the MLB postseason, the top-seeded teams struggled to stay consistent. If more spots are made available in the MLB postseason in the future, this trend will likely continue; the title of top seed will lose the little competitive edge that it now provides. Even if the current format remains unchanged for years to come, the spike seen in the 2012-2019 seasons will likely drop off as more data is made available. But what does this trend mean for MLB fans and teams today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For casual fans, this trend is nothing but beneficial. The expansion of the MLB postseason has provided baseball fans with content that was previously unavailable. Furthermore, the changes made to the MLB postseason have made the games more enticing&amp;mdash;no games are unwinnable and no spots are secure.  The MLB postseason can take any number of turns before a World Series champion is crowned, as the Washington Nationals showed us this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: washington.org&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For MLB teams, things are a bit more complicated. In recent years, the postseason format has come to influence team play styles and strategies. Due to the expansion of the MLB postseason, many teams have attempted to adopt a more conservative, consistent play style. In today's three round best-of-seven series format, consistency is more important than ever. To win the World Series, a team must be able to play at the highest level at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the format changes have resulted in an extended MLB postseason, they have not always resulted in the most competitive games. When wild card teams and the Division Series were first introduced to the postseason in 1995, competition levels took a turn for the worst. Under this new format, the wildcard teams&amp;mdash;often considered the underdog teams of each league&amp;mdash;would immediately face off against the top-seeded divisional champion of their respective league. In recent years, these matchups have given top teams an easy route to the ALCS or NLCS. Consequently, many top-seeded teams arrive to the ALCS or NLCS unprepared for the competition and pressure that the series will surely bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the differences may be subtle, they cannot be ignored. For the ALCS and the World Series, there is little to be said. The average number of games played per series has remained relatively constant, despite postseason format changes. The NLCS, however, brings up questions for concern. From 1985 to 1993, the average number of games played per NLCS was 6.3. In today's postseason format, this number is almost a whole game lower at 5.5. In a simple best-of-seven series, this change is quite drastic. Although we cannot be sure what brought about this change, it is likely that MLB postseason format changes&amp;mdash;specifically the addition of wild card teams&amp;mdash;had a direct impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how could something as impartial as format changes possibly have such an impact?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation is the prevalence of baseball dynasties or 'dream teams' in recent years. As the postseason format has changed over the years, so has the importance of consistent play. When the postseason was first introduced to the MLB, inconsistent teams won the World Series quite frequently. However, in today's three round best-of-seven series, consistency is more or less a requirement. Thus, as consistent play gradually became more and more important, select teams were able to find their niche among a particular postseason format. The result was an absolute domination of MLB league and postseason play. Let's see if any baseball dynasties formed from 1995 to 2011 in which the three series best-of-seven (with one wild card team for each league) format was used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the New York Yankees were able to find great success in the MLB postseason throughout these years. Whether or not this success was due the postseason format cannot be known for sure. However, the history of the New York Yankees and their performance in previous MLB postseasons support the claim that the postseason format played a major role in their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 1985 to 1993, when the postseason was a two round best-of-seven series, the New York Yankees were unable to win a single World Series. When this format was changed, however, the Yankees looked like an entirely new team. In the early years of this new format, the Yankees were unstoppable; they were crowned World Series champion three years in a row, beginning in 1998. Without the postseason format change of 1995, it is unlikely that the Yankees would have been so dominant in these years. When the postseason format was changed in 2012, their success came to an end. Since these changes, the New York Yankees have not won, or participated in, the World Series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many professional baseball teams and fans dream of a time when the MLB stops altering the postseason format, it is unlikely that this dream will come true any time soon. While previous format changes have resulted in lower levels of postseason competition and occasional dynasties, the MLB has only benefited from the changes. By extending the postseason format and introducing wild card teams, the MLB is raking in more cash than ever. The MLB has no reason to halt the postseason changes that they have profited so greatly from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2001, the MLB has seen annual increases in revenue. In more recent years, this trend has only become more apparent. Every year, the MLB seems to outperform themselves, pushing their annual revenue to unprecedented levels. With this in mind, I would not be surprised to see the MLB postseason expanded even further in upcoming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: baseball-reference.com, statista.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Fischer Sherrod</name></author><summary type="html">For many baseball fans, the MLB postseason&amp;mdash;the World Series in particular&amp;mdash;is the ultimate test of skill and teamwork. Over the course of a month, the best teams battle it out to become the World Series champion. Dating back to the first MLB postseason in 1884, the title of World Series champion has been the highest achievement that a professional baseball team can attain. Thus, the importance of the postseason to MLB teams and baseball enthusiasts alike cannot be understated. This, however, has not kept the MLB from changing the postseason format every 10 to 20 years. As expected, these changes are met with criticism and controversy, roster and strategy changes, and&amp;mdash;in rare cases&amp;mdash;MLB dynasties.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christian Yelich and the Rise to Stardom</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ChristianYelich" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christian Yelich and the Rise to Stardom" /><published>2020-01-15T10:30:55-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-15T10:30:55-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ChristianYelich</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ChristianYelich">&lt;p&gt;Drafted as a Florida Marlin 23rd overall in 2010, Christian Yelich was a very highly touted prospect with loads of potential. As predictions usually go for players drafted in the first few rounds, he was expected to eventually reach the Major Leagues and be a top of the order bat, hitting in a fierce and intimidating Marlins lineup (80-82, 3rd in NL East in 2010) that was supposed to include Giancarlo Stanton, Hanley Ramirez, Emilio Bonifacio, Cameron Maybin, and eventually Marcell Ozuna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.minorleagueball.com/2012/5/23/3037479/prospect-of-the-day-christian-yelich-of-miami-marlins-scouting-report&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A scouting report compiled by John Sickles on minorleagueball.com&lt;/a&gt; in 2012 stated that Yelich has a &quot;decent feel for the strike zone and is tapping into his natural power with greater efficiency. Although he isn't likely to develop into an overwhelming home run masher, Yelich should hit for average, get on base at a good clip, and produce above-average power.&quot; Florida (then Miami after the 2012 season) began it's rebuild late into 2017, sending both Stanton and Ozuna away. In early 2018, Yelich was traded to the Brewers in exchange for a plethora of top prospects, including outfielder Lewis Brinson, the Brewers top prospect at the time. The Brewers, anticipating a leadoff man in return from Miami, were actually in store for much more than they bargained for. Yelich became one of the most dangerous hitters in the MLB, now a perennial MVP leader with a massive uptick in power and Batting Average, whos also one of the leaders in stolen bases in the National League. On July 19th, Yelich had batted 60 Home Runs and stolen 33 bases in his previous 162 games, the first MLB player to ever launch 60+ HR and swipe 30+ SB in that time span.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how was he able to do this? How did Christian Yelich change his approach at the plate, shifting him from a slightly above average MLB player with the Miami Marlins to one who is seemingly on track to become a first ballot Hall of Famer with the Brewers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we take a dive into the mind of Milwaukee's Starting Right Fielder, understanding the slight tweaks that have created such dominance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We begin with the way in which Yelich has changed his approach at the plate. Following the trade from Miami to Milawukee, the right fielder has decreased the average amount of pitches that he seen per plate appearance, with the number now falling under 4. A rate of less than 4 pitches per at bat means Yelich has clearly seen the ball better and attacked early, not letting himself get too deep into counts, where he could be in danger of seeing tough offspeed pitches (sliders, curveballs, changeups) that are known for producing swings and misses. This strategy in the batters box is further evidenced by Yelich's 1st pitch swing percentage. His swing rate has shot up from an average of 19.4% over his 5 seasons with the Marlins to tallies of 28.8% and 29.7% respectively in his first two campaigns with the Brewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There simply do not exist enough players in baseball who swing on the first pitch, as most hitters take in order to get a sense of how the pitcher is throwing. However, a large portion of the time, when a pitcher hurls in his first pitch of an at bat, they do so with the intention of getting a sense of the strike zone. This is where hitters like Yelich have now begun to cash in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite his tendency to swing early and often, Yelich has also walked in a substantial 13.8% of his at bats, good enough for a rate that clocks in as the 14th highest in the Major Leagues. It certainly makes sense why this number is very high, as pitchers are scared to throw hittable pitches to the star right fielder. However, his slight adjustments in the off season prior to Milwaukee have clearly added an effective plate discipline to Yelich's aggressive approach, leading to the productivity that can be seen from his results at the plate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest contributors to Yelich's exponential boost in offensive production has to do with launch angle. It's a known phenomenon that an increase in launch angle has a positive correlation with an increase in extra base hits. Many thought that Yelich would regress slightly from his 2018 campaign, playing off his MVP season as a fluke, calling him a magician on the offensive side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Yelich has frankly gotten even better in 2019. In his 2018 campaign, his launch angle was ranked 445th in the MLB at 4.7 degrees. In 2019, he has more than doubled his launch angle degree to 11.2, a statistic that ranked him 278th in the MLB. An increase in launch angle leads to an increase in fly balls which leads to an increase in home runs and extra base hits. As we can see in the below graph, as his launch angle increased, his ratio of XBH to hits has also followed suit. Because of this, he has seen less of his batted balls hit the ground in comparison to the amount that are skyrocketed into the air. Yelich, in his MVP year, had 57 of the balls that he put into play hit the barrel of his bat (8.8%), ranking 18th in the big leagues. This year, in less games and 71 fewer at-bats, Yelich has had 59 of his batted balls hit the barrel of his bat (10.2%) ranking him 7th in the majors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Hosmer and Christian Yelich had once been very similar players based on their style of play and their approach at the plate. However, the reason that Yelich is accelerating into the peak and prime of his career and Hosmer is on the decline (his peak coming with the Kansas City Royals from 2013 to 2017) is because unlike Hosmer, Yelich has made the necessary adjustments to his launch angle (Hosmer ranks 451st in the MLB with an average launch angle of 2.1%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yelich is now hitting 3x the amount of homers as Hosmer and grounding into now about 2/3 of the amount of double plays as Hosmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the two graphs below, before joining the Brewers, Yelich didn't contribute much towards his respective teams' win rate as he was hovering around 50% for the majority of his career. However, largely contributed to his adjustments at the plate, since joining the Brewers, Yelich is hovering around a 55% win rate, so he is contributing to 5% more wins for a .500 team. A correlation can be drawn between the steady rise of Yelich's OPS and the fluctuations in the added winning percentage he brings to an average team. The raise in OPS seen in Yelich's stat line since joining Milwaukee can be attributed partially to his decreasing AB/HR rate, meaning Yelich is hitting with an increased amount of power as a result of the changes he has made to his swing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In talking about the Brewers as a team, Milwaukee finished the 2018 season at 95-67, 1st in the NL Central, advancing to the NLCS before losing the pennant in 7 games to the Los Angeles Dodgers, who eventually lost in the World Series to the Boston Red Sox. Now, in 2019, at the time of initial data collection, the Brewers stood at 78-69, 4.0 games off of the division lead, and tied with Chicago for the 2nd wild card spot. With Yelich's performance, it begs the question as to where the team would be without his production at the plate. Yelich's WAR for the 2018 clocked in at 7.6, and he had already accumulated a total of 7.1 up to August 10th, in about 15 fewer games, when he suffered a fractured knee cap, ending his season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing Yelich from the Brewers roster resulted in an NLDS lineup of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the WAR statistic as a numerical measure of how this team would perform, rather than just looking at the potential lineup and observing that the Brewers look much less threatening without Yelich, the Brewers would have finished last season around a mark of 87-75, and would currently be a sub-.500 team at 71-76 overall at this point in the year. This would have left the Brewers completely out of last year's playoffs (forget their first division title since 2011) and second in the last 36 years or their NLDS win, and near advancement to the World Series. This season, they would be 11 games behind the Cardinals at the top of the division, and another 7 games back of the wild card, clearly a seller at the trade deadline, and not a team that reached the NL Wild Card Game. His 0.543% Waa, which indicates the winning percentage of a .500 club if they added Christian Yelich to their roster, is a good representation of how just his bat alone can turn an average team into a contender. With Yelich locked up until the 2023 season, being paid just upwards of $7M annually, the Brewers have a considerable amount of money to work with to add in the missing pieces that are halting World Series contention. Consider the 6 position players, other than Yelich (#8) who landed within the top 10 for WAR last season:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 6, only 2 of them have also won an MVP like Yelich, while 4 of the 6 have higher salaries than the Brewers right fielder. The two who have lower salaries, Ramirez and Chapman, are both just coming off of, or still on their rookie deals which is why they haven't reached max salary potential yet. Yelich, who just exchanged his rookie deal for a 7 year, $49M offer, is considerably underpaid in comparison to the $20M to $35M range expected for a player of his caliber. If the Brewers choose to keep Yelich on the contract, they save a solid $13M to $25M that could be spent on improving other areas of need on the team. While the 2019 Brewers are in the top half of teams for most batting statistics (R, OPS, OBP, etc), they fall into the bottom half for both Starting Pitchers statistics and Reliever stats. Players such as Gerritt Cole, Madison Bumgardner, Zach Wheeler, Cole Hamels, Rick Porcello and Dellin Betances will all be free agents come this next offseason, and it is reasonable to think that with a maximum of $25M of wiggle room, just alone from Yelich's contract, to both complement a blooming Zach Davies and Chase Anderson in the starting rotation with a front end and back end of the rotation starter and a reliever to provide some bullpen depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christian Yelich has become one of if not the best players in the MLB following his trade to Milwaukee, and it is up to the Brewers to take advantage of that before his contract expires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: baseball-reference.com, mlb.com/stats and mlb.com/statcast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Max Blane</name></author><summary type="html">Drafted as a Florida Marlin 23rd overall in 2010, Christian Yelich was a very highly touted prospect with loads of potential. As predictions usually go for players drafted in the first few rounds, he was expected to eventually reach the Major Leagues and be a top of the order bat, hitting in a fierce and intimidating Marlins lineup (80-82, 3rd in NL East in 2010) that was supposed to include Giancarlo Stanton, Hanley Ramirez, Emilio Bonifacio, Cameron Maybin, and eventually Marcell Ozuna.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analyzing Factors That Go Into a Fast Marathon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/FastestMarathon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing Factors That Go Into a Fast Marathon" /><published>2020-01-14T18:36:08-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-14T18:36:08-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/FastestMarathon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/FastestMarathon">&lt;p&gt;On October 12, 2019, it was still early morning as the world watched as Elliot Kipchoge put one foot in front of another, gracefully passing the finish line and becoming the first person ever to run a marathon in under two hours. He finished in a blistering fast time of 1:59:40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many factors came together to shatter the two hour time barrier in the marathon. First and foremost, Kipchoge is the best marathoner in the world, as he currently holds the official world record at 2:01:39. He was close to closing in on the barrier, but not quite there yet. The race organizers (INEOS) needed a way to trim down his time by at least 1:40. That equates to about 6 seconds faster per mile than the world record. INEOS was able to accomplish this by having the following: an army of pacers to swap in and out every couple of miles, a car with a laser to keep the pacers in check, an unreleased pair of shoes Nike specifically engineered for the race, an extremely flat course with minimal turns, and an optimal temperature that was cool and not too humid. While most marathon runners cannot expect the same level of support that was made available to Kipchoge, the last two factors seem to be more variable to regular marathon runners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To investigate the effects of the elevation of courses and weather on marathon times, we will consider the results from the Boston, Berlin, and Chicago marathons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Effects of Weather&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To look at the effects of weather, it is best to look at the Boston marathon. The Boston Marathon is infamous for it's volatile year to year weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The median finishing times year to year are almost uniform except for a few standout years. The median finishing times in 2004, 2005 and 2012 are higher than those of the other years shown. During these years, races all share a common factor: the temperature at the starting time was in the 70s with the high of that day reaching the 80s and 90s. Another interesting year is 2013, where the median finishing time was well below the other years'. We can also see that the spread of the times was much lower than the rest of the other results; the starting temperature was 37 degrees and only went up to 55 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These observations from the graph are summarized when we place these race years in bins of categorical temperatures.  This presented a problem because in a 2+ hour race, the temperature did not remain constant throughout the race. The solution was to bin these races with &lt;a href=&quot;https://findmymarathon.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;FindMyMarathon&lt;/a&gt;, where it shows the temperature at the start of the race and the high for that day. The races were placed into three bins: cold, moderate, and hot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;		• Cold races indicate races with a start temperature below 59 degrees fahrenheit and the daily high below 60 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;		• Moderate races were a little trickier, where I considered starting temperatures below 59 degrees but also having a daily high over 60.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;		• Hot races had starting temperatures of over 70 degrees with daily highs of over 70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately, we see the difference of the means between the three bins. To verify that the difference is statistically significant, I ran an Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) test to find that the p-value was approximately zero. Therefore, the difference of means is indeed statistically significant. In other words, there is a very low probability that the difference in the means would appear by chance alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Effects of Elevation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the analysis of the effects of course elevation, it is important to clear up a common misconception. While the difficulty of running up hills is widely recognized, the challenge of running downhill must also be accounted for. Running downhill requires your legs to &quot;catch&quot; you at every step you take to prevent you from falling over. This creates more wear and tear on the leg muscles, which is especially prevalent in long races such as marathons. Thus, the optimal course is one that is as flat as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To look at the effects of elevation, we will look at the Boston and Berlin marathons, two drastically different race courses in terms of elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let's look observe the elevation maps of the respective courses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Boston Marathon Elevation&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see that the Boston Marathon experiences drops of elevation throughout the entire race, showing that the course is mostly downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Berlin Marathon Elevation&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see that the Berlin Marathon elevation is mostly consistent throughout the entire race, showing that it is a relatively flat course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Berlin Marathon Times 2005-2013, Boston Marathon Times 2001-2014&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see that the Boston Marathon has a lower median, twenty fifth percentile, and seventy fifth percentile than the Berlin marathon. We can infer that the downhill course typically speeds up overall times in marathons. This is peculiar, as this same logic does not apply to elite runners, as they actually run slower on the downhill Boston course relative to the flat Berlin course. Perhaps this suggests a fundamental difference between the average runner and an elite runner when running uphill or downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from your individual fitness, the current weather and course itself does play a role in the finishing times. The ideal race temperature for when you're hoping to achieve a new personal best probably should be below 60 degrees. The fastest courses should also be those with the most downhill. However, with more data attributing other variables such as wind, splits and heart rate, we can find more specific relationships. But besides that, the next time you want to run a fast time, hope for a cool day and pick a downhill marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: FindMyMarathon&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Donald Chung</name></author><summary type="html">On October 12, 2019, it was still early morning as the world watched as Elliot Kipchoge put one foot in front of another, gracefully passing the finish line and becoming the first person ever to run a marathon in under two hours. He finished in a blistering fast time of 1:59:40.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Modern Fullback</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ModernFullback" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Modern Fullback" /><published>2020-01-14T17:01:27-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-14T17:01:27-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ModernFullback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ModernFullback">&lt;p&gt;When one hears the word defender, what comes to one's mind? A defender's main job is to prevent the opposition from scoring and stays back while the rest of the team attacks. Straightforward, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern fullback is way more than just a defender. Their duties and expectations have evolved as the game has changed over these past decades. Earlier, their main duties were to prevent opposition wingers from giving crosses, supporting the centre backs while defending and maintaining a good defensive shape. Fullbacks were famed by their defensive qualities and many greats such as Zanetti and Petit are still known for it. However, modern day fullbacks have to do all this and much more. They are now a vital cog to the team's attacking play, putting more emphasis on controlling the game in the attacking third and helping in the team's build up play. It is almost weird that sometimes their defensive duties become their second priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though there have been teams since the early 1950s who have been known for their attacking fullbacks, their importance and abundance has only grown in the past few years. One manager who was vital throughout this revolution was Pep Guardiola.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola has been a key figure for the tactical transformations which have happened in the past decade: one of them being the inverted fullback. He introduced this unconventional idea to the world with Dani Alves during his time at Barcelona and carried it on when he moved on to Bayern Munich. An inverted fullback is a fullback who essentially becomes a central midfielder during the team's build up play. David Alaba and Philipp Lahm flourished in this position and were vital to Bayern's domestic success. Seeing this, many of the top teams followed suite. In the coming years every top team in Europe has placed immense importance on fullbacks and has employed the role of an inverted full back to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This immense importance on fullbacks can clearly be seen in the recent years transfer market history.  Five of the eleven most expensive fullbacks were signed in the summer of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several teams have realized the important value of fullbacks and are ready to pay huge fees to acquire them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I talk about the modern fullback, I can think of 4 types of full backs which are commonly found in different tactical set-ups around the world. The most common one is the overlapping fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Overlapping fullback&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sport has become more tactically fluid over the past few years. Fullbacks started finding more opportunities to burst forward while wingers moved inwards to help create a numerical advantage against opposition defense. And, as the prominence of these narrow wingers grew, so did the presence and abundance of the overlapping fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overlapping fullback in the most simple words is the fullback who is continuously running back and forth, assisting in build up play and providing defensive cover every time the ball is lost. Hence, what this role requires most importantly is high fitness levels and a high level of athleticism. This is rare. A lot of players who attempt to play this role get defensively exposed as they cannot make it back in time to help with defense. This can lead to errors, goals, rash fouls and red cards too. But, if individuals are trained and taught correctly, the manager will be blessed with game-changing fullbacks. Two of the best overlapping fullbacks in the game play in the same team, under Jurgen Klopp; the iconic duo of Andrew Robertson and Trent Alexander Arnold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: David Rawcliffe&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking several records last season, notching 11 and 12 assists respectively, these two embody the role of an overlapping fullback and highlight a fullback's massive importance. Andrew Robertson, being the more defensively sound of the two, is an especially good example of what it really means to be an overlapping fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What one can see for Andrew Robertson and to some extent for Trent Alexander Arnold is a great balance between attacking and defensive output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Flanagan's statistics have also been added here to show the evolution of the game. Jon Flanagan, an ex-Liverpool right back, had mainly defensive duties and contributed barely anything to the team's attacking play. The very same position is now used by Trent Alexander Arnold, who under Jurgen Klopp's management has become one of the best attacking right backs in the game of football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is Liverpool's passing map for a game they played vs Watford last season. One can see how high Andrew Robertson and Trent Alexander are placed on the pitch. The size of the circles around them also shows how involved they were in the game. The more red the circle the higher their xG (Expected Goals) is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordi Alba is another example. An essential part to Barcelona's build up play is Jordi Alba's link up play with Lionel Messi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left back ended last season with 2 goals and 8 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another type of overlapping fullback is Aaron Wan Bissaka who gained fame last season and has now secured a $65 million move to Manchester United. Wan Bissaka, even though he notched up only 3 assists last season, put in eye-catching performances throughout last season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wan Bissaka managed to get a lot of defensive work done and also played an important role in dribbling and moving the ball forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not all teams are gifted with such amazing fullbacks who can contribute on both ends of the pitch. To prevent getting exposed when the fullbacks move up the pitch, teams have only one fullback join the attack at a particular time. But, more commonly the defensive midfielder moves in to a defensive role while the fullbacks move up, as seen with Fabinho or Milner at Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Inverted fullback&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guardiola's creation. When Pep moved to Bayern he realized the qualities of the world class wingers, Robben and Ribery, didn't quite match what he was gifted with at Barcelona. Robben and Ribery were not natural narrow wingers, like Messi and Pedro at Barcelona. They liked starting wide and then cutting inside to create more chances. Their starting wide, obviously limits the space for fullbacks to bomb up the pitch. Thus it made sense to have the fullbacks take up narrower positions and help the team structure in other ways.  Crucially, this allowed them to fill the gaps in midfield helped prevent counter attacks from sides that defended deep, possibly the only weakness of Guardiola's Barcelona team. Pep has used several of his fullbacks in different variations of this role; Alaba, Lahm, Delph, Walker and Zinchenko are few prominent names in recent years.Several other managers have also developed and use some amazing inverted fullbacks. Players like Joshua Kimmich and Alex Sandro are world renowned fullbacks in their roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle Walker's heatmap at Tottenham Hotspur:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle Walker's heatmap at Manchester City:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in Walker's heatmaps before and after his move to Manchester City, he has played more centrally. Playing centrally allowed Manchester City's wingers to take up wider, more natural roles and flourish. Occupying this more central position thus allowed central midfielders David Silva and Kevin De Bruyne to push higher up the pitch and create more and more chances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Independent.ie&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Wingbacks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though these players aren't directly counted as fullbacks, many of the players who play in this role are fullbacks. Essentially wingbacks are found in 3 at the back formations (3-4-3, 3-5-2, 3-1-4-2, etc). Wingbacks are very attack minded fullbacks with reduced defensive duties. Using wingbacks allows team to have a more fluid structure and transition quickly between defense and attack. The perfect example of the impact of wingbacks were Chelsea's dynamic duo of Marcos Alonso and Victor Moses in the 16/17 season. The two were crucial to Chelsea's emphatic title win in Premier League.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consistently bombing forward, Alonso and Moses notched up some amazing numbers for a defender. Alonso ended the season with 6 goals and 3 assists while, Moses ended up with 3 goals and 2 assists. But this isn't all. Consistently going up the pitch, they provided an extra option to Chelsea's midfielders to play diagonal balls to. They created 2 v 1s versus the opposition fullback and made it that much tougher to defend and stop goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clip below highlights how Marcos Alonso's movement frees up space and allows the midfielders to play in diagonal balls to open up tight defenses :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9nffHeS_RfQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another team which uses its wingbacks very wisely is Wolverhampton Wanderers. After being promoted in the 18/19 season, they shocked a lot of viewers and teams not only with their counter attacking style of football but, also their defensive solidarity. Surpassing all expectations, they managed to finish 7th in the league and got into the Europa League. One player who played a key role was Matt Doherty. The right wing back was not only good defensively but was a vital cog in the attacking play. He ended the season with 4 goals and 5 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_13.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Independent.ie&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Defensive Fullback&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside the top tier of European teams, this is probably the most common type of fullback found. Teams need to concentrate on defending to stay alive in the league and to not be destroyed by the stronger teams. By doing so they give up on fluid, quick, attacking football and hence they do not need fullbacks who focus too much on going forward. Take a team such as Burnley for example. They are a defensive team with their attacking output mainly making use of long balls, aerials and the players' sheer physicality. This is their fullback, Phil Bardsley:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being able to do basic defensive tasks such as dominating in the air are also useful, so it's not shocking that all the radar shows him doing is winning aerial duels and not giving the ball away. If Burnley were to try and do anything more direct and attacking, Bardsley would be continually exposed, but as it is, he does what is required of him and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_14.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 14&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few more numbers which show the evolution of a fullback in the game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_15.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 15&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
	
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_16.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 16&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
	
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_17.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 17&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fullback position has evolved so much in the past few years it is actually impossible to define the role of a modern fullback. It largely depends on how defensive, attacking, fluid, direct, counter-attacking or possession- based a team wants to play. And they are ready to splash out big money to get the correct fullback to meet their tactical preference. But, this is potentially the same for any position on the pitch, highlighting not only the importance of the modern fullback but the evolution of the entire game of soccer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: Statsbomb, Sofascore, The Guardian.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishaan Shah</name></author><summary type="html">The modern fullback is way more than just a defender. Their duties and expectations have evolved as the game has changed over these past decades. Earlier, their main duties were to prevent opposition wingers from giving crosses, supporting the centre backs while defending and maintaining a good defensive shape. Fullbacks were famed by their defensive qualities and many greats such as Zanetti and Petit are still known for it. However, modern day fullbacks have to do all this and much more. They are now a vital cog to the team's attacking play, putting more emphasis on controlling the game in the attacking third and helping in the team's build up play. It is almost weird that sometimes their defensive duties become their second priority.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Evolution of the Free Throw</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/BSA_Writeup_The_Free_Throw" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Evolution of the Free Throw" /><published>2020-01-06T20:57:40-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-06T20:57:40-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/BSA_Writeup_The_Free_Throw</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/BSA_Writeup_The_Free_Throw">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/shaq_freethrow.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From Wikimedia&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Free Throw: the only shot in basketball that is theoretically free, but players continue to show that it's more difficult than it originally appears. In the early 2000's, the idea of &quot;hack-a-shaq&quot; was introduced. This strategy had players intentionally foul poor free throw shooters, such as Shaquille O'Neal to send them to the charity line. The hope: at least one missed free throw, and an opportunity to seize possession once more. However, as this strategy became popular, teams sent their poor foul shooters to the bench at late moments in a game. Fast forward to 2015: Stephen Curry became the eighth player to join the 50/40/90 club (50% field goal, 40% three-point, 90% free throw), and many shooters began to score at an all-time high rate. With shooting success becoming fundamental to an increasingly offensive game, we thought it would be interesting to look at how the free throw differs from years, stars, position, and three-point shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;PROCEDURE&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To evaluate and compare how the free throw differs from years, stars, position, and three-point shooting, we decided to look at the evolution of the free-throw percentage over two different three-year spans separated by nearly 20 years (2000-2003 and 2016-2019). The question: were players getting better at shooting percentages or was there simply a higher volume of shots and, importantly, how does that relate to the free throw? We compared each individual year of the three-year spans to one another, in order to get an idea of what year-to-year variation in shooting looked like. Next, we compared the two decades with one another to see how the game was truly changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, however, Stephen Curry and Shaquille O'Neal are very different players and should not be compared directly with each other--and thus should be categorized as such. To accommodate for this, we created groups in accordance with the main player's position (e.g. center, point guard).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we thought it would be worthwhile to delineate between the Matthew Dellavedova's of the world and the Lebron James' of the world--those that are high scoring versus those that are not. To do so, we looked at the variation between &quot;stars&quot; (defined as top 20 in points or top 10 in rebounds or top 10 in assists) versus the variation in non-&quot;stars&quot; (people who are not in any of the above categories).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From si.wsj.net&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During garbage time, the trailing team can sometimes rack up an unusually high tally of statistics, leading the respective box score to be misleading with respect to their actual game performance. To limit the players we are analyzing, we added the following caveats to exclude garbage time players: a player must play at least 20 games, average at least 10 minutes per game, have a minimum of one free throw attempt per game, and strictly shoot more than 0.5 three point attempts per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;OUR PREDICTIONS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, especially because of the &quot;hack-a-shaq&quot; era of the early 2000s, we anticipated a large discrepancy in the free throw percentage by position; we expected guards to have the highest percentage (~85%), followed by forward (~75%), and lastly centers (~65%). Furthermore, it seemed reasonable to conclude that if players shoot the three-point shot at a higher rate and percentage, then hopefully, those same players would spend equal time practicing the one shot they should be guaranteed to make every time: the free throw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we believe that non-stars will have less variation in free throw percentage, as stars don't need to focus on the free throw, given their tremendous impact to other facets of the game. Non-stars, however, have less room for error--and should practice, seize, and execute at an opportunity of free points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;DATA&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before crunching numbers, we noticed an interesting trend in the amount of players who qualified for our study over the years. For example, whereas the average number of centers who met our shooting qualification (as defined above) in the 2000's was 5.67, the average number of centers for the 2010's was 29.67. Likely, this can be attributed to centers shooting the three point shot more often as time went on, and thus, more qualified under the &quot;3PTA &gt; 0.5&quot; requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variation in the year-to-year data within the early 2000s--the first of two time periods in this article--remained relatively low, with the greatest variation across the three years occurring at the forward position, but it was still within 1% (76.88% to 77.72%). The data from the early 2000s also emphasizes the general trend which we expected, specifically, that centers had the lowest free throw percent (hovering around 74%), followed by forwards (~77%), and guards with the highest (~79.5%). Although the data did not have the percentages which we expected at the outset of the investigation, there was still a delineation between each position. Further, since the variability between these individual years remained low, any difference between these years and the decades could be attributed to a difference across basketball eras as opposed to the accumulation of annual differences; each position had a dip in free throw percentage either in the 2001-2002 season or the 2002-2003 season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the tail end of the 2010s--the second of two time frames studied in this article--the data appears murkier when comparing the positions. In terms of variation by year, each position still remained relatively steady with the largest range of ~3% occurring at the guard position (81.11% vs. 78.08%). Although the variation did increase--as shown through the higher standard deviations--the data remained constant enough to compare this time frame to that of the early 2000s to look for the desired change in free throw percentage, at least by position. The aspect of this table which surprised us was the free throw percentage of centers compared to forwards, as they were approximately equal, with centers having a slight edge, not forwards; the guards had a higher percentage than the other two groups but by less than earlier in the NBA's history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2000's v. 2010's:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To concatenate the data for the two basic time periods: 2000s and 2010s, we took an average of the three year periods we originally studied, for each decade period. This combined data is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data highlights the surprising lack of difference within each of the three positions from the early 2000s time frame to the late 2010s. In the 2000s, at least, the data appeared exactly how we expected: centers, then forwards, then guards, albeit at a lesser degree than what we anticipated; there was only a 2% difference when grouping by position as opposed to our expected 10% difference. However, in the 2010s, the data paint a distinctly different story, as the centers increased their free throw percentage, while guards and forwards actually had a decrease in their free throw percentages as a position group, making their free throw percentages all occur within a 3% range. Furthermore, the players during the 2010 era exhibited greater variation, as their standard deviations increased by about 1.5 percentage points: thus, players in today's NBA occur across a broader range of the spectrum, as there are some elite free throw shooters (e.g. Steph Curry, James Harden), but also some horrendous ones (e.g. Lonzo Ball).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;STARS v. NONSTARS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From NYDailyNews&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data shows that the stars in the NBA have a higher free throw percentage by a margin of almost 2% in both decades. Likewise, in both decades, the standard deviation for stars is less by a notable margin of at least 0.5%. Unexpectedly, both the free throw percentage of stars and nonstars went down by a factor of at least 0.5% from the 2000s to the 2010s. Moreover, shooters in the 2000's were much more consistent, as demonstrated by an increase of 1% in standard deviations from the players in the 2000s to 2010's.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;THREE POINT CORRELATION&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was our hypothesis that there would be a correlation between three point percentages and free throw percentages.  To show this correlation, we created graphs conveying each player as a dot, placed according to his free throw and three-point percentage. Additionally, we have created a line of best fit, showing the general trend for each decade in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2000's exemplify consistency. The line of best fit shoots a free throw possession from around 73% to up to around 82%. Additionally, there is a large clump of players all in the same spot. With few outliers, the data leads to the conclusion that the 2000's was very consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010's are much more turbulent. This can likely be attributed to higher shooting volume. Here, the line of best fit for free throw percentage spans from as low as 60% to as high as 87%. This is a much different range than in the 2000's where the deviation is 9 points as opposed to the 2010's where the deviation is 27 points. Additionally, there are more outliers than the 2000's, as well as a generally larger clump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From NBC Pro Basketball Talk&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We overlaid the graphs, as shown below, to get a visual of what the two decades looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2000's seem more consistent, as the line of best fit seems to go from around 74% to up to 85%. However, as shooting as increased over the decades, the 2010's graph shows a different story. Not only are there more points in the 2010's--due to higher shooting volume--there is also more inconsistency. At the top end, in the 2010's, shooters have higher three-point-to-free-throw percentage ratio, such as Lonzo Ball. While the visual is an eye sore, it shows the correlation and development over the years; the game has progressed such that there is a higher volume of shooters, but with the increase in volume there is a much higher variance in percentages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From i.pinimg.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our data paint a picture that is in stark contrast to our initial expectations. No single position has completely distanced itself from the other two in terms of free throw percentage; in fact, in today's game there is less of a difference in free throw percentage amongst different positions than there was in the 2000s. More variability in our data also emphasizes that, although we have better players at the line today, we also have worse ones. The average for guards and forwards decreased between the two time frames, while centers had an increase. These results lead us to question the &quot;hack-a-Shaq&quot; method which has become so renowned -- the fouling of big men in crunch time. Perhaps centers have responded to that method of &quot;bullying&quot; by bolstering their free throw percentage, especially when compared with players at other positions. Maybe the adage should simply be revised, as free throw percentage is not as position-dependent as it seems on TV. Maybe the adage for today's NBA should not be &quot;hack-a-Shaq.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it should be &quot;hack-a-Lonzo.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: NBA (NBA.com), ESPN (espn.com)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ethan Allavarpu</name></author><summary type="html">The Free Throw. the only shot in basketball that is theoretically free, but players continue to show that it's more difficult than it originally appears. In the early 2000's, the idea of &quot;hack-a-shaq&quot; was introduced. This strategy had players intentionally foul poor free throw shooters, such as Shaquille O'Neal to send them to the charity line. The hope. at least one missed free throw, and an opportunity to seize possession once more. However, as this strategy became popular, teams sent their poor foul shooters to the bench at late moments in a game. Fast forward to 2015. Stephen Curry became the eighth player to join the 50/40/90 club (50% field goal, 40% three-point, 90% free throw), and many shooters began to score at an all-time high rate. With shooting success becoming fundamental to an increasingly offensive game, we thought it would be interesting to look at how the free throw differs from years, stars, position, and three-point shooting.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Maximize Your Investment in Top Sports Stocks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/TopSportsStocks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Maximize Your Investment in Top Sports Stocks" /><published>2019-07-19T11:37:50-07:00</published><updated>2019-07-19T11:37:50-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/TopSportsStocks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/TopSportsStocks">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sportsstock/pic_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Under Armour&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, Nike became the official uniform and footwear supplier of Major League Baseball (MLB). This means that Nike now dominates three of the four major professional sports leagues within the U.S.: MLB, NBA, and NFL. When I learned that Nike had secured its third major deal, I was curious about its recent stock performance. Using portfolio analysis and optimization techniques, my goal was to create an efficient sports stocks portfolio. For those who are unfamiliar with portfolio analysis, a portfolio is essentially a group of assets. The assets, or stocks, that I included in my analysis were: Nike (NKE), Under Armour (UAA), Disney (DIS), Adidas (ADDYY), and Foot Locker (FL).  Identifying the most efficient portfolio is an optimization problem, and there are two main objectives involved. The first is to select a portfolio that yields high returns, whereas the second is to assure that these returns are stable. For this reason, my goal is to determine which combination of sports assets will yield minimum risk and high expected return. The data is composed of monthly adjusted close prices, which are adjusted for dividends paid or stock splits. It ranges from May 2013 to May 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though Nike secured its NFL deal in April of 2012, I chose to begin with 2013 data because another rather interesting deal occurred this year: Steph Curry signed a $4 million per year deal with Under Armour. Compared to other major shoe deals, such as Lebron James's $90 million Nike deal when he was first drafted from high school, Curry's contract seems highly insignificant. When Nike first attempted to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/15047018/how-nike-lost-stephen-curry-armour&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1563565539073000&quot;&gt;extend their initial endorsement deal&lt;/a&gt; with Curry, they not only mispronounced his name during the pitch, but also forgot to remove Kevin Durant's name from a pivotal slide. The Swoosh would not back down from its $2.5 million deal, and refused to match Under Armour's offer. For this reason, Steph Curry decided to partner with Under Armour, and it has proven to be vastly successful. In fact, the Curry One grossed $153 million within its first three months on the market. I can imagine that after three NBA championships, two NBA MVP awards, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.businessinsider.com/steph-curry-worth-14-billion-to-under-armour-2016-3&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1563565539074000&quot;&gt;being worth approximately $14 billion to Under Armour&lt;/a&gt;, Nike must have some major regrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the missed opportunity, Nike's stocks are still doing well. This comes as no surprise considering that Nike not only supplies the MLB, NBA, and NFL uniforms, but also dominantes the sports market due to major endorsements from Lebron James, Kevin Durant, and Michael Jordan. In 2015, James extended his initial $90 million contract and the deal could be worth approximately $1 billion in the near future. Durant also secured a ten year extension to his initial contract, which was a seven year, $60 million deal, and the new contract could be worth a whopping $300 million. Then, there is Michael Jordan who is in a league of his own. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.businessinsider.com/how-michael-jordan-spends-his-money-2015-3%23nike-founder-phil-knight-called-signing-jordan-the-best-decision-he-ever-made-nabbing-the-nba-rookie-for-250000-a-year-in-1984-11&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1563565539075000&quot;&gt;Business Insider&lt;/a&gt;, the Jordan brand generates more than $3 billion per year. Of this net revenue, Jordan pockets approximately $110 million. Evidently, the Swoosh and its ambassadors remain vastly successful. In the graph directly below, the Nike stock is the optimal pick. Although Adidas has the highest expected value, the Nike stock has both low risk and high returns. Within the last six years, the Foot Locker sports stock actually demonstrates the worst performance. It has the highest risk, and the lowest expected value of the five sports stocks. In fact, Foot Locker's earnings have recently declined by approximately 20% since the last official report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sportsstock/pic_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Nike's stock performance has been impressive over the past six years, I would strongly advise against investing all of your money in the Swoosh. When Zion Willamson's Nike shoe tore apart within the first minute of the Duke v. North Carolina match and resulted in a knee-sprain injury, the Nike stock plummeted by approximately $1.1 billion. Due to unpredictable incidents and stock market variability, it is vital that investors create a strategically diversified portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Portfolio Possibilities Curve, which is located directly below, is the first step towards identifying an efficient portfolio consisting of the top five sports stocks. An investor could hypothetically invest anywhere along the curve because it is constructed using several different combinations of the five sports stocks. The graph also exemplifies the performance of the five sports stocks, the minimum risk portfolio, and the efficient frontier. The five points furthest to the right are the sports stocks, whereas the triangular point is the minimum risk portfolio. The purpose of the minimum risk portfolio is to determine which combination of stocks yields the lowest risk. In other words, let's say that you have $1,000,000 to invest in the five sports stocks. The minimum risk portfolio divides your $1,000,000 investment into each respective stock at the lowest possible risk. The efficient frontier begins at the minimum risk portfolio and extends to the maximum expected return. It is the upper half, or concave portion, of the portfolio possibilities curve. As you travel along the efficient frontier, both the expected return and risk increase. Because the risk increases significantly, it might be best to play it safe and invest in the minimum risk portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, however, the decision lies in the hands of the investor. Investing further along the efficient frontier may result in a higher expected return. For instance, a risk of 0.10 is projected to result in an expected return of approximately 0.25, which is greater than the minimum risk portfolio's return. However, the associated risk severely increases. When seeking the optimal portfolio, it is important that investors maintain low risk in order to maximize their investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sportsstock/pic_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rather than investing in the minimum risk portfolio, there is also the possibility of investing in the portfolio that is tangent to the line on the efficient frontier. In the graph below, I have created several portfolios using various combinations of the five sports stocks. These portfolios are indicated by the black points. The large green points are the five sports stocks, and the large blue point is the tangent point. It is advantageous for an investor to invest his money in the point that is tangent to the efficient frontier because it signifies slightly higher risk for an even greater expected return. The tangent point divides the investment as follows: 22.04% is invested into Disney, 5.29% into Under Armour, 45.99% into Nike, 29.81% into Adidas, and -3.14% into Foot Locker. The model that my data is based on allows for riskless lending and borrowing, which is why my investment into Foot Locker is negative. In other words, 3.14% is borrowed from the Foot Locker stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sportsstock/pic_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The likelihood of receiving a $90 million endorsement from powerhouses like Nike or Under Armour is slim. Nevertheless, using portfolio analysis, the average person can create a strong portfolio and obtain a solid return. In regards to the five sports stocks, I would argue that the most efficient portfolio lies tangent to the efficient frontier. Investing the majority of your money into the Swoosh's stock appears to be the most efficient method.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Breanna Ramos</name></author><summary type="html">Earlier this year, Nike became the official uniform and footwear supplier of Major League Baseball (MLB). This means that Nike now dominates three of the four major professional sports leagues within the U.S.&amp;#58; MLB, NBA, and NFL. When I learned that Nike had secured its third major deal, I was curious about its recent stock performance. Using portfolio analysis and optimization techniques, my goal was to create an efficient sports stocks portfolio. For those who are unfamiliar with portfolio analysis, a portfolio is essentially a group of assets. The assets, or stocks, that I included in my analysis were &amp;#58; Nike (NKE), Under Armour (UAA), Disney (DIS), Adidas (ADDYY), and Foot Locker (FL). Identifying the most efficient portfolio is an optimization problem, and there are two main objectives involved. The first is to select a portfolio that yields high returns, whereas the second is to assure that these returns are stable. For this reason, my goal is to determine which combination of sports assets will yield minimum risk and high expected return. The data is composed of monthly adjusted close prices, which are adjusted for dividends paid or stock splits. It ranges from May 2013 to May 2019.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How the Sharks’ Versatility Led them to the Conference Finals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/KnightsvsSharksBrainstorm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How the Sharks’ Versatility Led them to the Conference Finals" /><published>2019-05-29T20:17:32-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-29T20:17:32-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/KnightsvsSharksBrainstorm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/KnightsvsSharksBrainstorm">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;AP Photo/Jeff Chiu&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the thrills of watching playoff hockey is the emotional aspect, following a team through several games against the same opponent with everything on the line, and an especially close series makes the thrill even higher. The San Jose Sharks playing the Vegas Golden Knights in the first series of the playoffs was notable for its excitement, intensity, and controversy. The series was highly anticipated as a rematch of the previous year's second round, where the Knights won in six games. This time around, the Sharks were a much improved team, adding key players Erik Karlsson and Gustav Nyquist, while Vegas had more-or-less kept the same lineup as the previous year's Stanley Cup Final-bound team, with the notable addition of top line forward Mark Stone. The Golden Knights took early control of the series, finishing Game 4 with a 3-1 lead in games won. The Sharks managed to battle back, scoring a miraculous overtime goal in Game 6 to force a deciding game in San Jose. A close, hard-fought series was expected on the outset, but the conclusion shocked everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Game 7 versus the Golden Knights with just over ten minutes remaining in the third period, the Sharks were trailing the Knights 3-0. However, the referees made a controversial call when Pavelski was crosschecked by Cody Eakin, and Eakin subsequently received a five minute misconduct and crosschecking penalty for this offense. Though it would have been justifiable  for Eakin to receive a two minute minor penalty, many argue that a five minute major penalty was too harsh of a punishment. Pavelski did get injured by Eakin on the hit after falling awkwardly, making the situation look quite severe, but some argue that the hit itself was not worthy of a major penalty. To add insult to injury for the Knights, the Sharks scored four goals within a span of four minutes while on the power play. The call was already controversial, and since it was a major penalty, the power play did not stop when just one goal is scored. Golden Knights fans were clearly not pleased with this, losing their 3-0 lead in four minutes in the third period. Clearly, if this call were not made, chances are the Knights would have held onto the lead to win the series, but nonetheless, the Sharks capitalized on this call and went on to win the game and series in overtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_2.gif&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bYGPnFccbMk&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes the NHL playoffs so interesting, compared to the regular season, is the immense potential for adaptation over the course of a series. Overall team parity is often brought up as both a positive and negative about the league. The playoffs are unpredictable. Any team could realistically beat any other team--the recent Lightning-Blue Jackets series is a prime example. Unpredictability, however, simply a product of the role of luck in deciding a series. This is not to suggest that luck (which is really better described as random variability) is absent in the on-ice product of the NHL, or that luck is even something to be avoided in a well-designed sport. What it does suggest is that the NHL regular season is not a good predictor of playoff success because the regular season is more-or-less a completely different game. The constant variation of opposition forces teams to generally run one system that they hope would maximize their point total; i.e. the system that works the best against the most teams. In the playoffs, when a team is pitted against another seven times over the course of two weeks, teams can adjust their system to be tailored entirely to its single opponent. Perhaps more importantly, if something doesn't go as planned, the team can adapt in between games. This system of adaptation goes beyond the players, whose individual contributions toward change may be hard to quantify or even describe for an onlooker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge decider in this pivotal Sharks and Golden Knights first round playoff series was the evolving goaltending, more notably on San Jose's side. After a strong performance in Game 1, Sharks goalie Martin Jones took quite the tumble as he was even pulled from Game 2 after just under seven minutes of time on the ice. Jones continued to struggle through Game 3 and Game 4 until the Sharks faced elimination in Game 5. As the Sharks' season seemed to be over, Jones finally executed a playoff worthy performance and he carried that determination through the end of Game 7 to lift San Jose over Vegas and into the second round. However, there is still the question of how exactly did Jones break his pattern of disappointing starts to give the Sharks the ultimate edge over the Golden Knights. We'll look at the quality of shots Jones faced and the quality of goals he allowed to examine whether the Sharks' goaltender actually changed his play or if Vegas' shooters simply gave him an easier time in the later games of the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the regular season, both Jones and Vegas' Marc-Andre Fleury eked out below average performances. However, while Fleury could be considered a mediocre goalie on the season, Jones was remarkably terrible. The Sharks' goaltender had a GSAA of -23.35 over 62 games played, meaning he allowed over 23 more goals than the average NHL goalie would have. The fact that the Sharks still finished the season with over 100 points despite Jones' abysmal performance attests to the outstanding season by the rest of the men on their roster. However, throughout the 2018-2019 season, Martin Jones faced the fourth most high danger shots of any goalie in the league with 525. The danger of a shot is measured by where it is shot from on the ice, and thus, by how much reaction time a goalie will have in order to make the save. A high danger shot will have almost no time for a goalie to get in place to make a save while a goalie should have plenty of time to set up for a low danger shot. Many hockey fanatics familiar with advanced metrics in the sport argue that what separates an elite goalie in the NHL from the average goaltender is their ability to save high danger shots. I would also argue that teams with great defenses would not allow their opponents to take many high danger shots. We all know that it is impossible to call Martin Jones an elite goalie based on his performance this season, but there is no denying that his defense is partially to blame too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This detrimental pattern of the Sharks allowing their opponents to take high and medium danger shots undoubtedly continued into the first round of this year's playoffs. Let's start with Game 1, where the Sharks actually had a decent start to the series, winning 5-2 at home. Jones had a solid SV% of 0.923 and he saved nine of ten high danger shots faced. The only other goal he allowed was off of a medium danger shot during a Sharks' penalty kill. In this game, Jones only allowed two goals compared to an expected goals against of 3.19, so a rather solid performance. However, this stability would not last into Game 2 of the series where things went downhill fast for the San Jose goaltender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first 6:39 minutes of play in Game 2, Jones allowed an astonishing three goals with only .5 expected goals against. He allowed one of each high, medium, and low danger goals after facing only seven shots. We know Jones is no elite goalie as of recent, yet allowing a low danger shot to find its way into the net is a bad look in the playoffs. Even though Jones was fourth in the league for low danger goals allowed with a whopping 30 goals, there is no exception for that kind of play in the postseason. Continuing into Game 3, Jones' performance did not improve as he allowed six goals in his full 60 minutes of ice time. Of these six goals, five were scored from high danger shots and one from a medium danger shot. Almost half of the Golden Knights' 40 shots were high danger shots, and knowing Jones' lackluster performance as of late, the Sharks' defense shouldn't have let Vegas take those 17 chances to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game 4 in Vegas looked like the end of the road for the Sharks who lost 0-5. Martin Jones and backup Aaron Dell split time on the ice for San Jose but neither ever found their groove. All three of Aaron Dell's goals allowed came from high danger shots while Jones gave up a high danger and even a low danger shot to the Knights. Even though the two goaltenders allowed five goals, they received no help from the rest of the roster as Fleury had a shutout night. At this point in the series, the Sharks either had to make drastic changes to their play or it was Vegas' series to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the next three games, I would argue that is was a combination of less effort by the Knights and a fire burning for redemption in Martin Jones that allowed the Sharks to bounce back from almost certain death. As the series moved back to San Jose for Game 5, the only two goals Jones allowed were during a Knights power play. He allowed no goals on 28 shots during 5-on-5 play and had an overall SV% of .938. Of course one of the goals Jones allowed was off of a low danger shot, but it is a little more forgivable once your offensive line steps up and gives you a nice cushioned lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the final two games of the series were much closer in score and heightened in drama as both went into overtime. During Game 6, Martin Jones had over 90 minutes of ice time and allowed only one goal on 59 shots. Although Vegas' single goal of the night came on a high danger shot, the Knights took a series high 33 low danger shots compared to only nine high danger and eleven medium danger chances. This could be attributed to better Sharks defensive play but there is no doubt that Vegas' poor quality chances did not help them close out the series that night as they lost just 2 to 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game 7 featured a typical Jones performance with a SV% of .895, allowing two high danger and two medium danger goals. Yet what made the difference that night was not San Jose's goalie, but the powerplay prowess for the Sharks as Fleury gave up four of his five goals on the Knights penalty kill. Although Jones returned to his regular season self, the Sharks were still able to pull off the upset in overtime play with a tremendous offensive effort. San Jose finally found a balance between relying on Jones' goaltending and relying on their forwards' abilities and consistently adapted to ultimately come out on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coaches Peter DeBoer and Gerard Gallant exemplified this form of shifting strategies throughout their series. The nature of lines and the distribution of ice time found in hockey provides coaches the capability to completely change their approach from game to game. It cannot be stressed enough: these approaches were vastly different for the two teams in virtually every facet of the game. DeBoer and the Sharks were aggressive in their bench management, making sweeping changes to their lines and player usage in just about every game. Gustav Nyquist played on the first, second, and fourth line depending on the game in the series. Joakim Ryan's ice time varied between playing 5% of Game 1 to playing 30% of Game 3. At least one of the Sharks power play lines was tweaked prior to every game. The Golden Knights, on the other hand, were much more systematic with their approach to change. Their line combinations went nearly untouched - a Game 2 substitution of their 6th defenseman and a Game 7 return of Brandon Pirri are the only exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Rolling four lines&quot; is an oft-cited goal for many teams, but perhaps none exemplified this strategy more than Vegas, particularly in Games 3 and 5. It is almost cliche to bring up this point about the Knights, but it was utilized to such an extreme level in these games that it cannot go without discussion. In Game 3, the five most-worked of Vegas' defensemen played within three minutes of ice-time of each other. Their eight most-worked forwards played within two minutes of each other. Compare this with the over-seven minute difference between the Sharks' five most-played defensemen and five minute difference for the Sharks' top-eight forwards. Also distinguishing itself from the Sharks is Vegas' first power-play unit, which featured the exact same five players in all seven games of the series. This only further shows off how differently the two teams were comprised. Both teams have significant depth through their lineups, of course, but San Jose is a team made up of bona-fide stars (Erik Karlsson, Brent Burns, Joe Pavelski, etc.) while Vegas is noteworthy in their collection of very good players that are not in the public eye as often (Paul Stastny, Reilly Smith, Jonathan Marchessault, etc.). While the Sharks were able to dynamically go after specific matchups that varied from game to game, the Knights were more comfortable staying true to their philosophy of lineup consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partially due to playing most of the series from a deficit, San Jose was much more willing to try out new strategies than Vegas. The top line in particular is noteworthy. After a heartbreaking Game 2 loss in which the top line of Evander Kane, Tomas Hertl, and Gustav Nyquist got largely outplayed, the Sharks shifted Hertl's position from center to left wing, and replaced Nyquist's role with Joe Pavelski for Game 3. This game ended in a rout for the Knights, so the Sharks shifted again: this time bringing Hertl back to center and placing Joonas Donskoi on his wing. This, too, ended poorly for San Jose, so for Game 5, they went back to their lines from the first game. On defense, Marc-Edouard Vlasic's Game 2 injury led to significant issues for the Sharks. Vlasic, who typically plays about 40% of every game and is known for his defense-first gameplay, missed the majority of Game 2 and the entirety of Games 3 and 4. His role on the team was partially replaced by Joakim Ryan, who went from playing three minutes of Game 1 to playing nearly 20 minutes each game in Vlasic's absence. Though certainly far from the sole reason, Vlasic's absence from Games 2-4 corresponds exactly to the games Vegas won. His defense was surely missed, as these were also the only games Vegas scored five or more goals in. San Jose was also constantly innovative on the power play. The Sharks' top power play unit saw five different lineups over the seven games. Logan Couture and Tomas Hertl were the only constants on the line. The desire to try new strategies ultimately paid off, as Timo Meier was added to the top line for the first time of the series for Game 7, in which a late major penalty swung momentum heavily in the Sharks favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the overall lack of combination changes from the Golden Knights, the way they utilized individual players did shift in rather interesting ways as the series went on. For the purpose of this analysis, ice-time for players will be measured in percent of game played rather than their raw number of minutes played due to Games 6 and 7 going to overtime (and double overtime). As a general rule, a forward that plays 30% of the game is one that is relied on fairly heavily, as is a defenseman that plays 40% of the game. The bulk of the Knights' ice-distribution adaptations occurred within their defensive group; however, one notable exception is Cody Eakin. Eakin began the series eating up a modest 23% of ice-time before having his contributions skyrocket for Games 2 and 3 to above 30%. The remainder of the series saw his time decline slowly to near 20%. His bump in ice-time comes after scoring a goal in Game 2; his 5-on-5 play for games after this was fairly strong, boasting 64% unblocked shot attempts for (11.6 percentage points higher than average for his team) when he was in play, yet Gallant opted to utilize him less and less. Overall, however, the forward group showed remarkable consistency in their usage; ironically, it is when the Knights shifted to a more Sharks-esque reliance on top stars late in Game 7 (when Mark Stone played more minutes than any other player, including defensemen, on the team), that they were beaten in overtime by one of San Jose's depth players in Kevin LaBanc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vegas' defensive group contributed to the bulk of Gerard Gallant's tinkering. The lines stayed constant after Game 1, but the amount each line was used varied wildly. Four different defensemen (Theodore, McNabb, Schmidt, and Engelland) had exactly one game in which they played 40% or more. Despite the Knights' trademark lineup consistency, there was a notable lack thereof when it came to their defensemen's time on ice. Vegas relied on a different player to take on the bulk of the work just about every night. Their philosophy in this regard depended on the state of the game. In the three particularly close games (Games 2, 6, and 7), Brayden McNabb saw his minutes skyrocket. His single point in the series hardly stands out as impressive - compared to his typical partner Shea Theodore with eight points - but his controlled, puck-possession style of play gained Gallant's favor in these critical games. Over the seven games, when McNabb was on the ice, the Knights took over 56% of unblocked shot attempts (easily the highest of their four top defensemen); he also finished with a plus-minus of four, the highest on the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McNabb's fluctuation of ice time is a microcosm of Vegas' changes toward the end of the series. The Knights began the series with their trademark quickness, seamlessly transitioning out of the neutral zone and generating quality chances on the rush. In Games 1-4, eight of their nine 5-on-5 goals were scored off rush opportunities. In the last three games, this skillful play vanished. They scored no 5-on-5 goals off transition plays in these games. This dramatic shift is shocking but can be explained by the adaptation of the Sharks and lack thereof from the Knights. Vegas did not change their top three offensive lines once the entire series, and the Sharks, at least in transition, figured out how to subdue them. Yet, more so than the disappearance of speed from Vegas' game, it is special teams failure that can show Gallant's faults. At first glance, this claim seems wildly inaccurate when referring to the power play. The Knights did score seven power play goals in the series, after all. What this does not show is the neglect to adapt to changing defensive strategies. Vegas' top power play unit remained constant in each game, manned by Stone, Pacioretty, Stastny, Theodore, and Tuch. In Games 1-4, they managed a whopping five power play goals from this line alone. Then, they never scored again. Worse, even, the line gave up the Game 6 shorthanded goal in double overtime to lose the game. The penalty kill shows the opposite story. The Sharks scored two goals in Games 1-4 against the Vegas penalty kill. They then scored two more in Games 5 and 6, before Vegas gave one of the worst defensive performances ever against the Sharks late five minute power play in Game 7, costing themselves four goals and ultimately their season. All controversy on this call aside, it is clear that more than just Martin Jones's increased performance is to be blamed for the Golden Knights blowing a 3-1 series lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Sharks won the series against the Knights, they went on to play the Avalanche in another tight and thrilling series, which featured many striking similarities to the first round. Taking a look at how San Jose's performance continued into the second round serves to further highlight their ability to adapt, and it provides grounds for greater appreciation for how they came back to defeat the Knights. Against the Avalanche, continuing to adapt to the unexpected was a must, with two key offensive players, Joe Pavelski and Joonas Donskoi, out for much of the series with injuries. Despite having these assets out of the lineup, DeBoer was able to tinker with lineups and other players were able to step up, keeping the Sharks alive. Similarly to the Knights series, the Avalanche series went out to seven games, with both teams having moments of dominance, looking like either team could proceed to the conference finals. The Sharks ended up coming out on top in Game 7, but not without more controversy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Avalanche series, the Sharks again had some major luck in Game 7. In the second period, the Avalanche scored a goal to equalize the game at two goals each. Though it was seemingly a good goal, the Sharks challenged to review the goal. After review, the referees concluded that the Avalanche forward Gabriel Landeskog who was just finishing his shift was offside, disallowing the goal. Although Landeskog had no involvement in the play and was just about to enter the bench, his skates were still on the ice, making the Avalanche offside. The Sharks maintained momentum after this call, winning the game 3-2 to close out the series. Although both the call versus the Knights and the call versus the Avalanche were considerably justifiable, there is no doubt that these two calls contributed to the success of the Sharks in the otherwise even series. This reinforces the unpredictable and random nature of the playoffs, where one lucky call can determine the winner of the whole series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_8.gif&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4QbgWMNbEow&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another prominent parallel between the Sharks' series against the Golden Knights and the series against the Avalanche is the dominance of two defensemen, Brent Burns and Erik Karlsson. Against the Golden Knights, Brent Burns and Erik Karlsson played an integral role on both the defensive side and offensive side, and this continued into the series versus the Avalanche. DeBoer relied heavily on the two during both series, Burns clocking in a total of 409.58 minutes and Karlsson clocking in 345.15 minutes. Karlsson dealt with a groin injury for most of the year, but he still managed to tally nine points against the Knights and three against the Avalanche. Aside from simply looking at points by player, one way to measure and compare the performances of players is to use the Corsi statistic, which computes the total number of shots for, missed shots for, and blocked shot attempts divided by the total number of shots against, missed shots against, and blocked shot attempts against. The relative Corsi statistic for each player can also be looked at, which takes each players' Corsi statistic and compares it to the rest of the team's Corsi statistic. Out of the top six defensmen on the Sharks, the average relative Corsi statistic during the Knights Series was a -5.86, but Karlsson had a 1.78 relative Corsi statistic. Aside from Burns, Karlsson was the only defenseman with a positive Corsi statistic, showing his dominant possession over the Golden Knights and showing his ability to work as an attacking minded defenseman. Furthermore, during the regular season, Karlsson averaged only .849 points per game, but in the first series of the playoffs, he was averaging 1.286. His veteran status might have given him an edge in the first round against the Knights, but in the succeeding round, his six years of experience in playoff hockey did not give him any leverage, averaging just under half a point. Though Karlsson saw a decrease in points during round two of the playoffs, possibly caused by a flare-up with his groin injury, he still contributed immensely to the Shark's defensive efforts, playing an average 40% of each game while only conceding 1.14 goals against on average per game when on the ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burns, in contrast to Karlsson, started out in the first round with only four points and then dominated in the second round with a total of ten points. In the first game against the Knights, Burns, like Karlsson, started off very effective offensively, tallying a goal and an assist. However, in subsequent games, Burns was less effective due to the fact that the Knights gave him full pressure and little space to attack. Like the rest of the team, Burns was shut down by the Knights, but nonetheless his attacking side started to show in Game 6 and Game 7, earning points in back-to-back games. In the second series, however, Colorado gave Burns much more space to attack, and Burns started to completely dominate offensively. In game one, he totalled one goal and three assists, meaning he was involved in four out of the five goals that the Sharks scored. This showed the strength of not just Burns, but also the Vlasic-Burns partnership that continued to succeed offensively and defensively in Game 2, where Burns tallied two goals and an assist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/sharks_versatility/pic_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only did Burns and Vlasic dominate in the attacking zone, but they were also the stand-out pairing in the defensive zone. Altogether, through the series against the Avalanche when Burns and Vlasic were on the ice together, they only let in six goals out of the seventeen scored. Considering this was the most popular defensive pairing utilized by DeBoer, with Burns and Vlasic playing 46% and 40% of the game respectively, it shows their dominance in the defensive third and their effectiveness as a pair. Therefore, it is clear the return of Vlasic after his absence in Game 2 through Game 4 against the Knights and his partnership with Burns positively drove both the Sharks' offense and defense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps too harsh to suggest that the Sharks triumphed over the Golden Knights due to their superior ability to adapt as the series went on. After all, even if one accepts this as truth, they still by all accounts should have lost in Game 7 if it were not for a poor penalty call that they had no control over. Despite this, it is unfortunate that, for many, the series will be remembered and defined by that penalty instead of by the drastic performance turnaround in net or the reversal of special teams proficiency between the two teams. Regardless of the outcome, this was objectively a series of fantastic play from incredibly talented players. The dramatic conclusion will be a mainstay of highlight reels and rule debates for years to come, but the variation of styles and willingness to experiment are the greater takeaway, and one that may be a prelude to the future of NHL playoff coaching.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Haley Rao</name></author><summary type="html">One of the thrills of watching playoff hockey is the emotional aspect, following a team through several games against the same opponent with everything on the line, and an especially close series makes the thrill even higher. The San Jose Sharks playing the Vegas Golden Knights in the first series of the playoffs was notable for its excitement, intensity, and controversy. The series was highly anticipated as a rematch of the previous year's second round, where the Knights won in six games. This time around, the Sharks were a much improved team, adding key players Erik Karlsson and Gustav Nyquist, while Vegas had more-or-less kept the same lineup as the previous year's Stanley Cup Final-bound team, with the notable addition of top line forward Mark Stone. The Golden Knights took early control of the series, finishing Game 4 with a 3-1 lead in games won. The Sharks managed to battle back, scoring a miraculous overtime goal in Game 6 to force a deciding game in San Jose. A close, hard-fought series was expected on the outset, but the conclusion shocked everyone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The issues with the Duckworth-Lewis-Stern Method</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/DuckworthLewisSternMethod" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The issues with the Duckworth-Lewis-Stern Method" /><published>2019-05-28T22:16:59-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-28T22:16:59-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/DuckworthLewisSternMethod</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/DuckworthLewisSternMethod">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Jonny Bairstow batting against Chennai Super Kings in an IPL 2019 game (Credits: in.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Indian Premier League wrapped up and the ICC World Cup just on the horizon, the cricket fever is definitely reaching its peak. As more and more people turn towards cricket to keep themselves entertained over the summer, it is probably safe to say that people who have been newly introduced to the sport won’t find it particularly easy to follow. While cricket is an already complicated game to begin with, there is one notorious component of the game that even most seasoned cricket fans fail to completely grasp - the Duckworth-Lewis-Stern (DLS) method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What is the Duckworth-Lewis-Stern Method?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of it, cricket is all about scoring more runs than the opponent. While test cricket has more flexibility in how this can be achieved, limited overs cricket (ODIs and Twenty-20s) is more straightforward in terms of the objective of the game. You have a certain number of overs available to you and you try to score as many runs as you can. Where the DLS method comes in is in the event of any interruptions during the game, most likely rain, which restricts the match from being completed in its entirety. In such a scenario, the number of overs that either one or both of the teams will face is adjusted, in order to finish the game in time, and the DLS method is used to accordingly adjust the score that the team batting second would require to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Frank Duckworth and Tony Lewis (Credits: The Telegraph)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DLS method is based on the principle that in a limited overs match, a team has two ‘resources’ available to them. The first one is the number of overs that they still have to face and the second is the number of wickets that they have left. It is easy to see that a team’s final score is strongly dependent on how many resources they have left at a particular stage of the game. Obviously, a team with more overs left will face more deliveries, and hence will have more chances to score. As for the wickets remaining, a team with more wickets can afford to take more risks and bat more aggressively, hence boosting their score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two points manifest themselves in a resource table, which provides the percentage of resources that a team has at different points of the game. Another peculiarity of cricket shows up here because in all international and first-class matches, the ‘Professional Edition’ of the system is used, which is not publicly available. Due to the presence of such a black box in the DLS calculations, I’m restricted to the use of the ‘Standard Edition’ for my analysis. The difference between these is that the ‘Professional Edition’ takes into account the score of the team batting first and makes slight adjustments to the resource table accordingly, while the ‘Standard Edition’ doesn’t take this into consideration. The ‘Standard Edition’ showed huge deviations in high scoring games and the switch to the ‘Professional Edition’ has helped fix this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DLS method was formulated to be used for 50-over games, but with the inception of the now incredibly popular Twenty-20 (T20) format, the method has been used in this format of the game as well. While it was devised considering the moderate scoring rates in 50-over games, the fact that the same formulation is being used for the much more explosive 20-over format does raise some concerns and this is exactly what I hope to investigate in this article. The relative importance of wickets and overs remaining was calibrated for the 50-over format and critics often point out that wickets are relatively less valuable in the shorter format of the game, making the DLS method less accurate. The ‘Standard Edition’ resource table scaled for a T20 game is shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;How is the Duckworth-Lewis-Stern Method used?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DLS Method is based around this straightforward equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The par score is the number of runs that the team batting second has to score in order to tie the game up. For instance, a game between Rising Pune Supergiants and the Kolkata Knight Riders during IPL 2016 was interrupted by rain at the end of the 18th over during Rising Pune Supergiants’ innings due to which Kolkata Knight Riders could only bat for 9 overs. As a result, their target was reduced to 66. This is slightly higher than a target of 61, which is what would have been obtained using the ‘Standard Edition’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Scorecard for the game (Credit: ESPN Cricinfo)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How effective is the Duckworth-Lewis-Stern Method?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/imrankhan17/t20matches&quot;&gt;dataset of over 6000 Twenty-20 matches played between 2003 and 2017&lt;/a&gt;, we can see that the split between the games won by teams batting first and those won by the team fielding first is pretty even. This holds true even for games which were interrupted due to rain and required the use of the DLS method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when we focus just on the games played in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/manasgarg/ipl&quot;&gt;Indian Premier League between 2008 and 2018&lt;/a&gt;, we see a huge disparity in the split. While the games played under normal conditions are more or less equally distributed in terms of whether teams batting first or second got the spoils, when we look at the matches in which the DLS method came into play, the team fielding first alarmingly won 74% of the time. It is important to note that this is based on a small sample size of merely 19 games, but the fact that this divide is present, does point towards a systemic issue in the DLS method which fails to account for the explosiveness and rapidly fluctuating nature of a T20 game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original Duckworth-Lewis Method used a score of 245 as the average score in a 50-over game in its formulation. This translates to a run rate (average runs scored per over) of 4.90. Looking at the first innings scores for Indian Premier League games, we see that the average runs scored is 162.11, which translates to a run rate of 8.11. This is significantly higher than what the norm was when Duckworth and Lewis came up with their formulation. This does give some validity to the argument made about the number of overs remaining being a significantly more valuable resource in a T20 game than it is in its 50-over counterpart. The boxplot below shows just how high the scores in T20 games can get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a better sense of whether the resource table fits well for a T20 game, I used data from the IPL games to see what the DLS method predicted the score to be for teams batting first based on the resources they had left at the end of the first half of their innings, i.e. 10 overs. The scores that the teams batting second achieved have been ignored because their strategy is often dictated by what the target is. For instance, a team chasing a lower target might chose to play conservatively and score at a rate slower than they normally would. Hence, they don’t provide an accurate representation of a team’s use of its resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a fair and accurate system, one would expect the predicted scores to be close to the actual scores and the error (actual score - predicted score) to have a mean near 0 along with a small standard deviation. While the scatterplot looks pretty evenly distributed, an in-depth analysis shows that the DLS method underestimated the final score in a staggering 59.39% of the games. The histogram, which shows the distribution of the error, does follow a Gaussian distribution, but it is easily noticeable that it is not centered around 0. The mean of the error is actually 4.44, which is pretty impressive, but the standard deviation comes out to be a disappointing 26.29. These predictions are based on the Standard Edition and even though the Professional Edition will allegedly provide better results, this does point towards systemic errors in the DLS method vis-à-vis its use in T20 games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another criticism that the DLS method faces is that it fails to account for the individuality of the players. A loss of wicket is treated the same in terms of the resources lost regardless of the player who was actually dismissed. This is not representative at all of what transpires over the course of an actual game. An in-form, experienced batsman is likely to do way more damage and both the teams are aware of this fact. The dismissal of a set batsman who’s been at the crease and been performing well can turn the game completely on its head, whereas the loss of the wicket of someone who isn’t at the top of his game will probably won’t have that deep of an impact on the game. So the fact that the DLS method provides equal weights to each batsman is slightly troubling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;David Warner's contribution to Sunrisers Hyderabad's 2019 IPL total&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the most recent season of the Indian Premier League, we can see that David Warner, who was the highest run scorer in the tournament, was responsible for an impressive 35.5% of his team’s total score in the 12 games that he played. Similarly, Kings XI Punjab’s K.L. Rahul alone scored 24.4% of the 2429 runs that the team accumulated over their 14 games. Taking into consideration the enormous contributions that these players made to their teams, it does seem unfair that the DLS assigns a weight of only a few percent to their wickets. A similar argument could be made for bowlers as well. Jasprit Bumrah’s brilliant bowling at the death was a key factor in Mumbai Indians’ winning performances. So the fact that his over is just as valuable as that of any other bowler shows another considerable discrepancy in the DLS method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/duckworth/pic11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;K.L. Rahul's contribution to Kings XI Punjab's 2019 IPL total&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;So what can be done?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The DLS Method is certainly an improvement on its predecessors, but that does not excuse the inherent issues that it has. With so much data being kept track of, building a system which incorporates batsmen’s strike rates, bowlers’ economy, and their averages is becoming more and more feasible. At least in the highest level of the game, making use of the numerous statistical tools and the plethora of available player and match data seems to be a logical step. Granted this would make the system even less transparent and more complex to understand, the stakes are so high that it surely warrants an attempt. Cricket is a sport where the tide can turn in a matter of a few deliveries, so it is obviously near impossible to account for each and every scenario. However, that does not mean that the current system cannot be improved. An overhaul is needed, but as for now, just hope that the rain gods are kind when you watch your favorite team play their next game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further Reading: Check out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stat.sfu.ca/content/dam/sfu/stat/alumnitheses/2011/M.Sc%20thesis-%20Gamage%20Harsha%20Perera_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;M.Sc thesis by Harsha Perera&lt;/a&gt; focusing on the Duckworth-Lewis Method in T20 Cricket. Keep in mind that this was published in 2011, before Professor Stern became the custodian of the method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I will have updated &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Vedant-Sahu?tab=repositories&quot;&gt;my GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, so that you can check out the analysis that I did and get the code for the plots that I made.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vedant Sahu</name></author><summary type="html">With the Indian Premier League wrapped up and the ICC World Cup just on the horizon, the cricket fever is definitely reaching its peak. As more and more people turn towards cricket to keep themselves entertained over the summer, it is probably safe to say that people who have been newly introduced to the sport won’t find it particularly easy to follow. While cricket is an already complicated game to begin with, there is one notorious component of the game that even most seasoned cricket fans fail to completely grasp - the Duckworth-Lewis-Stern (DLS) method.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What It Takes To Be World Number 1: An Analysis of the ATP Tour</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ATPTour" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What It Takes To Be World Number 1: An Analysis of the ATP Tour" /><published>2019-05-27T21:41:31-07:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T21:41:31-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ATPTour</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ATPTour">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to individual sports, the title of “World Number One” is the ultimate feat an athlete can achieve. Tennis may be the most popular example of such a sport, as it is played worldwide and is heavily driven by rankings from its lowest tiers to the professional stage. While the World Number One and other top players are very famous and appear in widely-known tournaments, the complex structure of men’s professional tennis and its ranking system are by no means common knowledge. The Association of Tennis Professionals (ATP) is the governing body that organizes the events and rankings that tennis fans are so familiar with. ATP tennis is unique in that it runs year-round with a higher activity level than most other professional sports, as tournaments take place on a weekly basis. While the four Grand Slams are the most prestigious of these events, every tournament throughout the year can impact a player’s world ranking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ATP Tour, the circuit that men's professional tennis runs on, consists of several tiers that vary in prestige and quality of competition. The tier of a given tournament determines how many ATP points a player earns for winning matches in that tournament. The four main playing fields are the ATP 250, ATP 500, ATP Masters 1000, and Grand Slams. A player can participate in as many tournaments as he wants, but outside of Slams and Masters, only his six best results from all other events will count towards his ranking points. The number of points a player receives at an event increases as he wins more rounds, with the winner receiving the number of points indicated by the tournament's tier (the winner of a Slam gets 2000). Furthermore, the ranking system runs on a rolling basis and players must constantly defend the points they have. Essentially, a player only gains points from a tournament if he makes it to a further round than he did at that tournament the year before. If he cannot do this, he loses the points he failed to defend (or breaks even if he has the same result as he did a year prior). Through this point system, at the beginning of each week, the player with the most ATP points is the current World Number One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system is very straightforward, but becoming World Number One is easier said than done. Since the conception of this ranking system in 1973, only 26 men have sat atop the perch of men's tennis. Considering the rigid structure of the ATP Tour, scheduling is crucial to a player's road to relevance. To reach number one in the rankings, the question that players should ask themselves is, &quot;How can I optimize my ATP schedule to maximize the points I earn?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, there has been a noticeable trend in the activity level of the reigning World Number One:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;width:50%; float: left;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;width:50%; float:right&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Year by year, the World Number Ones are generally finishing with more points despite playing fewer tournaments per year. It is clear that careful selectivity plays a key role in the path to the top. Attending a large number of tournaments is unnecessary if a player can plan his year out in such a way that he maximizes his performance in the events that he does attend. For instance, going deep in a Masters 1000 is far more valuable than trying to win two ATP 250 tournaments in the same time span. To further examine such selective scheduling among top players, we need not look past the last fifteen years. This era of tennis has featured an unprecedented control of the top spot by three players who are clearly a cut above the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Big Three&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Time Magazine&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Of the 782 weeks from 2004 to 2018, Roger Federer, Novak Djokovic, and Rafael Nadal have combined to hold the number one ranking for 738 weeks. While they are all brilliant tennis players who are capable of racking up points through talent alone, sustaining that level of success over the course of nearly two decades requires intelligent tour scheduling as well. Looking back to the 2004 season (the first full year where all three played tour level matches), here is how the Big 3 have split up their tours:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Time Magazine&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;When gunning for world number one, the Grand Slams and almost all Masters events are essentially non-negotiable. However, the attendance of the Big 3 at 250 and 500 events is extremely similar as well. Although these lower-level events are the most abundant on tour, the fact that all three of them play roughly four per year suggests that they do not place much value on these tournaments. While these events offer ample opportunities to gain chunks of points quite easily, the Big 3 most likely use them as tuneups to keep themselves in form as they head into the top-tier tournaments. Consequently, the line between the lower two tiers becomes blurred as the Big 3 categorize them under one umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, there are notable similarities in the way that the Big 3 space out their tournaments. Below are maps that depict the activity levels of each of the Big 3 based on the ATP points they earned each week in the years that they finished as World Number One:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that jumps out is the way that all three of them make it a point to be active in the weeks leading up to Grand Slams and then rest in the weeks following them. Coming off of a one-month layover from the previous season, they all play an ATP 250 tournament in the two weeks right before the Australian Open. Similarly, they all play nearly the entire month of May heading into the French Open. Because clay is a slower surface that requires lots of stamina and the clay court season is relatively short compared to the hard court swings, they need to gain as much match play as possible on the red dirt before Roland Garros rolls around. Moreover, this pattern of tuning up for Slams is especially clear during August, as they each play at least two tournaments to prepare for the U.S. Open at the end of the month. The time leading up to Wimbledon is unique in that there is less than a month between it and the conclusion of the French Open. Regardless, the Big 3 still make sure to squeeze in exactly one grass tournament during this brief period. Given that grass is the fastest surface and favors shorter points, it does not require as much conditioning as clay. Therefore, one week on and one week off allows them to achieve the optimal balance between getting in form for Wimbledon and having ample recovery time from Roland Garros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Slams have finished, the Big 3 take their rest. After the Australian Open, Wimbledon, and U.S. Open, they all take at least two weeks off. As discussed earlier, the time after the French Open is an exception because of how quickly Wimbledon arrives, so they have no choice but to play a tune-up grass tournament immediately after Roland Garros (although they still make sure to take a week off). The tournaments that take place immediately after Slams conclude are of little to no benefit for the Big 3. To them, the entire purpose of smaller events is to build up their confidence and sharpen their form heading into the larger ones. Therefore, resting after Slams is the most practical course of action, especially since all three of them are over 30 years of age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Federer, Nadal, and Djokovic all specialize on different surfaces (grass, clay, and hard court respectively) and possess strikingly distinct play styles. Despite these differences, they demonstrate a clear similarity with the way that they cater their tournament scheduling to the Grand Slams. From a simple mathematical perspective, this is a sound formula for capitalizing on the limited opportunities they have throughout the year to reap the largest rewards on the tour. But not everyone is talented enough to take this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What About Everyone Else?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned formula makes plenty of sense, provided that the player in question is actually capable of consistently going deep in Grand Slams. Unfortunately, for most of the world, this is not the case. The Big 3 have claimed the lion's share of Grand Slam success for the last fifteen years. Of the 60 Grand Slams from 2004 to 2018, the Big 3 have won 50. On top of that, only four Grand Slam finals since 2004 have not featured a member of the Big 3. This level of dominance does not exist in any other sport and has completely shut down the natural transition from one generation to the next that sports typically go through. No player born in the 1990's or later has ever won a Grand Slam. In fact, only two have ever made it to a Grand Slam final. Essentially, Grand Slam trophies are a distant dream for the mere mortal tennis players of today's world. In order to stay alive in the race for World Number One, the rest of the top ten players must offset this deficit by playing many more tournaments in general. Below is a display of the paths that the Big 3 took last year to earn their ATP Points compared to those of five other top 10 players: Alexander Zverev, Kevin Anderson, Dominic Thiem, Kei Nishikori, and John Isner.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;width:50%; float: left;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;width:50%; float:right&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;-&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workload disparity between the two parties is quite glaring. While the Big 3 had long, flat periods and moved up large chunks at a time, the other top ten players' paths were very busy. At a substantially high rate, they generally moved up small steps at a time in order to counteract the Grand Slam points that the Big 3 consistently racked up. On average, these five players roughly played 3 ATP 250 events and 5.5 ATP 500 events last year while the Big 3 averaged only 0.3 250s and 2 500s. Through such a high attendance rate, Alexander Zverev was able to finish within 40 points of Roger Federer for the number 3 spot, with Djokovic and Nadal at 1 and 2 respectively. It should be noted that Federer is 37 years old and has generally skipped the entire clay court season the last few years whereas Zverev is 22 years young and extremely hungry to become the face of men's tennis one day. That is no knock against Zverev; this high-frequency strategy makes plenty of sense for young players whose bodies can handle 25+ tournaments per year. And for those especially talented youngsters like Zverev and Thiem, it's the only chance they have of fighting for World Number One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the approach that the rest of the top ten players take to shoot for World Number One is very different from that of the Big 3. While the Big 3 focus their entire year on the four Slams, there is a consensus among the rest of the tour in that the Slam trophies are extremely difficult for them. Despite being years younger, they would need the stars to align in order to outsmart Federer, outwork Nadal, or outclass Djokovic over five sets. So instead of banking on Slams, they feed on the many other tournaments throughout the year in order to get themselves within striking distance of a top ranking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;No Way Around Perfection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, becoming World Number One ultimately comes down to a matter of who collects the most ATP points. A player who wins six ATP 500 events and makes it to the semi-finals of all of the Masters events and Grand Slams already has more than 9000 points, which is generally enough to contend for World Number One. But in reality, there is a limit to how much one can game the system. In the history of tennis, there has only been one man (Marcelo Rios) to hold the number one ranking without ever winning a Grand Slam in his career. As obvious as it may sound, becoming World Number One requires sensational tennis, far beyond what that player normally puts on display. The Elo Rating System is an all-encompassing metric that calculates the relative skill levels of players based on factors such as quality of opposition and magnitude of matches won. Below is a comparative chart (dating back to 1973) of the Elo ratings of every year-end World Number One that year relative to his career Elo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic13.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The average career Elo of all Year-End World Number Ones since 1973 is 2092.58, so the fact that players improve their Elo ratings by hundreds of points in their number one years underscores just how much they elevated their levels of play. We should acknowledge the two negative bars at the end that represent Nadal's 2017 and Djokovic's 2018 seasons. They finished those years with lower Elo ratings than years prior, but these lesser versions of themselves were still easily enough to end those years at atop the rankings. Generally speaking, World Number Ones reach new heights en route to claiming the ATP's top spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2000 is the Magic Number&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ATPTour/pic14.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 14&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As we've discussed, the ATP tour has many layers, all of which factor into a player's world ranking. But it is clear that the road to World Number One goes through the Grand Slams. It is no coincidence that the Big 3 have won 52 combined Slams and controlled the number one ranking for almost 95% of the last fifteen years. Despite the efforts of other top players who play far more tournaments to make up for the Slams, the 2000 points gained from these four events is still too much to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Slams have separated the contenders from the rest of the pack, the remaining tour events then determine who belongs at the top. Stan Wawrinka and Andy Murray each have 3 Grand Slam titles, yet their careers have played out quite differently. Outside of the Slams, Murray has won 42 titles, 14 of which are Masters, whereas Wawrinka has won just 13 titles, only one of which is a Masters. Not surprisingly, Murray was the World Number One for 41 straight weeks, while Wawrinka has never even reached number 2. Slams are paramount, but what truly separates the top player from everyone else is the full body of work over 52 weeks. So, the next time you see a World Number One on TV, you'll have a better understanding of exactly how much weight that title carries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: ESPN, ATPTour, UltimateTennisStatistics&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kevin Hahn</name></author><summary type="html">When it comes to individual sports, the title of “World Number One” is the ultimate feat an athlete can achieve. Tennis may be the most popular example of such a sport, as it is played worldwide and is heavily driven by rankings from its lowest tiers to the professional stage. While the World Number One and other top players are very famous and appear in widely-known tournaments, the complex structure of men’s professional tennis and its ranking system are by no means common knowledge. The Association of Tennis Professionals (ATP) is the governing body that organizes the events and rankings that tennis fans are so familiar with. ATP tennis is unique in that it runs year-round with a higher activity level than most other professional sports, as tournaments take place on a weekly basis. While the four Grand Slams are the most prestigious of these events, every tournament throughout the year can impact a player’s world ranking.</summary></entry></feed>