<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-13T18:16:50-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">Which Team Won the 2020 Draft?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/DraftWinners" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Which Team Won the 2020 Draft?" /><published>2020-06-13T18:03:14-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-13T18:03:14-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/DraftWinners</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/DraftWinners">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/draftWinners/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Forbes&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Process:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the NFL draft having recently concluded, many fans and outlets have been releasing draft grades, as per the annual tradition. While the grades vary from A's down to the occasional F, there's really very little analysis put into deriving these letters; these outlets often base their grades on the pre-draft reputations of the players picked, only considering whether they themselves believe these players are &quot;good value&quot; and not really taking into account scheme fit and other underlying factors that could sway the odds of success in the team's favor. My goal in this article was to look into external cues of player success. The three main factors I decided to focus on to attempt to find indicators of this year's most successful draft were combine data, strength of conference, and team history of drafting success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first criteria, I attempted to find a streamlined way to quantify athletic ability, and see if there are any athletic indicators that hint at success. For the offensive tackle, defensive-end, wide-receiver, cornerback, running-back and linebacker positions, I looked at the 6 major combine drills: Broad Jump, Bench Press, Vertical Jump, 40 yard dash, 3 Cone, and the Shuttle. The 40 yard dash, Broad Jump and Vertical jump help show speed and explosiveness, while the 3 Cone and Shuttle both help display short-area quickness and burst. The Bench press is more a test of determination, work-ethic and strength. The higher the number of reps completed, the more will-power it shows, especially for a position that doesn't need a high bench-press score. Thus, I would consider the bench-press to be an indicator of toughness and character for many positions. I chose the positions I did because they are the major archetypes needed to build successful teams, excluding the quarterback, who can't be quantified by purely statistics, as there's so much more to the position. The offensive tackle can serve to represent the offensive line, as these are often the most athletically gifted and important protectors on the line. The wide-receiver and running-back are focal points of the offense. The cornerback position is a premier defensive-back position and can for the most part be used to judge safeties as well, although safeties must often be more fluid and better in run-support. The defensive-end position is an anchor for a ferocious defensive-line, and the inside linebacker position is critical as a field-general, in both 3-4 and especially 4-3 defenses. For each of these major positions, I found the percentage of high-performers in each of the drills (1.5 standard deviations better than the combine average), and found the probability of these athletically superior players developing into impact players (all-pro players or multiple time pro-bowlers). I then compared this to the position average as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second criteria, I looked at strength of conference, and found the percentage of players picked from each conference between 2006-2015 who became pro-bowlers, and compared this to the entire draft. The SEC has, for the most part, been considered the top conference in the nation in-terms of talent and strength for the last decade and a half, and I wanted to see if this was supported by draft data. On top of this, not only did I calculate hit-rate per draft on SEC players, and the draft's overall hit-rate, but I also calculated the hit-rate of the other 4 major conferences (Pac-10/12, Big Ten, Big 12 and ACC). With this, I was able to gather an overarching perspective on the success of each of these conferences in churning out impact NFL talent, and this was key in projecting into the 2020 draft, as it allowed me to roughly estimate a probability that a selected player is a Pro Bowler based on his conference. Furthermore, I gathered the hit-rate of players picked in each round over the 10 year span I examined (2006-2015) in order to weigh each round of the draft accordingly. I didn't want to accidentally overlook the importance of draft-position and give Joe Burrow and an unknown SEC player picked in the 5th round the same chances of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third criteria, a team's history of draft success, helps eliminate teams who satisfy the criteria above but may not have the history of success of other teams. For example, if both the Ravens, a franchise which historically drafts extremely well, and the Browns, a franchise known for ineptitude, had drafts which seemed exceptional by the standards above, I would consider the Ravens draft better because of what they have shown in previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, when looking at this model part-by-part, you can see that with the first step, I address a player's overall athletic background and talent. While not every freak athlete who enters the league pans out, it definitely helps to be one of the best athletes in the world. Secondly, I layer athletic ability with how the player has been developed in college, and whether they were able to go to programs and play against programs which churn out NFL-caliber talent on a consistent basis. Better competition leads to a better player, and while it would be hard to capture pure statistical production on the field in my data, I am able to capture the level of competition they played against, which is an important factor in its own right. By weighting each round, I believe that production in college will be included in the model for the most part, as players who produce in college are usually picked higher in the draft than those who don't. For those who say that NFL teams prioritize athletic ability over everything else, Lamar Jackson and D.K. Metcalf stand out as prime recent examples of players who have not gone as high as their athletic ability billed them to. Finally, by taking into account the team that picks these players, I favor the players who will have a better development staff and more successful team around them to pick them up and give them an advantage. My rankings will depend as much on the team as the players, something which many draftniks don't factor in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Findings:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After tracking Combine data since 2000, I found a series of notable observations. Of the most stark was the importance of a good broad-jump for cornerbacks, which makes sense due to the quick plays they need to make on balls coming their way, and the overall short-area explosiveness necessary to play the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/draftWinners/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking at players who tested at 1.5 standard-deviations above the mean, 9 out of the 36 qualifying players were impact players, meaning they made either multiple pro-bowls or an exclusive All-Pro team during their careers. While the 3-cone drill also had high-success rates, the population of players 1.5 standard deviations above the mean consisted of a significantly smaller sample of players. The list of players with broad-jumps well above average included current stars such as Jalen Ramsey and Byron Jones, as well as former greats such as Charles Tillman and Antonio Cromartie. Thus, when looking at corners, a high Broad-Jump is heavily favored. Next, for offensive-tackle, you could once again see the value in the broad-jump, as well as in the 40 yard dash, with each having 7 impact players out of pools of 30 qualifying athletes whose scores were head-and-shoulders above their peers. The running-back position also showed an importance in the broad-jump, with 7 out of 28 qualifiers becoming impact talents. The inside-linebacker position had high-success in the players who had above-average vertical leaps, with 5 out of the 15 players lying 1.5 standard deviations above the mean becoming impact talents. This list includes former stars in Luke Kuechly and Patrick Willis, two of the most dominant middle linebackers of the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant drill for defensive ends was the 40, as a little more than 1/6th of the top performers (6/34) were all-pro caliber players at some point of their career. This makes sense due to the fact that edge-defenders need to have world-class acceleration off the line to beat offensive-linemen, so a high 40 also signals an exceptional 10-yard split. The 10-yard split is the time it takes for a player to sprint from 0 to 10 yards when running the 40 yard dash, and is important because it translates well onto the football field, signalling a player's short-range explosiveness and power. It's one of the more important athletic indicators of success. This is an indicator I especially expected to translate to the wide-receiver group, which ended up not showing much of a pattern. While I expected short-area drills like the 3-cone and shuttle to have importance, as receivers need to be agile and able to make quick, crisp cuts to run clean routes,  these metrics didn't show a significant ability to predict breakout talent at the position. This is probably due to the fact that players can thrive at this position playing in so many different ways, whether it is through crisp routes, long speed, or the ability to win jump-balls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/draftWinners/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this information processed, I proceeded to look at the hit-rate per conference in each of the drafts from 2006-2015, as shown above. In this 10 year split, I was trying to see how many players blossomed into solid NFL players, so my criteria was a bit lower, just requiring a singular pro-bowl appearance to be included. Most NFL teams aren't built on stars but rather a solid core group, and I wanted to see how many of these players came out of each conference. As expected, the SEC dominated, with 71 players becoming pro-bowlers out of the total 441 players selected, which comes out to an average of 7 pro-bowl players per year and an insane 44 players picked per draft. This 15.9% hit-rate handily outperformed the draft's overall hit-rate of 12.1%, which was derived from the 307 pro-bowlers that blossomed out of 2546 total drafted players. Out of the other major conferences, only the Pac-12 outperformed the draft over the same span, and that was by a paltry 0.7%. On a year-by-year basis, the SEC beat the overall draft in terms of the proportion of Pro Bowl players 9 out of 10 years.  In terms of the other conferences, the Pac-12 beat the draft in 8 out of the 10 years, the ACC beat it 4 times, the Big 12 had 3, and the big ten had a paltry 2 years. As seen, the SEC and the Pac-12 have been far and away the two most consistent conferences, but the SEC is still head-and-shoulders above the rest, having the best pro-bowl rate of any conference in 5 out of 10 years while the Pac-12 enjoyed this honor only once. The fact that the SEC was able to achieve these high-rates with more players being drafted than any other conference makes this all the more impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/draftWinners/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I looked at drafting success by round, as shown in the bar-plot above, which further cemented the notion that the first round obviously has far and away the most impact talent, with a 43.75% pro-bowl rate over the 10 year span. The second-round is far and away the next best round to find talent, with teams still having a very respectable 20.4% hit-rate, so one out of every five players picked in the second-round ended up panning out. After the second round though, the draft becomes far more unreliable in terms of coming away with talent. The 3rd round's odds of landing a pro-bowl level player are just about 10%, the 4th round sits at 8.6%, and afterwards the 5th, 6th and 7th round are basically a blind game of darts, with odds of hitting on a player in the 5th is 5.6%, 6th is 4.2% and the 7th is a paltry 1.8%. Using this information, we can start to form an idea about the workings of the draft, and notice that players picked from the SEC at the top of the draft are usually the players safest bets to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in-terms of the hit-rates of current NFL general managers, many of the teams with long-standing general managers tend to have the best hit-rates. This is most likely due to survivorship bias, as most of the long-standing regimes have only survived for so long due to sustained success. Some of these teams include the Pittsburgh Steelers (11.8%), the New Orleans Saints (14.7%), the Atlanta Falcons (13.79%), the Minnesota Vikings (13.33%), and of course, the Dallas Cowboys (12.9%) with their league leading 36 pro-bowlers picked under owner Jerry Jones. Other teams with a breadth of experience include the Carolina Panthers (10.4%), the Seattle Seahawks (10.3%) and the New England Patriots (9.09%). Out of the new-comer general managers, Eric DeCosta of the Baltimore Ravens, Chris Ballard of the Indianapolis Colts, and Ryan Pace of the Chicago Bears seem to be the best bets. DeCosta has worked with the Ravens since 2003 and was a big presence during their dominant drafting stretch under former GM Ozzie Newsome, who retired a year ago. Chris Ballard has only had 2 drafts (excluding 2020), but in his first draft he was able to land 2 All-Pro players with his first 2 picks. Finally, Ryan Pace has the highest overall hit-rate of active general managers, landing pro-bowlers with 5 out of his 32 picks (15.6%), which as a Bears fan, is quite shocking and definitely skewed by Mitchell Trubisky's 2019 Pro Bowl appearance. Regardless, Pace has done well with himself and has an Executive of the Year award under his belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, with this information, we now have an accurate framework to judge the 2020 NFL draft and its results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;2020 outlook:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2020 draft's first-round once again displayed the SEC's dominance, with a record 15 SEC players picked. As the draft progressed, this trend continued, with 40 players from the conference picked through the first 3 rounds and 63 players selected overall. Because of the SEC's dominant hit-rate compared to other conferences, the first step in deducing this year's best draft (draft with the probability of having pro-bowl talent), was to narrow my selection of teams to either those which had multiple first round picks or those who picked an SEC player in the first round. Doing so produced an expansive list of the following teams, listed in the order of the players selected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/draftWinners/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One team with multiple first-round picks notably missing from this list is the LA Chargers, who used both their picks on non-SEC players, with one of them being a developmental quarterback. On top of this, despite the linebacker they drafted in the first-round (Kenneth Murray) being a great player, they were forced to give up plenty of draft capital to earn this right. As you can see, early front-runners for the best draft seem to be the teams with the most picks. This makes conceptual sense, and in a year where almost half of the first-round was out of the SEC, teams with multiple first-round picks such as the Jaguars and the Dolphins seemed to capitalize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move to the second and third rounds, the list further narrows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/draftWinners/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three teams were eliminated for various reasons. Firstly, the Cincinnati Bengals were not considered further due to a combination of a lack of SEC picks and owner Mike Brown's paltry drafting history, with a hit-rate barely higher than 6% despite being involved with the Bengals' drafting process for almost 30 years. The Bengals current dearth of talent would also make it difficult for any draft-picks to have early success. I also didn't consider Kansas City and Tennessee further simply due to the fact that they had both fewer picks and later picks than the other teams. On top of this, with both teams having made deep playoff runs, there won't be as much of an opportunity for players to contribute heavily early on. The Ravens, although in a similar boat, had two more picks and managed to take arguably the best inside linebacker in the nation with their first pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I was able to choose a cloud of 10 teams, comprising of a bit less than the top third of NFL drafts, I decided to use my round-by-round and per-conference hit-rate percentages to come up with rough estimations to separate these drafts in terms of quality. These numbers were derived from adding the pro-bowl probability of each player, which I calculated by multiplying the pro-bowl-probability per round and the pro-bowl probability per conference. This number, while not taking in the entire landscape of the graph, should serve to provide a good idea of each team's chances at landing an impact talent from the 2020 draft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/draftWinners/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After looking at these numbers, the far-and-away best draft turned out to be that of the Miami Dolphins. Despite all the data collection about conference and round-by-round data, the Dolphins were always going to be the front-runner purely due to the number of picks they had. The Jaguars and the Vikings, who both had two first-round picks, also fared well in the draft. The Vikings may have done well with their 5th round cornerback, Harrison Hand, whose broad-jump lands over 1.5 standard-deviations above the mean for his position. For his position, this drill has merit, and thus the selection serves as a good flier on a prospect with top-notch athletic talent. The Raiders also had 2 first-round picks to help with their score, and are followed by the Ravens, the first team on the list who only had one first round pick. The rest of the teams on the list are a cloud of teams, with these numbers tending to be fairly packed together. Of the teams in this year's draft that had only one first round pick, all things considered, I would choose the 10th team on this list, the Panthers, as the prime draft to look out for. The Panthers are a bare-boned team with plenty of opportunities to offer rookies playing-time while undergoing a regime-change and rebuild. General manager Marty Hurney has a reputable and long-stretching history of successful drafting, and new head coach Matt Rhule, as a college coach in 2020, had the upper-hand of seeing these players play and coaching against them first-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus we can finally come to the conclusion of who I think won the draft in 2020. The answer is an obvious one, which we probably could have guessed beforehand: The Miami Dolphins. Buoyed by their 3 first-round picks in the midst of a mass rebuild, the Dolphins were able to grab value and maximize their chances of an impact player with their massive stockpile of picks. In-terms of the best draft out of last-year's crop of playoff teams, my answer would have to be the Minnesota Vikings, with their league-leading 15 picks. Finally, in terms of the draft's winner out of teams with just 1 first round pick (a lack of special draft-capital) I would choose the Carolina Panthers, for the reasons I mentioned before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a bonus, I wanted to wrap up this article by briefly touching upon the teams in this draft without exceptional draft capital (those missing a first-round pick). While these teams face odds stacked against their favor, I would be remiss if I didn't mention at least one team in this pool that did well. My favorite draft out of those teams that were &quot;capital-challenged&quot; was Chris Ballard's of the Indianapolis Colts. With his two second-round picks, Ballard was able to pick a running-back with one of the fastest 10-yard splits at the combine, a score which bodes well for his future success. He also picked wide-receiver Michael Pittman Jr., who posted strong agility scores at a 6'4&quot;, 220 pound frame. While teams without a first-round pick face long odds of having an impact draft, Ballard's drafting history and the two second-round players picked offer Colts fans some hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: pro-football-reference.com, footballdb.com, nflcombineresults.com, kaggle.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vishal Sundaram</name></author><summary type="html">With the NFL draft having recently concluded, many fans and outlets have been releasing draft grades, as per the annual tradition. While the grades vary from A's down to the occasional F, there's really very little analysis put into deriving these letters; these outlets often base their grades on the pre-draft reputations of the players picked, only considering whether they themselves believe these players are &quot;good value&quot; and not really taking into account scheme fit and other underlying factors that could sway the odds of success in the team's favor. My goal in this article was to look into external cues of player success. The three main factors I decided to focus on to attempt to find indicators of this year's most successful draft were combine data, strength of conference, and team history of drafting success.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assessing the Tiers of Modern NFL Receivers With the Help of Machine Learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/modernreceivers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assessing the Tiers of Modern NFL Receivers With the Help of Machine Learning" /><published>2020-05-26T21:57:15-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-26T21:57:15-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/modernreceivers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/modernreceivers">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: SFGate&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like what has happened to basketball during Stephen Curry's career, the offensive philosophy of football has changed over the last few years. The traditional usage of wide receivers that has been around for decades is slowly fading away as football enters a new era of play calling and receivers in general are becoming far more versatile. Given all of this, I decided to look into how the tiers of receivers in the modern NFL can be better classified and how different they are from the traditional roles we have known for years. With the help of some analysis I did to classify advanced receiver data, I was able to find some pretty interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Basics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: viqtorysports.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, there are three main receivers in an offense: the X, the Y, and the Z. The X receiver is the number one guy; he typically lines up on the weak side of the formation and right on the line of scrimmage. He's expected to be a physical player that's great with his hands and savvy enough to get off the ball and his man when jammed at the line of scrimmage. The Y receiver is usually a tight end; he's a blocker with pass-catching abilities and typically lines up closest to an offensive tackle. And lastly, the Z receiver is known as the 'flanker' or the number two guy. He typically lines up on the strong side of the formation about a yard off the ball and has the ability to motion in and out of the formation. He's usually relatively fast and can utilize that speed without worrying about getting jammed at the line of scrimmage to generate separation from his man. These are the labels by which plays have largely been called in the NFL for decades, but the actual roles of receivers within offenses have become far more convoluted than a simple X, Y, and Z classification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the two teams that participated in this year's Super Bowl as examples. The Kansas City Chiefs' number one receiver is actually their &lt;i&gt;tight end&lt;/i&gt; Travis Kelce; play caller Andy Reid simply puts him all over the field as if he's a top wideout. It's actually more accurate to say that the Chiefs have two number one receivers (Kelce and Tyreek Hill) rather than a simple X, Y, and Z. Their opponent, on the other hand, has zero X receivers. The 49ers' receiving corps is made up of three number two guys, a freakishly athletic tight end, and a fullback that had more yards per target than any of the starting receivers in 2019. And yet, these two rather unconventional offenses were in the top three in net yards gained per pass attempt last season before ultimately squaring off in a Super Bowl. In many ways, that game was indicative of the current trajectory of football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reid, Niners play caller Kyle Shanahan, and many of their peers today subscribe to the following mindset: on any given play you have five eligible receivers; which five you roll with and how you choose to deploy them is entirely up to your creativity. There aren't really any other rules to this chess game. Tight ends can play like wide receivers, wide receivers can play like running backs, and fullbacks can play like tight ends. The NFL has changed, but by how much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_3.gif&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: NFL (Youtube)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Methodology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with advanced data from the NFL's &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextgenstats.nfl.com/stats/receiving&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NextGenStats&lt;/a&gt; database of every wide receiver and tight end in the NFL over the last four years (2016-2019) who averaged at least 2.5 targets per week. The categories of data I took for each receiver along with their name, the year, their team, and their position were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 45%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal was to create a k-means clustering of this data to see what patterns I could find in the groups that the algorithm split the receivers into. The way a K-means algorithm works is by initially choosing the desired number of centroids (mean values of clusters) and then constantly adjusting these centroids as it takes in more data points by using the Euclidean distance between points to place them into clusters. But with high-dimensional data, the calculation of this distance becomes more and more meaningless. To reduce the data to a few meaningful variables, I used Principal Component Analysis, a method that represents a given dataset with orthogonal vectors that explain the original dataset's variance. A subset of these orthogonal vectors (components) can then be used to represent a given percentage of the variance in the data. To determine the exact number of components that would be used in the k-means algorithm, I plotted the cumulative sum of the explained variance as the number of components increases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three components explained 73.6% of the variance in the data. After that, the increase in explained variance was not significant enough to warrant the inclusion of another component in the model, so I decided to proceed with three principal components for this data set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once that was complete, an optimal number of clusters for the k-means algorithm needed to be determined as well. To do this, I simply ran the algorithm 20 times with a different number of clusters each time and stored the within-cluster sum of squares (WCSS) for each run. WCSS is the sum of the squared deviations from each data point and its cluster centroid, which essentially makes it a metric for how distinctive each cluster is (the smaller the WCSS, the more compact the clusters are). Plotting these values revealed that the drop in WCSS began to level off at around three clusters, so that's how many clusters I decided to use in the algorithm. With three principal components and three desired clusters, the k-means clustering produced the following classifications of NFL receivers over the last four years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting part had finally arrived. The receivers had been split up into three groups as shown above, but what exactly are the groups? After spending some time looking through the names and stats in the different groups, I arrived at some loose conclusions about what kind of receivers were in each group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Cluster 1: Tight Ends and YAC Monsters (211 players)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, these receivers do not have the highest share of the team's air yards and they work closer to the line of scrimmage (lower Avg. TAY), but they create more separation per play and have more yards after the catch (YAC) per reception than any other cluster. This assessment has 'Tight End' written all over it and surely enough, most of the tight ends in the data set fell into this cluster. But these statistics also accurately capture faster wide receivers that are number two or number three guys within their respective offenses and who are great after the catch, so many notable YAC specialists over the years fell into this group as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Cluster 2: Unproductive Speedsters and Old/Injured Stars (156 players)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cluster is characterized by players who have more targeted air yards but a lower catch percentage and less YAC per reception than any other cluster. This was easily the most interesting cluster of the three because for the most part, it seemed like the worst receivers in the dataset appeared here, with some notable names also appearing. As far as the bulk of the receivers in this group goes, their commonality seems to be that they are generally very fast players that have no other dimension to their games than their speed (in that particular year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this does not explain why certain popular receivers that have been known to be very productive throughout their careers fell into this group. Looking closer at these names, almost all of them appear to have something in common. I've listed a few examples below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost every surprising name in this cluster was in the final year(s) of his career, injured, or both (almost every player in the above table was once a Pro Bowler). As a result, they got put into the same group as the generally unproductive receivers because their overall value to their passing offense is roughly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Cluster 3: The Best Receivers in Football, True Number Ones (139 players)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like the modern NFL does still have the concept of the X receiver in terms of number one guys, even if the way these players line up is not always how the traditional X lines up. These players have the highest share of their teams' air yards and they lead the league in catches, targets, total yards, and touchdowns. They are some of the most recognizable names in football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Additional Thoughts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clusters do a decent job of capturing the development of receivers over the four years of data. For example, Tyler Lockett was a Cluster 1 receiver in 2016 and 2017 but transitioned into a Cluster 3 receiver in 2018 and 2019 as he became the Seahawks' premier target. Moreover, the clusters also give a pretty accurate depiction of the offensive situations of the 32 teams in the NFL. Going back to our Super Bowl teams, we can see that Kansas City has two Cluster 3 receivers in Kelce and Hill, backing up what the world knows about their high-octane passing offense. San Francisco, however, has zero Cluster 3 receivers, correctly leading us to believe that they are a team that relies on scheme to move the ball through the air rather than top-tier receivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernReceivers/pic_13.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Falcons Wire&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clustering was by no means perfect. There are still certain head-scratchers in each cluster, which can largely be attributed to the random nature of the NFL. But it is also important to note that some of the strange output can be a result of cross-season comparison of these receivers. Using four seasons worth of receiver data and treating it all the exact same way is not entirely correct given the way sports tend to change over time. All in all, it's almost impossible to entirely classify a football player's value or production based on numbers alone, but this project did a solid job in helping illuminate the status of receivers today. Circling back to the discussion of traditional receiver roles, it looks like the X receiver is very much alive and well as the alpha of the receiving group, but with the way that pre-snap motion and shifts have started to take over the league (for various reasons that can be discussed in another article), these number one guys tend to line up all over the field rather than just the typical spot for X receivers on the weak side of the formation. The traditional Y and Z roles, however, seem to be merging into one and the evolution of tight ends is likely the culprit for this. While most of the tight ends are Cluster 1 players, many tight ends have been making their ways into Cluster 3 over the years. The standard for tight end play is increasing every year in the NFL as they are becoming extremely athletic, dynamic players that play callers like to use as wildcards within their offenses. As a result, the production of tight ends is becoming extremely similar to number two and even number one wide receivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that it won't be long before Cluster 1 and Cluster 3 start to overlap as well. The Cluster 1 guys are generally better after the catch and the Cluster 3 guys are generally more physical players with better hands, but the Cluster 3 players are also tremendous YAC receivers and the Cluster 1 players are becoming number one options for many teams. The line between those two will only become more blurry as the years go on. It's not official, but football seems to be entering an era where three players that can do a little bit of everything are becoming more valuable than a group consisting of a pure X, Y, and Z. 'Positionless basketball' is one of the hot phrases in sports today, but it may not be long before we have positionless offensive football as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: nextgenstats.nfl.com, pro-football-reference.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View Code: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Kathirilango/Sports-Analytics/tree/master/receiver_cluster&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Github Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kathir Ilango</name></author><summary type="html">Much like what has happened to basketball during Stephen Curry's career, the offensive philosophy of football has changed over the last few years. The traditional usage of wide receivers that has been around for decades is slowly fading away as football enters a new era of play calling and receivers in general are becoming far more versatile. Given all of this, I decided to look into how the tiers of receivers in the modern NFL can be better classified and how different they are from the traditional roles we have known for years. With the help of some analysis I did to classify advanced receiver data, I was able to find some pretty interesting things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Faces of Tomorrow’s NBA?: A Comparison of the Atlanta Hawks’ and Dallas Mavericks’ Offenses</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/HawksMavs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Faces of Tomorrow’s NBA?: A Comparison of the Atlanta Hawks’ and Dallas Mavericks’ Offenses" /><published>2020-04-07T12:04:51-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T12:04:51-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/HawksMavs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/HawksMavs">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/hawksMavs/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Photo by Kyle Terada&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When All-Stars Trae Young and Luka Doncic were swapped for each other on the day they were drafted in 2018, nobody could have predicted the offensive numbers they both would be putting up today. They weren't traded for each other straight up, with the Mavericks forking over a draft pick along with the rights to Trae Young. Doncic was highly valued at the time because he was dominant in the second-most competitive basketball league in the world, winning the Euroleague MVP before his 20th birthday. He was generally viewed as a polished, NBA-ready prospect. Trae Young, on the other hand, had popular media questioning both his defense and the sustainability of his uncanny long-range shooting ability. Some media outlets pointed at him as one of the prospects with a chance of flopping in the NBA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over halfway through the 2019-20 season, both Doncic and Young are averaging better than an eye-popping 28.5 points and 8.5 assists per game, numbers that have only been seen from a few select offensive juggernauts: Oscar Robinson, Tiny Archibald, LeBron James, Russell Westbrook, and James Harden. Neither Doncic nor Young is great on the defensive side of the ball, so it's more entertaining to focus on what they're doing to help their teams score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/hawksMavs/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Photo by Scott Cunningham&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sensational sophomores have been the beneficiaries of an offensive trend that some NBA teams are leaning into. To sum it up, these teams are running their offenses more than ever before through their single biggest playmaking and scoring threat. They're spacing the floor around them with shooters so that the star player has room to either score or disrupt the defense enough to find an open teammate, taking the role of a point guard to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trend can be seen statistically by the recent rise in players with high scoring and assist rates per 100 possessions. The graph below shows that the levels of pace adjusted scoring and assisting we're seeing from individual players in today's NBA are historically unprecedented. This increase in reliance on the best offensive player on the court has led to awesome levels of production from the modern NBA stars we all know and love like Giannis, Damian Lillard, and LeBron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/hawksMavs/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Doncic and Young, who are both exceptional passers and crafty scorers with seemingly limitless range, this offensive philosophy has led to their teams putting them in tons of pick and roll ball-handling situations, and both have performed brilliantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to miss the greatness of superstar Slovenian, Luka Doncic. His Mavericks have by far the best offensive rating in the league, which measures a team's offensive efficiency. Their current mark of 116.1 is the best offensive rating according to NBA.com since 1996 where their data ends. Doncic is already regarded among the NBA elite with only the Greek Freak having better odds to win 2019-20 NBA MVP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hawks, on the other hand, have struggled mightily to score the ball, and this lack of success has tainted the reputation Trae Young deserves as one of the league's top offensive players. The Hawks offensive struggles can be seen by their 105.6 offensive rating, which puts them near the bottom of the league. It takes a bit of below-the-surface analysis to see that the inefficiency of the Hawks offense led by Trae Young has had a lot to do with the pieces that surrounded the sharpshooter, or more accurately, the lack thereof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-trade deadline Atlanta Hawks and Dallas Mavericks without their young stars are polar opposites in terms of their depth. The Hawks completely lacked a second scoring option with their productive power forward John Collins suspended for 25 games. As a result, the 43 year-old Vince Carter is averaging more than 15 minutes per game, which illustrates the Hawks' lack of options. Without another player with a significant offensive impact, Young is forced to carry the load offensively for the Hawks. This makes Young's success even more impressive as he is averaging nearly 30 points per game at the All-Star break, even though opposing teams are solely preparing to stop him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, the Dallas Mavericks have Kristaps Porzingis to shoulder some of the offensive load and draw the defense's attention away from Doncic. Porzingis is a problem to stop because his size allows him to bully guards, and he can stretch more traditional post players with his outside shooting. So far this season he is averaging almost 20 points-per-game with a 35% three-point field goal percentage. Recently, he has been putting up bigger numbers, possibly catching his stride as he did not play all of last season due to an ACL tear. In 6 of the last 11 games that he has played in, he has scored more than 25 points, and has reached 38 points twice during that stretch. The Mavs offense is multi-dimensional, which softens up defenses for Doncic to pick apart. Additionally, role players such as Seth Curry, Tim Hardaway, Dorian Finney-Smith and Maxi Kleber are limiting defense's help-side willingness with their 38% or greater three-point field goal percentages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following chart illustrates the discrepancy between the offensive production by each player on the Mavericks and the Hawks for players who have played in at least 15 games. Box plots are shown for each team comparing their Offensive Box Plus/Minus (OBPM). Basketball-Reference defines OBPM as &quot;[a] box score estimate of the offensive points per 100 possessions a player contributed above a league-average player, translated to an average team.&quot; Clearly Young and Doncic standout as high-side outliers, which demonstrates their enormous offensive impacts. More importantly, though, the Atlanta Hawks mean OBPM is about the same as the lowest value for the Mavericks. Nearly all Hawks players are below league average compared with the Mavericks, whose median player OBPM is above league average. Young just lacks the support from his teammates on offense that Doncic benefits from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/hawksMavs/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hawks noticed their shortcomings at the trade deadline and doubled down on building a supporting cast for Young. They brought in five new players with the idea that their roster could be competitive as soon as next year. Jeff Teague and Treveon Graham were added from Minnesota. Teague, the former Hawk, is a capable backup point guard, even as he gets up there in years. In a four-team trade, Atlanta managed to snag Clint Capela and Nene Hilario. Capela is the key part of this trade because he is a big body in the point that blocks shots and pulls down rebounds. Additionally, he is a lob threat in the pick-and-roll game that has had plenty of practice in a similar position with James Harden. He should fit in with Atlanta's offense too because he allows John Collins to be a lethal perimeter threat. The Hawks' final move was acquiring the seven-foot Dewayne Dedmon, who can fill in as Capela's back up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlanta's offense looks to be much more deadly after the All-Star break as Young will have two new centers to use in the pick-and-roll. To help space the floor, they still have Kevin Huerter, who shoots 3 pointers at a 41% clip, and John Collins, who is still establishing himself after his suspension and now can spend more time on the perimeter. The Hawks will not become a multi-dimensional scoring machine like the Dallas Mavericks overnight, but they are taking steps in the right direction to help Young be successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/hawksMavs/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Photo by Kyle Terada&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the coming off-season, the Hawks could still grow more because of their significant cap space available. John Hollinger of The Athletic reports that Atlanta will have the most cap space of any team this off-season with nearly $48 million. They could be a very enticing landing spot for a skilled player, who is looking to cash-in on their talent and support a team that could be starting to trend upward. Moreover, even if the Hawks do not turn around this season for whatever reason, they are in a perfect position to receive a high lottery pick and either add young talent to their roster or trade it away for a proven player. The Atlanta Hawks have decided that they are Trae Young's team and are finding ways to put offensive weapons around him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at the 2018 NBA Draft, it is impossible to know what would have happened if Young and Doncic were not traded for each other that night. However, it is an interesting thought-experiment to consider if Young's offensive talent would have translated to helping the Maverick's offense develop into what it currently is. They are both offensively-gifted, young players who will continue to grow and impact the NBA, but the talent surrounding them thus far in their careers is vastly different. The remaining part of this season and next year could provide telling signs for what Young is able to accomplish with more weapons around him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: basketball-reference.com, theathletic.com, stats.nba.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Oscar O'Brien</name></author><summary type="html">When All-Stars Trae Young and Luka Doncic were swapped for each other on the day they were drafted in 2018, nobody could have predicted the offensive numbers they both would be putting up today. They weren't traded for each other straight up, with the Mavericks forking over a draft pick along with the rights to Trae Young. Doncic was highly valued at the time because he was dominant in the second-most competitive basketball league in the world, winning the Euroleague MVP before his 20th birthday. He was generally viewed as a polished, NBA-ready prospect. Trae Young, on the other hand, had popular media questioning both his defense and the sustainability of his uncanny long-range shooting ability. Some media outlets pointed at him as one of the prospects with a chance of flopping in the NBA.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting Success: Why the White Sox are the Next Rays</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/WhiteSoxRays" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting Success: Why the White Sox are the Next Rays" /><published>2020-04-07T10:30:45-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T10:30:45-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/WhiteSoxRays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/WhiteSoxRays">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/whiteSoxRays/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: billboard.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Major League Baseball, it is notoriously difficult for a single player to lead a team to the playoffs, unlike sports such as basketball or football. With only a soft salary cap &amp;mdash; the luxury tax &amp;mdash; teams with more financial power have more playoff success than teams with little spending money. Since the modern luxury tax system was established in 2002, seven out of the eight top taxpayers have won a World Series, with the Detroit Tigers being the only exception. How then, do teams compete with these top spenders? Some try to match their spending, some cheat, and others try to come up with creative ways to stay afloat with these financial juggernauts. Generally, spending money is positively correlated with winning ball games. One immediately thinks of the Yankees, the most successful franchise in major league history, who seemingly sign every marquee free agent to a 9-figure contract. From the scatterplot of payroll against win percentage since 2008, some observations are immediately apparent. As payroll increases, win percentage increases. The Yankees, with an astronomical cumulative payroll (from 2008-2019) of $2,475,188,736, have the highest cumulative win percentage of .571 while the San Diego Padres and Miami Marlins, with cumulative payrolls less than $900,000,000, among the bottom five in the league, have the lowest two win percentages of around .452. Four of the top six teams in win percentage are also in the top six in payroll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/whiteSoxRays/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One team in particular, the Tampa Bay Rays, has consistently overcome a low payroll to vie for the divisional crown over the last few years against historical powerhouses in the New York Yankees and Boston Red Sox. Despite never being higher than 21st in team payroll obligations per season since 2008, the Rays have accumulated 5 playoff appearances in arguably the toughest division in the league, including a 2008 trip to the World Series. From 2008 to 2019, the Rays have had the lowest cumulative payroll obligation, a paltry sum of $777,941,938, but have accrued a winning percentage of .533, a top-five figure in the league. How then, can a team best known for its historically poor attendance and almost universally disliked home park, the Trop, win so many ball games? In order to overcome their monetary deficiencies, the Rays have employed innovative methods such as being one of the first teams to consistently employ the defensive shift, using the opener, and giving contract extensions to young players with less than a year of service time. They've also recently made savvy, seemingly lopsided trades in their favor and have a stacked farm system (#1 in the league according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baseballamerica.com/rankings/2020-mlb-organization-talent-rankings/&quot;&gt;BaseballAmerica's 2020 preseason report&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Allergic to Superstars&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rays have historically been hesitant to give out large free agent contracts, much to the chagrin of their fanbase. The largest contract the team has given out in their relatively short 21 year history was a $100 million contract to Evan Longoria, their franchise player now on the San Francisco Giants. By avoiding the mega-contract, they've avoided being handicapped with their already limited financial means. Let's look at some of the $200+ million contracts signed at least five years ago, avoiding the most recent signings so we can assess player performance through part of the life of the contract. Perhaps the most notorious of these is Albert Pujols' 10-year, $240 million deal with the Angels in 2012. Pujols was a veritable first-ballot Hall of Famer through his first eleven years with the St. Louis Cardinals, racking up three MVP awards with a .328 average (AVG), .420 on-base percentage (OBP), and .617 slugging percentage (SLG) contributing to a 1.037 OPS, with a 170 OPS+ (OPS+ is normalized for park factors and is relative to the rest of the league; a league average OPS+ is 100, and 170 is 70% better than the average hitter). He accumulated 86.6 Wins Above Replacement (WAR) which is a general overall performance statistic, taking offensive and defensive capabilities into account. In eight years since joining the Los Angeles Angels, he's accumulated just 13.7 WAR for a triple slash line of .258/.314/.450 with an OPS+ of 110. Even though he is a below average first baseman now, the Angels still trot him out every day, citing the enormous, backloaded contract as the reason. This contract has seriously inhibited the Angels, who haven't made the playoffs in five years, even with the presence of the consensus best player in baseball, Mike Trout. Other examples include Miguel Cabrera's 8-year, $240 million contract signed in 2016 with the Detroit Tigers and Robinson Cano's 10-year, $240 million contract signed with the Seattle Mariners in 2014. Although performing at an above-average level for the first five years, the rebuilding Mariners decided to trade him in 2018 to the New York Mets, including 2018 American League Reliever of the Year, Edwin Diaz, to get rid of the contract. Although there have been a few contracts worth the length (such as the Max Scherzer deal with the Washington Nationals), most of these deals have the players playing at an above-average level for the first few years while declining due to age for the latter part. These mega-contracts are also typically backloaded, with the average annual value (AAV) doled out increasing for the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn't to say spending money on free agents is a bad thing; the graph above plotting payroll vs. win percentage says otherwise. Teams like the Rays succeed in wise spending. They pick up players who won't demand a large sum, signing players whose once top-prospect pedigree has flamed out, like Avisail Garcia, who had a triple slash of .282/.332/.464 for a 111 OPS+ - solidly above average - or players who GMs think can't continue their success with a new team, like Charlie Morton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/whiteSoxRays/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: nypost.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morton never figured it out in Pittsburgh, pitching to the tune of a 4.39 ERA, but became elite during his two year tenure with the Astros. Most teams, thinking his success was unsustainable at age 35 and attributing it to pitching coach savant Brent Strom, passed on him. The Rays decided to give him a short two year, $30 million deal with a third year vesting option, which adds a third year if the player achieves         outlined incentives. Morton went on to post a career-best 3.05 ERA, landing third in American League Cy Young voting. They also choose decent, high floor players, who probably won't play at an elite level, but historically have shown that they're consistently above average. Ben Zobrist (36 WAR over 9 seasons) and Tommy Pham (6.3 WAR over 1.5 seasons) fall into this camp. The Rays also sign players who don't live up to expectations with their previous club, in hopes that a change of scenery and new coaching will allow them to reach their potential. Some of these players include Ji-Man Choi (3 WAR in 1.5 seasons) and Fernando Rodney, who accrued 48 saves and had a then-record 0.60 ERA in 2012 after a poor showing in Anaheim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/whiteSoxRays/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Farm System&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph above shows the proportion of team WAR that comes from homegrown (draftees and those coming via trade) players and free agent acquisitions for each of the top five teams in winning percentage in the previous graph. The proportions are cumulative from the last three 90+ win seasons for each team. This was done because often times rebuilding teams don't sign free agents and instead send out their young players to gain experience, regardless of whether they're major-league caliber or not. This can lead to the homegrown portion of the team WAR being skewed. It is evident in the bar graph that from their last three 90+ win seasons, the Rays have the highest proportion of their team WAR coming from trades and draft picks, with the Yankees following. Due to the volatility of trades, teams like the Rays emphasize their farm system depth. The Rays' farm system has been ranked in the top five each of the last six years. They have the consensus top prospect in baseball, Wander Franco, and have produced superstars such as David Price, Evan Longoria, Scott Kazmir, and Blake Snell. This is extremely impressive noting the fact that the Rays have only been around for 21 years. They've already produced two Cy Young winners, a testament to their investment in the farm system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/whiteSoxRays/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: nytimes.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Increasing Popularity of Prospect Extensions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rays fans often complain about the team not keeping players by paying them when it comes to free agency. They have a point. Because of their small payroll, the team cannot afford to pay their homegrown stars once their rookie contracts end and they hit free agency. In attempting to remedy this, the team has stumbled upon another innovative move: signing players with barely any major league service time to a major league extension. The idea seems incredibly risky, considering how often even first-round picks flame out. The Rays appear confident in their abilities to properly assess the future of certain prospects. In 2008, with only 24 days of service time under his belt, they signed future franchise icon Evan Longoria to a six-year, $17.5 million deal. This was a gamble at the time, since it was a significant sum of money to pay a player in Longoria who did not seem to have star potential. Now, in his age-34 season, he is set to make more than $15 million per year for the next three years. The original deal now looks extremely team-friendly, almost to the detriment of Longoria, but has now spawned numerous other similar deals. The Rays inked Matt Moore to a five-year, $14 million deal in 2011 where he went on to pitch to a solid 3.88 ERA in six years with the club. Some of the deals they've inspired have been even more daring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/whiteSoxRays/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Sox signed prospect Luis Robert to a six-year, $50 million extension before he even made his MLB debut, and the Mariners signed first baseman Evan White to a six-year, $24 million deal. If these players break out, the teams have potential superstars for pennies. If they don't pan out, the team will pay a small sum, in this current age, to a player who has now secured their financial future. Below is a dot plot showing the increasing occurrence of extensions given to players who haven't made their MLB debuts, evidence of the Rays once again being on the cusp of innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;White Sox&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for the fun part: trying to determine who will be the next Rays. Based on our research, we believe that the Chicago White Sox will fill that role for the coming season. Like the Rays, the White Sox sit on the lower end of the MLB spending spectrum, with a budget of $118 million, which sits just below the league average of $129 million. And while the Sox are undoubtedly bigger spenders than their counterparts in Tampa, their reputation in the 2010s was similar to that of the Rays. The teams were both notoriously bad, with few-to-no big names and below .500 records for the majority of the decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Signings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big names of this offseason have come and gone. Gerritt Cole, Anthony Rendon, Madison Bumgardner, and now David Price and Mookie Betts, have all left their former teams. Like we noted in the above section on superstar signings, baseball is unique in that a single superstar, or even two, does not make a team good, much less a contender (the stats behind that are ones for another paper). This is why the MLB draft is not as significant as their counterparts in the NBA or NFL. The White Sox are far more privy to what we like to call the MLB's &quot;B-list&quot;. Former or declining stars, young and unproven but talented players, and those middle of the liners that simply aren't superstars all make up this class of players. This is where the White Sox have made their mark. Last year, the White Sox were notably starved for any sort of veteran leadership, and this offseason, they made multiple changes to fix that issue. They signed Dallas Keuchel and Gio Gonzalez, as well as Edwin Encarnacion and Yasmani Grandal to contracts. These players definitely fall into the low-risk, high-reward column of players, and could serve the White Sox well. And, if they don't, there is no multi hundred million dollar contract that they are bound to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Young Guns-White Sox Farm System and Young Signees&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five names that stick out for non-veterans on the White Sox: Giolito, Anderson, Moncada, Abreu, and Jimenez. Over the course of the late 2010s, these players all took turns establishing themselves as solid players. Abreu has sneakily been one of the best players in the MLB, with three top-25 finishes for MVP in six years in the league, as well as a career batting average of .293, and more than 100 RBI in five seasons. He is currently signed to a one-year deal for 18 million dollars, making him one of the White Sox' heftier contracts, but is still neatly settled beneath the 20 million a year mark. Eloy Jimenez and Tim Anderson are also signed to two smaller-end contracts for six years, 43 million dollars and six years, 25 million dollars respectively. Jimenez, who was a Rookie of the Year finalist for the 2019 season, slugged an impressive 31 home runs and looks to continue the impressive campaign this year. Anderson effectively broke out in 2019, leading the American League in batting average. And while his performance seems most likely to be an anomaly, Anderson certainly holds the skills in his toolbox to repeat. As of March of 2020, Moncada is rumored to sign a new contract with the White Sox, a five year, 70 million dollar extension, joining the Sox' class of superstars making less than 20 million dollars a year, as well as effectively locking him up through his mid-to-late twenties prime. The last of the White Sox' &quot;bargain bin&quot; players is definitely one of the best values in the league: Lucas Giolito. Coming off being probably the worst pitcher in the league in 2018 (led in earned runs and walks), Giolito returned in 2019 with an amazing campaign. He finished sixth in Cy Young voting, with three complete games and two shutouts. However, the best aspect of Giolito: he is eligible for an arbitration contract, and with his less-than-consistent past, he will most likely not be given a large contract by the arbitrators. These five players make up the heart of the White Sox' homegrown/young core, and they look to be this year's Rays, a team that has mostly mid-to-low cost stars who are all coming off of some of the biggest years of their careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/whiteSoxRays/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Forbes&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there it is &amp;mdash; our prediction for the newest success in the MLB. Will the White Sox win a title? Almost definitely not. The current sports trend is to create superteams, and with the Dodgers, Red Sox, Yankees, and Cubs building teams by picking up stars for huge sums of money, a small-spending team will have a tough time beating all of them. But the Rays are a team on the rise, and they did so by making smart signings and relying on their own homegrown players who came into their own at the perfect time. This year, all signs point towards the White Sox to make this jump into the upper-middle echelons of the MLB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: stevetheump.com, baseball-reference.com, baseballamerica.com, sportsrac.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Luke Ito</name></author><summary type="html">In Major League Baseball, it is notoriously difficult for a single player to lead a team to the playoffs, unlike sports such as basketball or football. With only a soft salary cap &amp;mdash; the luxury tax &amp;mdash; teams with more financial power have more playoff success than teams with little spending money. Since the modern luxury tax system was established in 2002, seven out of the eight top taxpayers have won a World Series, with the Detroit Tigers being the only exception. How then, do teams compete with these top spenders? Some try to match their spending, some cheat, and others try to come up with creative ways to stay afloat with these financial juggernauts. Generally, spending money is positively correlated with winning ball games. One immediately thinks of the Yankees, the most successful franchise in major league history, who seemingly sign every marquee free agent to a 9-figure contract. From the scatterplot of payroll against win percentage since 2008, some observations are immediately apparent. As payroll increases, win percentage increases. The Yankees, with an astronomical cumulative payroll (from 2008-2019) of $2,475,188,736, have the highest cumulative win percentage of .571 while the San Diego Padres and Miami Marlins, with cumulative payrolls less than $900,000,000, among the bottom five in the league, have the lowest two win percentages of around .452. Four of the top six teams in win percentage are also in the top six in payroll.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Coin Toss</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CoinToss" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Coin Toss" /><published>2020-03-30T00:41:53-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-30T00:41:53-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CoinToss</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CoinToss">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;width:47.83%; float: left;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: neilleifer.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;width:52.17%; float:right&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: thebiglead.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Introduction&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A coin toss is just a flip of the coin, but in recent years-especially during the NFL playoffs-it has seemingly gained heightened importance. A prime example of this is the coin toss of the Super Bowl: in the early years, only the select few captains and a single referee met at midfield in a very quick exchange. Today, however, things are drastically different, as a small village of camera crews and important individuals accompany the captains to film the result of the coin toss. Moreover, mantras about which option to choose (&quot;tails never fails&quot;) have emerged, the coin is specially engraved for the occasion, and Las Vegas sportsbooks create a prop bet on whether the result of the coin toss will be &lt;i&gt;heads&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;tails&lt;/i&gt;, indicating the grandiosity of what should be an insignificant event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These decisions, in turn, have led to an increase in the talk about &quot;coin toss strategy,&quot; if such a thing even exists. We wanted to see if there is any validity to this talk, or if people were just blowing smoke. The coin toss doesn't seem like the type of event to make or break a game, so we were wondering why people pay so much attention to its outcome and their team's decision. For the purpose of this article, we have limited the games we will be investigating to the playoff games between the 2002 and 2019 NFL seasons to impose &lt;i&gt;somewhat&lt;/i&gt; of an equal playing field (i.e. there are no 0-15 teams facing a 13-2 team).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason we chose to compare the 2002-2006 era to 2015-2019 was because coin toss data was not easy to find before this era.  In addition, deferring seems to have become the prevalent choice in recent years, but was this the case 18 years ago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;NFL Playoff Coin Tosses:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown by the graph above, when comparing the results of the coin toss decision (defer vs. receive) between two different eras (2002-2006 and 2015-2019) for the NFL Playoffs, the percent of decisions resulting in a deferral drastically increased, from around 5% to around 85%. In fact, when performing a test for difference of proportions with a null hypothesis of no difference and an alternative that there is &lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt; difference (either positive or negative), we obtained a p-value of , indicating that we would reject the null hypothesis. It appears that the percentage of coin tosses that resulted in a deferral decision has statistically significantly increased from the era of 2002 - 2006 to 2015 - 2019, as we expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to 2002 playoff games, we calculated the overall deferral percentage in the playoffs for that year and compared it to the win rate of the teams that deferred to understand if there was a correlation between deferring the coin toss and winning the game. On the x-axis we plotted the year up to the 2019 season and on the y-axis the win rate as a proportion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of deferral percentage, the data plotted clearly suggest an upward trend in recent years. In fact, to our surprise whereas up until 2006 no team deferred more than three times, in recent years no team has received more than three times. Perhaps misleadingly, the win percentage for those years is either at 1.0 or 0.0 as there was not a large sample size of defers to choose from, thus polarizing the figures. Interestingly, as the deferral percentage among teams rises, the win percentage caps at roughly 0.5. In the early years of the deferral revolution (2010-2012), winning percentages see a significant increase -- perhaps suggesting that deferring contributed to a team's overall success in the game. However, as the trend takes off from 2015 onward, nearly every team defers if they win the toss. Consequently, the win percentage tumbles, before leveling off around 0.5. This is because teams today no longer have an advantage when every single team is doing the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To confirm this belief we took to plotting the opposite trend: going back to 2002 playoff games, we calculated the overall receive percentage in the playoffs for that year and compared it to the win rate of the teams that recieved. While the receive percentage is simply the inverse of the deferral percentage plot (blue), the receive win percentage draws on a whole new sample size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming the previous hypothesis is correct, it is expected that from 2002-2006 while the receive percentage is at a league high, the win percentage should be stagnant around 0.5. However, from 2010-2012, the percentage should be lower, as teams transition into a new meta of deferring before finally jumping between the two extremes of 0.0 and 1.0 with a small sample size of teams receiving from 2015 onward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting the hypothesis, the 2002-2006 sector corroborates the idea that when all teams are doing the same thing, in this case receiving, the win percentage is roughly even. The year 2010 illuminates seemingly a major turning point for the league. Recall that in 2010 60% of teams deferred and of those teams they won 40% of their games. However, of the teams that received (the remaining 40%), they won 0% of the games for the only time in the 18 year window. Additionally, skipping to 2015 when all the teams begin to defer, this leaves a small group going against the grain by receiving. Just as in the defer group from 2002-2006, this group of those who receive from 2015 onward have an average 0.8 win rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this point we've proven that from the years 2002-2006, NFL teams were likely to receive should they win the toss. Moreover, from 2015 onward, the reverse is true: NFL teams are more likely to defer than to receive. We decided to plot the deferral rate as a proportion on the timeline by round. We expected that as the games got &quot;bigger,&quot; the teams would become more likely to either receive or defer -- dependent on what was in style at the time. In other words, from 2015 onward, it's assumed that the deferral rate should increase from the wild card to the super bowl -- not only because the games are more important but also due to the sample size. On the x-axis we plotted the year and on the y-axis the deferral proportion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, in those two major time periods, the trend is true: for all ten of those years in the conference championship and super bowl, teams picked the popular trend at the time (meaning 30/30 times the team picked the popular choice). Additionally, for the last decade the team that has won the toss at the super bowl has chosen to defer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, we wanted to see &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; teams switched from receiving the football to deferring to the second half upon winning the coin toss. Was it because that strategy was &quot;better&quot;? Bill Belichick is renowned for deferring to the second half, as it provides his team with the opportunity to &quot;double up&quot; just before and just after half time: if his team can score at the end of the first half, then, by receiving the ball to start the second half, they have the chance to score again; this provides the team with the chance at a big momentum swing of up to two possessions (i.e. sixteen points). By considering this strategy, it would appear that deferring is the better decision and that the teams which defer would be expected to have a higher win percentage than the teams which receive after winning the coin toss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above bar graph displays the win percentages for teams that won the coin toss separated by their decisions to (1) defer and (2) receive for all years in the data set (2002 - 2019). As depicted, there was no significant difference in win percentage between teams that deferred versus teams that received &lt;i&gt;on the whole&lt;/i&gt;, indicating that the sole decision of deferring versus receiving does not help a team in the playoffs. However, as some of the graphics displayed earlier in the article convey, this percentage could vary depending on the year and whether deferring was considered &quot;popular&quot;. When further looking at the data, it is interesting to note that the win percentages hover around 0.45 for teams that won the coin toss regardless of decision, leading us to wonder whether teams that won the coin toss in the playoffs had a statistically lower win percentage than teams that lost the coin toss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When comparing the win percentages for teams that won the coin toss against teams that lost it, we performed a hypothesis test for difference of proportions to see whether the observed difference was statistically significant. Since the p-value for this two-sided test was 0.0562, at the significance level, we fail to reject the null hypothesis that the percentages are different. What this means is that the likelihood of observing this difference of win percentage in a sample given that there really is no difference in the population is 5.62%; since our cutoff for that assumption being wrong is 5%, we say that we cannot reject the statement that the win percentage is different for these two categories. However, this p-value is still pretty low (almost significant), so we may want to investigate this issue further. While winning or losing the coin toss will not &lt;i&gt;directly&lt;/i&gt; determine whether or not a team wins the game, there could be confounding variables inherent to the data and to playoff games that could impact the relationship between the coin toss outcome and win percentage. One such example would be overthinking, as the team which won the coin toss would overcomplicate the decision and ultimately make a poor one. Another potential confounding variable would be the peril of herd mentality: as more and more teams are opting to defer, they may be opting to defer for the sole reason that other teams are making the same choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams have increasingly analyzed the coin toss and its effect on the game, in turn flipping the script from almost every team receiving the ball to almost every team choosing to get the ball in the second half. This change has become so prevalent that many football fans are outraged when their team &lt;i&gt;doesn't&lt;/i&gt; defer after winning the coin toss. However, blindly choosing to defer has its own pitfalls: teams are not thinking about their decision at all but merely going with the flow, which could have negative consequences if they are not prepared. Just like football, making a decision from the coin toss is dynamic and adaptive: each opponent is different, each team is different, and each game is different. Making the decision just because everyone else does it has perils of its own, and when looking at the data, the teams that generally saw an increase in their success were the ones that began this deferral trend and deferred when all anyone considered was receiving the ball and having the first possession. Maybe with an increasing number of teams choosing to defer, the right decision is to go against the grain and choose to receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then again, it's all just the flip of a coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: ESPN, Pro Football Reference&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ethan Allavarpu</name></author><summary type="html">A coin toss is just a flip of the coin, but in recent years-especially during the NFL playoffs-it has seemingly gained heightened importance. A prime example of this is the coin toss of the Super Bowl&amp;colon; in the early years, only the select few captains and a single referee met at midfield in a very quick exchange. Today, however, things are drastically different, as a small village of camera crews and important individuals accompany the captains to film the result of the coin toss. Moreover, mantras about which option to choose (&quot;tails never fails&quot;) have emerged, the coin is specially engraved for the occasion, and Las Vegas sportsbooks create a prop bet on whether the result of the coin toss will be heads or tails, indicating the grandiosity of what should be an insignificant event.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Team With the Best Clutch Gene</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ClutchGene" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Team With the Best Clutch Gene" /><published>2020-03-30T00:11:10-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-30T00:11:10-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ClutchGene</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ClutchGene">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: wallpapersafari.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2013 NBA Finals, Ray Allen hit arguably one of the most significant shots of the decade. With the rival San Antonio Spurs just seconds away from another NBA championship, Allen converted an offensive rebound into a 3 point shot to tie the game, send it to overtime and eventually secure a vital win. The Heat ended up winning the series and the championship and as a result, Ray Allen's three became one of the most memorable shots in recent history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did that shot change the outcome of the series, but it also fundamentally altered the narrative surrounding Lebron James &quot;taking his talents to South beach&quot;, creating the Big three, and marking the beginning of the superteam era. Without that shot, that &quot;superteam&quot; , having already fallen short once to an underdog Dallas Mavericks team, would once and for all have been labelled an underwhelming, failed endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NBA games consist of 2 and 3 point shots, but the context and time at which these shots are taken play a crucial role in determining the idea of clutch. According to the NBA, &quot;clutch time&quot; is defined as the last 5 minutes of a game in which the point differential is 5 or less. While discussions on the topic of clutch are usually centered around individual players, we shift our focus to teams and their ability to close out games in crunch time. We will spend more time discussing the teams' overall statistics during clutch time rather than specific plays made by individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Absolute vs Relative Clutch Win Percentage&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1 - Absolute Clutch Win Percentage&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2 - Relative Clutch Win Percentage&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 shows the value of a team's win percentage in clutch games subtracted by its overall win percentage. This is essentially the change in a team's win probability as they enter clutch time. A positive value would indicate that the team usually performs better in clutch situations than in regular games while a negative value would suggest that the team typically performs worse in clutch games. This method allows us to figure out which teams truly excel in clutch time by adjusting for their typical win percentage. For example, if we only look at the Charlotte Hornets's win percentage in the clutch, they come in at the middle of the pack at 51.9%. However, if we compare this to their season win percentage at 33.3%, we can observe that the Hornets have high relative success in clutch games and are deserving of being considered as more than just your average team in the clutch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads us to the question of whether a team's absolute or relative clutch win percentage reveals more about the clutchness of a team. To start off, we will define a team's clutchness to be its ability to adapt and perform better in the final moments of a close game. By this definition, a very clutch team should be a team that is able to take advantage of the close game they are in and play more efficiently than in other situations. We believe that the relative clutch win percentage (RCWP) would be able to model this quality of a team better than the absolute clutch win percentage (ACWP) because the RCWP accounts for the fact that not all teams are equally skilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Toronto Raptors are currently 4th in the league with a season win percentage of 72.7%. They also happen to be 4th when ranked by ACWP at 64.3%, so does this mean that they are the 4th clutchest team in the league? Well, if we look at how they usually perform versus their clutch performances, we can see that their win percentage dips by 8.4% in the latter, which may suggest that they might not be as good in the clutch as we thought. It is clear that the Raptors are 4th in ACWP rankings primarily because they are a very skilled team and are usually able to win games. However, since their performance in clutch situations suffers a considerable amount relative to all other games, they should not be considered a top clutch team. By using the RCWP to rank our teams, we are able to assess how well a team is able to improve its chances of winning in clutch games by isolating its clutch factor from its regular performance. The point here is that the team that wins the highest percentage of clutch games is not necessarily the team with the best clutch gene. As long as teams perform better in clutch time than in other situations, they are candidates of being considered as one of the top clutch teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Adjusted Offensive Rating&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3 - Adjusted Offensive Rating&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offensive rating is how many points the team scores per 100 possessions. The adjusted offensive rating (AOR) is the value obtained when the clutch offensive rating is subtracted by the overall offensive rating. This value is basically how many more points a team scores in the clutch per 100 possessions than in other situations. The Charlotte Hornets lead this chart with a 15.2 point rating increase, and the Dallas Mavericks suffer the most with a 21 point rating decrease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Adjusted Defensive Rating&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4 - Adjusted Defensive Rating&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defensive rating is how many points their opponent scores per 100 possessions. The adjusted defensive rating (ADR) is the value calculated when the overall defensive rating is subtracted by the clutch defensive rating. This value is essentially the decrease in their opponent's points per 100 possessions, so the higher the value of this decrease, the better. The Atlanta Hawks lead this metric with a 17.4 point decrease and the Chicago Bulls' defense suffers the most in clutch with a 14.8 point increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Adjusted Net Rating&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 5 - Adjusted Net Rating&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The net rating is calculated by subtracting the defensive rating from the offensive rating, with a higher offensive rating and a lower defensive rating being desirable. Applying the same principle as the adjusted win percentage, we believe that the best metric to determine the team with the best clutch gene is the team with the highest adjusted net rating (ANR) during clutch moments. The offensive rating and defensive rating are essentially measures of a team's efficiency. By using this metric instead of the adjusted win percentage, we are not discounting any losing teams who may have had a great performance in the clutch. Since we previously defined clutch to be a team's ability to perform well in clutch moments, a measure of their improvement in efficiency dictated by the points scored by both teams, whether they won or lost, would best fit our definition to determine the team with the best clutch gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Relative Clutch Win Percentage Based on Number of All-Star Appearance&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(excluded players with less than 10 games)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While looking at contributing factors for clutchness, we wanted to see whether the amount of talent or star power plays a role in a team's ability to close out in the clutch. We tested this by plotting the total number of All Star appearances for each team against their win percentage in &quot;clutch time&quot;. From the graph, most of the teams with a high clutch win percentage are heavily on the left, with fewer All Star appearances. This shows that teams' wins in the clutch aren't impacted by an individual star's performance; it is independent of how much talent an individual player may have. A possible explanation could be that overall team performance in clutch time overshadows individuals' performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the relative clutch win percentage, we can see that the Charlotte Hornets' win percentage in the clutch increases by 18.6% when compared to their overall win percentage, the highest improvement in the league. This was followed closely by their change in field goal percentage. With an increase of 6% in the clutch, this was also the best improvement among all NBA teams, with the average change in field goal percentage being a 3.81% decrease in the clutch. However, since we want to look at each team's performance during clutch time rather than if they just won or lost, we should look at their adjusted offensive and defensive ratings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Charlotte Hornets still lead the league with an adjusted offensive rating of 15.2 with the Oklahoma City Thunder following closely behind at 13.9. These two teams' AORs are more than double the value of any other team, making them top contenders to be the top clutch team. If we move to the teams' adjusted defensive rating, we can observe that the Atlanta Hawks are at the top with a score of 17.4, but since their AOR is a -13.4, they are not a top candidate. The Milwaukee Bucks are at second in ADR rankings at 16, and the Thunder and the Philadelphia Sixers are tied in 3rd place at 13.3. The Hornets' ADR rank at 11th at 6.4, which severely hurts their contention of being the best clutch team. Finally, if we look at the adjusted net rating, the Thunder come out on top with a score of 27.3 and the Hornets place second with a score of 21.6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these observations, we have come to the conclusion that the Oklahoma City Thunder are deserving of being named the team with the best clutch gene. Even though the Hornets perform very well offensively and are able to improve their win percentage greatly in clutch moments, their defensive performance hinders their stock of being the top clutch team. The Thunder have the greatest overall improvement in efficiency during clutch time as they have the best offensive efficiency and the third best defensive efficiency. In contrast, the Dallas Mavericks is the team with the worst clutch gene based off adjusted net rating, which is also reflected in their last place standing in adjusted win percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An assumption we made to arrive at our result was that during clutch moments, all teams face the same advantages and disadvantages against all opponents. However, this is unrealistic as this would change with each match. For example, a team with bad perimeter defense would be at a bigger disadvantage if the opponent specializes in 3-point shooting. Had they not faced a team that specializes in 3-point shooting during the clutch, their defensive rating might have been better. Given this assumption, we found that the Oklahoma City Thunder have the best ability to adapt and perform better in the final moments of a close game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: stats.nba.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wilson Yu</name></author><summary type="html">In the 2013 NBA Finals, Ray Allen hit arguably one of the most significant shots of the decade. With the rival San Antonio Spurs just seconds away from another NBA championship, Allen converted an offensive rebound into a 3 point shot to tie the game, send it to overtime and eventually secure a vital win. The Heat ended up winning the series and the championship and as a result, Ray Allen's three became one of the most memorable shots in recent history.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Legacy of Michael Phelps</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/MichaelPhelps" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Legacy of Michael Phelps" /><published>2020-03-29T23:34:39-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T23:34:39-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/MichaelPhelps</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/MichaelPhelps">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: mensjournal.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 28 Olympic gold medals, 27 World Championship gold medals, and 16 Pan Pacific Championship gold medals, Michael Phelps is the most decorated swimmer of all time. But Phelps' medals are just the beginning of his legacy. He has attended 5 Olympic Games, been named World Swimmer of the Year 7 times, and has set 39 world records--4 of which still stand today. His list of achievements goes on and on. In fact, many have acclaimed Phelps as 'the greatest swimmer of all time'. With his retirement in 2016, however, his achievements have flatlined. Now more than ever, the door is open for a new star to top his records and steal his title. The question is: Who could possibly rival Michael Phelps and the legacy that he has created?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this question, let's first take a more in-depth look at Michael Phelps' life to see how he was able to accomplish such impressive feats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Career&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Phelps began swimming competitively when he was in high school. It was during these years that he met his lifelong coach, Bob Bowman. Bowman quickly recognized Phelps' talent and soon began training him. By 1999, Phelps qualified for the U.S. National B Team. Just a year later, Phelps' time in the 200m Fly earned him a spot in the 2000 Summer Olympics. At the age of 15, Phelps was the youngest male swimmer to race in the Olympic Games in 68 years. Shown below is a table that documents Michale Phelps' placement races throughout his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in the year 2000, Phelps raced in every Olympic Games, World Championship, and Pan Pacific Championship until 2012. At the World Championship in 2001, Phelps brought home his first international gold medal. From this point on, Phelps went on a hot streak, taking home medal after medal--more often than not, gold medals. Michael Phelps' peak was likely the Olympic Games of 2008. This year, Phelps quite literally swept the field; he brought home a gold medal in every race that he participated in. Phelps' dominance continued until his retirement in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Physique&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While much of Phelps' success can be attributed to his work ethic, biology has nonetheless played a role. Michael Phelps' body is rather disproportionate; take his wing span for example. The average person's wingspan is about the same as his/her height. Phelps' wingspan, however, at an enormous 6' 7&quot;, is three inches longer than his height. His abnormally large wingspan allows him to generate more power with each stroke. While wingspan data doesn't exist for all professional swimmers, especially for those who raced in the twentieth century, we can take a look at how Phelps' wingspan stacks up against a few top-level competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among professional swimmers, an abnormally long wingspan is ironically all too common. While Phelps' wingspan is average, his ape span--the difference between one's height and wingspan--is among the highest in the group. With a large ape span, Phelps is reaping the benefits of a large wing span without the increase in weight that it typically comes with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: forbes.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to his wingspan, Michael Phelps has disproportionately small legs and a long torso. According to sports biographer Colleen de Bellefonds, &quot;Phelps has the torso of a man who's 6 feet 8 inches tall... and the legs of a man 8 inches shorter&quot; (bibliography.com). This means that his legs produce less drag than other swimmers of similar stature. The abnormalities continue with Phelps' hyperextended, size 14 feet. His feet are essentially flippers, working to propel him through the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we know a little bit more about Michael Phelps and his career, let's see if any current swimmer has a chance to rival his legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Analysis&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Michael Phelps is such a well-rounded athlete, with medals in four stroke categories--freestyle, butterfly, medley, and backstroke--it would be unfair to judge the entirety of his career based on his success in one of these groups. Instead, this analysis will take a more holistic approach, comparing swimmers based on their success in international championships&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Olympic Games&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micheal Phelps is perhaps best known for his performances in the Olympic Games, collecting 28 Olympic medals in five appearances. In 2016, when Michael Phelps retired from professional swimming, his medal count was unprecedented. Before Michael Phelps, the most decorated Olympian was Larisa Latynina, a Soviet gymnast of the 1960s who won a total of 18 medals. To get an idea of the success of Olympic swimmers before Michael Phelps, let's take a look at the graph below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many of these swimmers are amongst the 20 most decorated Olympians of all time, their medal counts pale in comparison to that of Michael Phelps. Furthermore, because all the swimmers on this list are retired, with the exception of 35 year old Ryan Lochte, none of them have a chance to surpass Phelps' medal count. But what about the younger generation of Olympic swimmers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any current Olympic swimmer were to break Phelps' record, he/she would have to be very young--no older than 25. The 20+ medal count advantage that Phelps has over any current swimmer would take many years to overcome. This swimmer would also need to have a few Olympic medals by now. Below is a table of all the current Olympic swimmers who fulfill these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of these 7 candidates, Katie Ledecky and Penny Oleksiak have the best chance of challenging the 28 medal record. Let's first talk about Katie Ledecky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: espn.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many followers of the professional swim scene consider Katie Ledecky to be the best female swimmer in the world. In her most recent Olympic appearance, Ledecky earned 5 medals. But she wasn't just placing top three in her events, she was winning them and often doing so by a significant margin. For example, in the 800m freestyle, she finished 12 seconds before the second place finisher! Katie Ledecky's dominance in events like these show her potential as an Olympic swimmer. As professional swimmers often retire in their early- to mid-30s, Ledecky will likely participate in four more Olympic Games. She will need to average approximately 6 medals per Olympics to tie Phelps' record. A challenging task, but certainly doable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: swimswam.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, Penny Oleksiak is a bit of a wildcard. In her first Olympic showing in 2016, Oleksiak won 4 medals--one gold, one silver, and two bronze. While Oleksiak walked away with only one medal less than Ledecky, her performance was far less convincing. Two of these medals were earned as a part of a 4 x 100m/200m team and her only gold medal was the result of a perfect tie. With this being said, Oleksiak is an incredibly young swimmer with plenty of time to improve. She is only 19 and could potentially compete in five more Olympic Games! With an average of 5 medals per Olympic showing, Oleksiak could become the most decorated Olympian of all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;FINA World Championships&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is more to swimming and an athlete's legacy than the Olympic Games. In the four years between one Olympic Games and the next, professional swimmers can compete in two World Championships and one Pan Pacific Championship. These events are a rare opportunity for professional swimmers to compete against their international competitors. As such, these competitions are taken very seriously. Because little data is available on the Pan Pacific Championship, we will focus on the World Championship in this analysis. Below is a table of the most successful swimmers in the history of the World Aquatics Championship (WAC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the Olympic Games, Michael Phelps' success at the WAC is unrivaled--for now. While Phelps is nonetheless the most decorated WAC swimmer, he has earned this title in a rather unconvincing fashion[b]. With 5 of the ten most accomplished swimmers of WAC history still competing, his title is far from safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shown above are the scatter plots and trend lines of the 5 active swimmers with the most WAC medals. The trend lines estimate each swimmer's potential medal count given their success in previous WACs and assuming he/she will compete until the age of 32. Let me use Caeleb Dressel's stats to explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: nbcsports.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Caeleb Dressel competed in his first WAC at the age of 20, earning medals in seven different events. At the 2019 WAC, Dressel one-upped his previous performance, adding 8 medals to his collection. Because Dressel averages 7.5 medals per WAC and he is only 23, this model estimates that he will earn more than 50 WAC medals by the end of his career! It is important to keep in mind, however, that this model is imperfect. It doesn't account for factors such as the effects of age on performance or the possibility of injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of this model's imperfections, the graphs above give us a general idea of each swimmer's potential. Among this group, Caeleb Dressel and Katie Ledecky stand out. Their potential WAC medal count--52 and 42 respectively--are well above Phelps'. Even if these athletes retire early or experience a slight drop-off in performance, they have a good shot at taking Phelps' WAC medal count record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a 22 year old with 6 Olympic medals and 18 WAC medals, Katie Ledecky is a top contender to rival Phelps' legacy. Right now, Ledecky seems unstoppable. With every passing meet, she seems to outpace her competitors by greater and greater margins. It seems unlikely that any swimmer will be able to match Ledecky in the near future. If Ledecky continues her dominant run of form, she will certainly put Phelps' legacy to the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: swimswam.com, olympic.org, fina.org, and usaswimming.org&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Fischer Sherrod</name></author><summary type="html">With 28 Olympic gold medals, 27 World Championship gold medals, and 16 Pan Pacific Championship gold medals, Michael Phelps is the most decorated swimmer of all time. But Phelps' medals are just the beginning of his legacy. He has attended 5 Olympic Games, been named World Swimmer of the Year 7 times, and has set 39 world records--4 of which still stand today. His list of achievements goes on and on. In fact, many have acclaimed Phelps as 'the greatest swimmer of all time'. With his retirement in 2016, however, his achievements have flatlined. Now more than ever, the door is open for a new star to top his records and steal his title. The question is&amp;colon; Who could possibly rival Michael Phelps and the legacy that he has created?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Story of Kyle Shanahan’s Offense and Where He Went Wrong in Super Bowl LIV</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/KyleShanahan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Kyle Shanahan’s Offense and Where He Went Wrong in Super Bowl LIV" /><published>2020-02-17T01:57:11-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-17T01:57:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/KyleShanahan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/KyleShanahan">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: San Francisco Chronicle&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing the 2016 season with 2 wins, the San Francisco 49ers decided it was time to try something new. They went into full-rebuild mode, giving six-year contracts to new head coach Kyle Shanahan and general manager John Lynch. Prior to their hiring, Shanahan was an accomplished play caller who was only 37 years old, while Lynch was a commentator for Fox Sports who had zero front office experience. It was certainly a gamble, but one that ultimately paid off as Shanahan and Lynch completely rebuilt the team from the ground up (46 of the 53 players on San Francisco’s roster were brought in by the new regime) and within three years, got the Niners to the Super Bowl for a shot at their sixth title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They ended up losing the game to Kansas City after holding a 10 point lead with under 10 minutes to play in the game, and blame has been thrown around various Niners players and coaches to explain the loss. But to truly understand what cost the 49ers the Super Bowl, it is important to know how this team really works and what makes it tick. Once you realize what this team really is, it becomes clear that it wasn't the defense or even the quarterback that cost the Niners the trophy; it was their play caller and head coach Kyle Shanahan himself. Let's look at Kyle Shanahan, the offense that he built in San Francisco, and what led to its fall in Super Bowl LIV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: New York Post&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle Shanahan is the son of Mike Shanahan, a former NFL coach considered by many to be one of the greatest offensive minds in NFL history (won Super Bowl XXIX with 49ers and XXXII and XXXIII with Broncos). Although Kyle played wide receiver at a Division-I school, he ultimately followed in his father's footsteps and became a coach in the NFL at a very young age. After spending years as an offensive quality control coach and quarterback coach with various teams, he got his first offensive coordinator job with the Houston Texans in 2008 at the age of 28. Over the next nine seasons, Shanahan served as the offensive coordinator for various teams and was incredibly successful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of the dysfunctional organization that is the Cleveland Browns, Shanahan was able to build all of his other offenses into Top-10 products. The 2016 Falcons were Shanahan's masterpiece; they displayed a surgical attack that scored the 7th most points in NFL history and netted quarterback Matt Ryan the league MVP award. They even took a commanding 25 point lead in Super Bowl LI before infamously blowing it and losing the game in the span of 22 minutes. The tough loss to end that historic season brings us to Shanahan's tenure in San Francisco as a head coach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Running Games Travel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Bleacher Report&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering his third season as the Niners head coach in 2019, after a couple of rocky and injury-riddled seasons to begin his head coaching career, Shanahan had finally put together the team he envisioned from the start in San Francisco. Despite coming off a previous job where he was known for his high-flying passing offense in Atlanta, he was still his father's son, and Mike Shanahan was known for finding unknown running backs and making them great behind a brilliant scheme. Kyle has been no different in San Francisco:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having three running backs, two of whom were not even drafted, in the Top-35 is a typical Shanahan staple. Mike Shanahan did this consistently in his time by having his backs play behind small but fast offensive lines. The goal was to open up gaping holes for the backs with speed and precision in blocking rather than pure power. The exact same philosophy went into the construction of San Francisco's offensive line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Niners have one of the NFL's best, if not the best, combination of light weight and speed in their offensive line. Having a line that gets downfield into the second and third levels of the defense faster than most allows San Francisco's running backs to gain huge chunks of yardage at a time and pick up tremendous speed while doing so. The average maximum speed by San Francisco's ball carriers on run plays this season was 13.27 MPH, the fastest in the NFL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 49ers rushing attack has Shanahan DNA smeared all over it, and Kyle Shanahan doesn't hesitate to make it the focal point of his entire offense. The Niners ran the ball on 51% of their offensive snaps this year, the second-highest clip in the NFL. But while the run game carried San Francisco to many wins, the other 49% of the offensive productivity was still important and proved to be the deciding factor in Super Bowl LIV. After all, Shanahan became a front-running head coaching candidate behind his creative aerial attack in Atlanta, which brings us to the hotly-debated man that Shanahan chose to be his quarterback in San Francisco: Jimmy Garoppolo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;What Do the Niners Have in Jimmy G?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: NBC Sports&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garoppolo receives copious amounts of criticism by most people who watch him, but he is in many ways exactly the quarterback that Kyle Shanahan wants to run his offense, and he put that on display in his first full year as a starter in 2019. To begin with, the beauty of Shanahan's offense comes on play action pass plays. His understanding of what defenders are instructed to do in certain situations combined with his running identity allows him to blow coverages wide open when he fakes handoffs and dials up plays downfield. This is what made Atlanta so deadly in 2016, and Garoppolo's ability to make splashes off of play action has allowed Shanahan to do the exact same thing in San Francisco:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garoppolo is given play action calls at the third-highest rate in the NFL, and while his overall passer rating is nothing special (101.8), play action Jimmy G. is the third-highest rated quarterback in the NFL (113.4). Shanahan dials up play action often, and Garoppolo gets the job done with incredible efficiency. On third down, Garoppolo's passer rating of 101.9 is also very solid. Moreover, Garoppolo does not throw the ball deep very often. In fact, his lack of deep ball throwing coupled with his tendency to throw the ball up for grabs every once in a while is what makes many critics lack faith in him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it appears that Garoppolo may be a poor deep ball thrower, his passer rating when going downfield is 105.2, almost 20 points above the league average and actually higher than Garoppolo's overall passer rating of 101.8. It's not that Garoppolo can't throw deep; Shanahan simply doesn't dial up such throws for him. Instead, Shanahan focuses the passing game on something else that explains Garoppolo's above-average rate of turnover worthy plays: the middle of the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Draft Kings Nation&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there's one statistic that the Niners offense is known for above anything else, it's YAC: Yards After the Catch. The way that Shanahan generates the YAC is by designing his plays to target the middle of the field, allowing his receivers to catch the ball with plenty of momentum and a lot of real estate around them so they can carry on for another chunk of yards before being tackled. This idea is well-reflected by Garoppolo's decisions on the field:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 70%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No quarterback in the NFL has a higher percentage of his targets go to routes that break inside than Garoppolo, as 50% of his throws go towards the middle of the field. Slinging the ball over the middle of the field constantly is surely dangerous, which explains Garoppolo's tendency to put the ball in harm's way more often than average. But Shanahan's philosophy is clear; he has built his passing game on the ability to gain YAC and, once again, Garoppolo has proven his ability to put that vision into action. Of the top 10 receivers and tight ends in the NFL for YAC, two play for the Niners:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shanahan brings in personnel based on his scheme that allows Garoppolo to thrive. Last year, when he was looking for a receiver, he could have easily drafted a monster like D.K. Metcalf who could out-muscle almost anyone, but he wasn't looking for size and strength. He instead drafted Deebo Samuel from South Carolina, a smaller player with speed, great hands, and fearlessness as a ball-carrier because those are the traits that make a great YAC receiver. George Kittle is no different at tight end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's clear that Shanahan has built every cubic centimeter of this offense the exact way that he wanted to. Garoppolo isn't asked to do too much thinking. Plays in the NFL where the quarterback doesn't have to make any read before throwing the ball (screen passes, etc.) are typically referred to as &quot;scheme&quot; looks. Garoppolo actually has the second highest percentage of such looks behind only rookie quarterback Kyler Murray:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 14&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing mysterious about Jimmy Garoppolo. The media wants to criticize him because he is not Aaron Rodgers or Patrick Mahomes, but Kyle Shanahan doesn't need him to be. He knows what he needs from Garoppolo and Garoppolo delivers it well: an efficient game manager who is good on third down and takes what Shanahan gives him down field. Sound familiar? There may be a certain six-time Super Bowl Champion quarterback with extremely similar traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the combination of a powerful run game and Garoppolo's efficiency in doing what Shanahan asks of him is what makes the Niners offense tick. This is the offense that Shanahan brought to the Super Bowl and ultimately failed with. The question we have finally arrived at is: what happened? The answer is rather complex, but can be simplified to one big idea. At the big moments in the game, Shanahan didn't become overly aggressive or even overly conservative. He instead became something worse than both of those things: scared and predictable. Chiefs quarterback Patrick Mahomes, with his ability to put up points in seconds, put enough fear into the 49ers play caller to the point that the flashy, quick, and creative Niners offense was reduced to a few predictable tendencies when it mattered most. As a result, Kansas City was able to pounce and take the trophy right out of Shanahan's hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Super Bowl LIV&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 15&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: The Mercury News&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a thorough understanding of San Francisco's offense, it's not hard to see that as they blossomed with Kyle Shanahan's play calling, they came crashing down just as fast when the puppet master himself made bad decisions. The Super Bowl started off fairly well for San Francisco; Shanahan opened the game with a couple of his classic reverse handoffs to Samuel and the Niners marched to the Chiefs' 20 yard line, where they ultimately settled for a field goal. After Kansas City responded with a touchdown, Garoppolo made his first big mistake of the game: an ill-advised floating ball right into the hands of Chiefs defensive back Bashaud Breeland. Kansas City consolidated the pick with 3 more points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, having a young quarterback that just threw an interception in a big game would cause a head coach to dial the offense back a little to let his guy get into a rhythm again. But Garoppolo has a quality that allows Shanahan to pretend as if the interception never happened; he is beyond excellent on drives following an interception:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_16.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 16&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Garoppolo right after throwing a pick is the best quarterback in football. Shanahan was well aware of this and did not hold back on the next drive. Along with a couple of great running plays, post-interception Jimmy G. went 3-for-3 for 42 yards and a touchdown to fullback Kyle Juszczyk. The first throw was a scheme play to Samuel and the next two were off play action to the middle of the field: a textbook Kyle Shanahan drive to tie the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shanahan's first big blunder came at the end of the half. The game was tied at 10 and the Niners stopped Kansas City with about 1:45 left in the half; instead of calling a timeout, Shanahan decided to let the clock run down to start his drive with 59 seconds left. After a few plays, the Niners had the ball at their own 45 yard line with just 14 seconds left, but Shanahan had something in mind. One of his specialties is his ability to exploit mismatches at opportune times and embarrass defenders. In this case, he had the perfect mismatch dialed up to justify his tanking of 40 seconds just a minute ago. Kansas City came out with six defensive backs. Two safeties were about 11 yards off the ball and Shanahan had his three wide receivers (and thus three Chiefs cornerbacks) lined up to Garoppolo's left, leaving tight end George Kittle isolated with backup safety Daniel Sorensen on the right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 17&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 110%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		Source: NBC Sports&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely enough, Kittle got separation and Garoppolo dropped the ball right in his hands for about 40 yards. Unfortunately, Kittle pushed off on the play even though he didn't need to, and the play was nullified due to the penalty. With just six seconds left, the first half, and thus the Niners' drive, came to an abrupt stop. Shanahan later admitted that he tanked the 40 seconds because he did not want to risk Kansas City getting the ball back with enough time to score, in case they stopped him deep in his own territory. He made his decision out of fear of what the Chiefs were capable of and as a result, he put all of his chips in on a play that was neither creative nor clever but rather reactive and forceful. He could have taken the timeout and had plenty of time to engineer a proper drive, but fear made him waste a potential scoring drive and cost San Francisco a halftime lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shanahan came out strong in the second half. The Niners kicked a field goal on the opening drive and after Mahomes threw an interception, got the ball back in good field position. Garoppolo fired another three lasers over the middle of the field, two of which were off play action, for 52 yards and San Francisco found the endzone. This would be the last time they scored all night. Kansas City eventually scored a touchdown with 6:13 left in the game and cut the lead to 3 points, 20-17. The next two San Francisco drives contained a sequence of events that made Shanahan look silly and won Kansas City the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the drive following Kansas City's score, on a 2nd down and 5, Garoppolo fired a ball that was intended for Kittle short in the middle of the field, but Chiefs defensive tackle Chris Jones jumped up and swatted the ball with perfect timing. The drive ended after Kansas City blitzed on 3rd down and Garoppolo launched the ball out of harm's way. Then, with 2:44 left in the game, Kansas City scored a touchdown and took the lead. San Francisco came back onto the field and on 1st and 10 at midfield, Garoppolo fired a ball to Deebo Samuel over the middle that was blocked by Jones &lt;i&gt;again&lt;/i&gt;. What was going on? It's extremely difficult for a defensive lineman to block a throw, let alone do it twice in the span of two drives in a Super Bowl. The answer lies in the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_18.gif&quot; alt=&quot;picture 18&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: NFL Films (Youtube)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both of the plays that Jones swatted the ball, Garoppolo's intended receivers (Kittle and Samuel) were lined up in the slot to his right. Garoppolo's average distance of throw in 2019 to each of these receivers was 6.1 and 7.6 yards respectively. Based on his 2019 targets, Garoppolo's probability of throwing inside on routes within that range is almost twice as high as his probability of throwing outside (29% vs. 15% respectively). But that's not all. Kittle and Samuel are Garoppolo's favorite targets by a mile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 19&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 40% of his completions go to these two receivers, and among his pass catchers who aren't running backs, Kittle and Samuel are in the top 3 in terms of the speed at which Garoppolo gets the ball out of his hands. The moment Kittle and Samuel lined up in the slot on their respective plays, Chris Jones knew two things: this receiver is going to break into the short middle of the field and the ball is coming out &lt;i&gt;fast&lt;/i&gt;. What Shanahan thought were high-percentage plays were actually the most predictable sequences of the game. Jones was simply timing Garoppolo and throwing his hands up to block the passes; Shanahan's plays in crunchtime were undone not by brilliant coverage, but by a defensive lineman that just did his homework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the play immediately after the blocked pass to Samuel, Shanahan tried to mix it up a little with a deeper throw over the middle to Kendrick Bourne. Jones didn't get the block, but at this point the Chiefs secondary had a feel for what was going on. Safety Kendall Fuller simply sat on the route, dove into the passing lane, and nearly got an interception. On 3rd down, Shanahan took a shot to the endzone to Emmanuel Sanders (the exact same play that won San Francisco their week 16 game vs. the Rams) and Garoppolo overthrew the ball. By 4th down, the Niners offense had lost all its energy from the previous three plays and Garoppolo inevitably took a sack. With 1:25 left in the game, the Super Bowl was over. Kansas City put the icing on the cake with a final touchdown and the game ended with a score of 31-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 20&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Sports Illustrated&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's ridiculous to blame Garoppolo for missing on a 49 yard bomb to the endzone on 3rd down in a Super Bowl with under 2 minutes to go. It's equally ridiculous to blame San Francisco's defense when they were getting almost zero rest due to their offense's lack of productivity the entire fourth quarter. The fact of the matter is that in the moments of truth, Shanahan worried so much about getting a single first down at a time that he lost sight of how to break the defense over a sequence of well-arranged plays, and instead went for seemingly high-percentage calls that Kansas City had studied all week. When his team needed to move the football more than ever, he lost his identity and let them down. Heading into the Super Bowl, everybody fully expected Kansas City's defense to commit to stopping the run and force Garoppolo to make some plays, and Garoppolo did what was expected of him. If the Niners had won, he would have been the MVP. He took what was given to him by his coach as he had all year. His coach was simply not giving him the right stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Super Bowl LI and now Super Bowl LIV, Shanahan and Super Bowls have become a dynamic duo in all the wrong ways. He's only 40 years old and he will likely be coaching for decades to come. He's too good not to. He's built a culture in San Francisco that any team would die for. He has his players playing selflessly and his coaches believing in everything he does. The way that NFL executives speak of him would have you believe that he is the second coming of Bill Belichick. Kyle Shanahan will win a Super Bowl someday, but until then, he's officially got a monkey on his back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: Pro Football Focus, ESPN, pro-football-reference.com, playerprofiler.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kathir Ilango</name></author><summary type="html">After finishing the 2016 season with 2 wins, the San Francisco 49ers decided it was time to try something new. They went into full-rebuild mode, giving six-year contracts to new head coach Kyle Shanahan and general manager John Lynch. Prior to their hiring, Shanahan was an accomplished play caller who was only 37 years old, while Lynch was a commentator for Fox Sports who had zero front office experience. It was certainly a gamble, but one that ultimately paid off as Shanahan and Lynch completely rebuilt the team from the ground up (46 of the 53 players on San Francisco’s roster were brought in by the new regime) and within three years, got the Niners to the Super Bowl for a shot at their sixth title.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sustainability of Lamar Jackson’s Production</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sustainability of Lamar Jackson's Production" /><published>2020-02-01T17:44:24-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-01T17:44:24-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: miro.medium.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When tasked with winning football games, every head coach in the NFL talks about establishing an identity, as all the best teams have one. The 49ers are winning off of a multi-dimensional running game and a ferocious defense that gets to the opposing quarterback. The Saints are winning off a dink-and-dunk quick-hitter offense. The Chiefs are winning with speed on the outside and a lethal deep-ball passer. The Patriots have been &quot;doing their job&quot; for the last 2 decades. But out of all the teams in football, there's one team's identity which stands out as the most established, physical, and against-the-grain in all of football&amp;colon; the 14-2 Baltimore Ravens, the best team in the league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all starts with their stifling defense which, once again, is a contender for the league's best. While they have a good defensive line, where they really shine is at defensive-back, where they have the league's deepest and most dangerous group. Headlined by the elite ball-hawking Earl Thomas and suffocating Marlon Humphry, the Ravens also have three other feisty cornerbacks in Brandon Carr, Jimmy Smith and Marcus Peters. On the other side of the ball, the Ravens run the rock up the opposition's throat, with a rock-solid offensive-line anchored by Ronnie Stanley and the ageless Marshal Yanda, premier blocking tight-ends in Mark Andrews and Nick Boyle, and one of the league's angriest runners in Mark Ingram. But these assets aren't what makes the Ravens special; they've been this type of team for a long time.  The addition of one piece has made their offense go from byzantine to innovative, from stagnant to electric. This one piece is arguably the best mobile quarterback in NFL history: Lamar Jackson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2013, the last time the Ravens won the Super Bowl, the NFL was a very different place. For starters, the team they faced in the Super Bowl, the 49ers, had Colin Kaepernick installed as their starting quarterback following an electric run to the big game. Kaepernick was one of the hottest young quarterbacks in the game because of his legs, having gashed the Packers in that very same playoff run for 181 yards and 2 touchdowns on an 11.3 yards per carry clip. This performance set the record for most single-game rushing yards by a quarterback not only in the playoffs, but in any game in NFL history, a record that still stands today. On top of that, the Rookie of the Year that season was none other than current Ravens back-up, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap1000000134287/article/robert-griffin-iii-wins-offensive-rookie-of-the-year&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robert Griffin III&lt;/a&gt; (RG3), who capped off a historic rookie season with 815 yards on the ground, a number that ranks 7th all time for quarterbacks. Another rookie that season was Russell Wilson, a player whose best rushing season ranks one rung above RG3's, at 849 yards. All of this is to say that the last time the Ravens were dominant, rushing quarterbacks were a trend. Since then, mobile quarterbacks like RG3, Kaepernick, Marcus Mariota, Tim Tebow and Johnny Manziel have flamed out, while remaining players with this skillset like Russell Wilson and the younger Deshaun Watson rely more heavily on their passing ability than their legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this trend slowly dying out, Lamar Jackson was a polarizing prospect when he finally hit the NFL draft in 2018. Michael Vick, the consensus greatest mobile quarterback of all-time before Lamar Jackson, endorsed him as a better runner than himself, but due to the decline of this skill's usage, many teams didn't even view Jackson as a quarterback prospect. Hall of Fame General Manager Bill Polian referred to Jackson as &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2760372-bill-polian-says-lamar-jackson-is-short-should-move-to-wr-in-the-nfl?source=post_page---------------------------&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;too slight for the position&lt;/a&gt;, not enough of a thrower, and stated that he should switch to a position such as wide-receiver, which is more reliant on speed. Jackson ended up being selected 32nd overall in the NFL draft, and is currently revitalizing speed for his position. His 1206 rushing yards through 15 games this season is an NFL record, shattering Michael Vick's previous high of 1039, and making him a surefire bet to win the MVP. After seeing this historical production, I wanted to measure Jackson's improvement since his rookie season, see how he stacks up to past quarterbacks in this department, and decide how sustainable his current level of production is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, through 7 starts in his rookie season, Lamar Jackson had 556 yards on the ground, an average of 79.4 yards and 17 attempts per game. Despite the excellent production, 17 rushing attempts is an unsustainable number for a quarterback. To make this number tangible, look no further than this year's leading rusher Derrick Henry. Henry is &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.redd.it/fq9o7krtz9d11.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;built like a truck&lt;/a&gt; and led the league in rushing this season. Despite all this, Henry averaged a hair under 19 carries a game (18.93), less than 2 carries per game more than Jackson in his 2018 season. The Ravens knew this had to change too, and hired Kaepernick's former offensive coordinator, Greg Roman, to run the offense. This season, Jackson averaged an even better 80.4 yards per game over a 15 game sample, but averaged under 12 attempts (11.7) per game on the ground, a much more sustainable number. To put Jackson's production in context, Ezekiel Elliott, who had the 4th most rushing yards in the league this season, rushed for 1357 yards in 16 games, which averages out to 84.8 yards per game. He did this in 125 more attempts than Jackson. Obviously, Jackson has the element of surprise on his side, and defenses crowd the box on Zeke, but still, a quarterback rushing for close to the same yardage per game as the highest paid running-back in the league is just absurd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph displayed below shows Lamar Jackson's per-game stats as a rookie compared to other notable running-backs' in 2018. This dot-plot includes every single 2018 pro-bowler at the position, as well as a few other notable players, such as Mark Ingram, Leonard Fournette and Jordan Howard. Despite the smaller sample size, the fact that he ranked 3rd in carries and 4th in yardage per game from the quarterback position over his last 7 games is eye opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jackson's development as a passer has been the key difference that has allowed him to drastically improve his production on a per-carry basis, as it doesn't allow defenses to blitz and key off on his running ability. At the end of last season, many were calling Lamar Jackson more of a running back than a quarterback. NFL.com's QB Index wrote that while Jackson arguably added more value as a runner in half a season than any quarterback in NFL history, his errant throws and league-leading 12 fumbles (in 7 games) kept his value in check, ranking Lamar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001007337/article/qb-index-patrick-mahomes-leads-yearend-rankings&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;23rd in the league&lt;/a&gt; out of 32 starting quarterbacks. At the end of this season, he was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001091708/article/qb-index-week-17-patrick-mahomes-vaults-russell-wilson&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;consensus number 1&lt;/a&gt; and an MVP shoo-in. What parts of his passing game improved? According to Pro Football Reference (PFR), his ANY/A (Adjusted Net Yards per pass Attempt) has gone up from 5.99 to 8.19, his completion percentage has gone up from a terrible 58.2% to a much better 66.1%, and his sack percentage has gone down from 8.6% to 5.4%. To rationalize this data, when analyzing PFR's passing index, where a score of 100 is league average and anything higher is better, Jackson has gone from below average values hovering in the 90s range to above average values in the early 100s in every notable passing stat, among them ANY/A, Touchdown Percentage (TD%), Interception Percentage (INT%) and Completion Percentage (CMP%). His touchdown percentage, in particular, was tops in the league, as he had a league-leading 36 passing touchdowns on the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stats show his increased mastery of the passing game, which increases the opportunity to make misdirection plays and establish a dominant running-game for the Ravens. The opposing defense must respect the pass and can no longer crowd up the line-of-scrimmage to stuff the run. The ANY/A in particular is telling, as this statistic has a strong correlation with offensive production. It is essentially a formula which takes passing yards, adds the number of touchdowns times a multiplier, subtracts the yardage lost due to sacks and the number of interceptions times a multiplier, then divides the total by the sum of the passing attempts and number of sacks taken. While this sounds like complicated jargon, it's essentially just calculating the average yards per play with touchdowns and interceptions thrown factored in. Thus, the ANY/A is an effective way to see how well a quarterback is able to lead his offense to points. This and the rest of Jackson's passing statistics help explain why his yards-per-attempt while rushing the football was substantially higher this season, sitting at 6.9 yards-per-attempt this year compared to last season's 4.7 average. It also helps explain how the Ravens as a team set the NFL's all time record for rushing yards in a season, with their 3296 yards on the ground breaking a mark that stood for 41 years prior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Lamar Jackson's improvement as a passer has fueled his and his team's improved statistical performance, I wanted to see just how sustainable this improvement truly is. Visually, Jackson's uniqueness is obvious. Lamar is just built different. He has unreal speed, better shiftiness than most running-backs, and touch on his passes. But, we've seen players like Kaepernick and RG3 take the league by storm in the past, just to regress to league average or worse in their next season. In order to gain statistical insight on what level of regression to expect, I recorded the statistics of a group of mobile quarterbacks in their first full season as a starter, and compared this to their statistics in their next full season accrued as a starter, attempting to see whether defenses figured them out. Players like Lamar Jackson and Colin Kaepernick had seasons where they started 7 games before their first full season, so I set the threshold of a full season as a starter to be a Week 1 starter who played at least 14 games. In order for me to consider the quarterback mobile, I wanted them to average at least 3 carries per game in their first season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to conduct this experiment, I gathered the statistics in major passing and rushing metrics for 10 mobile quarterbacks in the 2000s. This group consisted of Colin Kaepernick, Robert Griffin III, Marcus Mariota, Mitchell Trubisky, Russell Wilson, Cam Newton, Michael Vick, Daunte Culpepper, Dak Prescott and Deshaun Watson. While many of these players obviously play differently from Lamar, I believe most of these players are more than capable of running the football. Mitchell Trubisky and Marcus Mariota have shown commendable speed rushing the football, while Vick, Culpepper, Griffin and Kaepernick have had huge games on the ground. Newton, Wilson, Watson and Prescott have all had spurts of MVP play and have shown the ability to run and pass effectively throughout their careers. When collecting data, I once again started off by focusing on the Pro-Football-Reference metrics for ANY/A, Completion Percentage, Touchdown Percentage and Interception Percentage, four of the most important statistics for a quarterback. I found the Pro-Football-Reference metric valuable because it measured a quarterback's statistics in these categories relative to their peers in that given year, providing a standardized metric that adjusts for the changes in the passing game from Vick and Culpepper's eras to the present. Regardless, I found that all the players in the sample, on average, had above average statistics in their first full season as a starter. In their next full season, after an entire offseason of defenses keying in on their tendencies, this population of quarterbacks, on average, was slightly below league-average. Considering that the list contains a handful of MVP level talents, the observation that these quarterbacks went from close to the top 10 players at their positions to barely average is shocking. Obviously, there were some exceptions, but almost all the quarterbacks showed a slight regression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, wanting to also look at raw statistical change, I compared the raw values of each of these quarterback's rushing attempts, yards, ANY/A, TD% and INT% to see the noticeable per-player changes in each statistic. To do this, I found each of these quarterback's statistics in their first full year, and either found a proportional change (ANY/A), percentage change (TD%, INT%), or the raw change (rushing yards and attempts per game) in their statistics the next-season. This thus calculates the average individual performance decrease, regardless of a player's talent, as the player is now only being compared with himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings proved to be insightful. Firstly, most quarterbacks kept rushing the football the same amount, with around the same number of production. Exceptions included Trubisky and RG3, who both saw their number of rushing attempts decrease by over 1 attempt per game, as well as Culpepper, who saw an uptick in usage and production. The rushing attempts and yards per game of the average player remained almost the same, decreasing by a miniscule 0.16 attempts and 0.95 yards per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the Adjusted Net Yards per Attempt (ANY/A), the ANY/A value in the following year was 0.84 times the value in the first year. Thus, the regression was 0.16 multiplied by the ANY/A in the first year, with the proportional decrease displayed. Essentially, all that means is that these players were 16% less efficient in using their arm to gain yards and lead their offense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the touchdown percentage dipped by 1.1%, meaning 1.1% less of these quarterbacks' throws resulted in touchdowns. Culpepper had the most jarring drop in touchdown percentage, with 3.2% less of his passes ending in paydirt. Only two players had their touchdown percentages go up: Deshaun Watson and Michael Vick. On the flipside, the interception percentage went up, with these quarterbacks throwing picks, on average, on 0.58% more of their throws. Watson and Dak Prescott had the most sizeable increase in picks thrown, with 1.8% more of their passes winding up in the opposition's hands. That adds up to almost an extra 1 out of 50 passes ending up in a turnover. The average quarterback throws over 30 passes per game, so this number is significant over an entire season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does all this mean in-terms of Lamar? If we go by the raw average changes calculated, Lamar's ANY/A will go down to 6.88, his league-leading touchdown rate will go down to 7.9%, and his interception rate will go up to close to 2.1%. The data also indicates that his rushing attempts and yardage per game would remain somewhat similar. But, as we all know, all players are different, and even with these statistics factoring in an expected regression, Lamar Jackson would still be a player capable of wrecking games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Lamar Jackson is still going to be a game-changer, and the Raven's defense is still going to be suffocating. Regardless, I would expect defenses to catch on to Jackson to a certain extent, and I expect his statistics next season to hover closer to the numbers listed above than to those he recorded in his 2019 MVP campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking for a team to compare this Ravens group to, it's hard not to go back to the last time the Ravens hoisted the Lombardi Trophy and see parallels to the team they beat that fateful day. Both the 2019 Ravens and the 2013 49ers had a dynamic quarterback who took the league by storm, a stifling defense stacked with difference-makers, and most importantly, a Harbaugh at head coach.  Regardless of the similarities between Lamar's and Kaepernick's supporting casts, one of these players is the presumptive league MVP, and one of them has never made a Pro-Bowl. Despite this season's disappointing end, I expect Lamar Jackson and the Ravens to keep on flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: pro-football-reference.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vishal Sundaram</name></author><summary type="html">When tasked with winning football games, every head coach in the NFL talks about establishing an identity, as all the best teams have one. The 49ers are winning off of a multi-dimensional running game and a ferocious defense that gets to the opposing quarterback. The Saints are winning off a dink-and-dunk quick-hitter offense. The Chiefs are winning with speed on the outside and a lethal deep-ball passer. The Patriots have been &quot;doing their job&quot; for the last 2 decades. But out of all the teams in football, there's one team's identity which stands out as the most established, physical, and against-the-grain in all of football&amp;colon; the 14-2 Baltimore Ravens, the best team in the league.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Brief History of MLB Postseason Format Changes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Brief History of MLB Postseason Format Changes" /><published>2020-01-25T13:53:48-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-25T13:53:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: cnycentral.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many baseball fans, the MLB postseason&amp;mdash;the World Series in particular&amp;mdash;is the ultimate test of skill and teamwork. Over the course of a month, the best teams battle it out to become the World Series champion. Dating back to the first MLB postseason in 1884, the title of World Series champion has been the highest achievement that a professional baseball team can attain. Thus, the importance of the postseason to MLB teams and baseball enthusiasts alike cannot be understated. This, however, has not kept the MLB from changing the postseason format every 10 to 20 years. As expected, these changes are met with criticism and controversy, roster and strategy changes, and&amp;mdash;in rare cases&amp;mdash;MLB dynasties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the MLB postseason was first introduced to the professional league in 1884, it was very simple. After a few years of simple exhibition matches, the MLB decided on a postseason format that consisted of only one series&amp;mdash;later to be called the World Series. In this format, the top-seeded teams from the American League and the National League would face off in a single best-of-seven series (in 1903, 1919, 1920, and 1921 a best-of-nine was played). This oversimplified version was used for nearly a hundred years before it was modified. In 1969, when each of the MLB leagues were split into two regions, the postseason was extended to become a two round best-of-seven series. In this format, the top teams of each league would compete against one another in the ALCS and the NLCS before advancing to the World Series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: britannica.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a new region was again added to each MLB league in 1995, a third round, this time a best-of-five was added to the postseason. To accomodate for the odd numbers, a wild card team was added to each league; the wild card team would play the divisional champion in the best-of-five Division Series. Finally, in 2012 a second wild card was added to each league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you have probably concluded, the MLB's postseason format quickly became one of the most variable in all of American sports history. The ramifications of these changes were felt far and wide among the baseball community. One of the most direct impacts of these changes was on match variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before 1969, when the MLB postseason was comprised of a single series, match variation was nonexistent. At the end of each season, the top-seeded of the American League or the National League was guaranteed to win the World Series. However, as the MLB postseason was extended to accommodate for internal league changes, more and more teams gained access to the once elite MLB postseason. Resultantly, the World Series became unpredictable. As of 2019, ten teams participate in the MLB postseason, each fighting for the title of World Series champion. No teams are guaranteed a spot in the World Series, or even the ALCS and NLCS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any advantage that top-seeded teams once had in the MLB postseason is slowly diminishing. Let's take a look at how the probability of a top team winning the World Series has changed since 1969.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, these results are fairly straightforward. As the leagues split into more distinct regions and wild card teams were added to the MLB postseason, the top-seeded teams struggled to stay consistent. If more spots are made available in the MLB postseason in the future, this trend will likely continue; the title of top seed will lose the little competitive edge that it now provides. Even if the current format remains unchanged for years to come, the spike seen in the 2012-2019 seasons will likely drop off as more data is made available. But what does this trend mean for MLB fans and teams today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For casual fans, this trend is nothing but beneficial. The expansion of the MLB postseason has provided baseball fans with content that was previously unavailable. Furthermore, the changes made to the MLB postseason have made the games more enticing&amp;mdash;no games are unwinnable and no spots are secure.  The MLB postseason can take any number of turns before a World Series champion is crowned, as the Washington Nationals showed us this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: washington.org&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For MLB teams, things are a bit more complicated. In recent years, the postseason format has come to influence team play styles and strategies. Due to the expansion of the MLB postseason, many teams have attempted to adopt a more conservative, consistent play style. In today's three round best-of-seven series format, consistency is more important than ever. To win the World Series, a team must be able to play at the highest level at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the format changes have resulted in an extended MLB postseason, they have not always resulted in the most competitive games. When wild card teams and the Division Series were first introduced to the postseason in 1995, competition levels took a turn for the worst. Under this new format, the wildcard teams&amp;mdash;often considered the underdog teams of each league&amp;mdash;would immediately face off against the top-seeded divisional champion of their respective league. In recent years, these matchups have given top teams an easy route to the ALCS or NLCS. Consequently, many top-seeded teams arrive to the ALCS or NLCS unprepared for the competition and pressure that the series will surely bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the differences may be subtle, they cannot be ignored. For the ALCS and the World Series, there is little to be said. The average number of games played per series has remained relatively constant, despite postseason format changes. The NLCS, however, brings up questions for concern. From 1985 to 1993, the average number of games played per NLCS was 6.3. In today's postseason format, this number is almost a whole game lower at 5.5. In a simple best-of-seven series, this change is quite drastic. Although we cannot be sure what brought about this change, it is likely that MLB postseason format changes&amp;mdash;specifically the addition of wild card teams&amp;mdash;had a direct impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how could something as impartial as format changes possibly have such an impact?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation is the prevalence of baseball dynasties or 'dream teams' in recent years. As the postseason format has changed over the years, so has the importance of consistent play. When the postseason was first introduced to the MLB, inconsistent teams won the World Series quite frequently. However, in today's three round best-of-seven series, consistency is more or less a requirement. Thus, as consistent play gradually became more and more important, select teams were able to find their niche among a particular postseason format. The result was an absolute domination of MLB league and postseason play. Let's see if any baseball dynasties formed from 1995 to 2011 in which the three series best-of-seven (with one wild card team for each league) format was used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the New York Yankees were able to find great success in the MLB postseason throughout these years. Whether or not this success was due the postseason format cannot be known for sure. However, the history of the New York Yankees and their performance in previous MLB postseasons support the claim that the postseason format played a major role in their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 1985 to 1993, when the postseason was a two round best-of-seven series, the New York Yankees were unable to win a single World Series. When this format was changed, however, the Yankees looked like an entirely new team. In the early years of this new format, the Yankees were unstoppable; they were crowned World Series champion three years in a row, beginning in 1998. Without the postseason format change of 1995, it is unlikely that the Yankees would have been so dominant in these years. When the postseason format was changed in 2012, their success came to an end. Since these changes, the New York Yankees have not won, or participated in, the World Series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many professional baseball teams and fans dream of a time when the MLB stops altering the postseason format, it is unlikely that this dream will come true any time soon. While previous format changes have resulted in lower levels of postseason competition and occasional dynasties, the MLB has only benefited from the changes. By extending the postseason format and introducing wild card teams, the MLB is raking in more cash than ever. The MLB has no reason to halt the postseason changes that they have profited so greatly from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2001, the MLB has seen annual increases in revenue. In more recent years, this trend has only become more apparent. Every year, the MLB seems to outperform themselves, pushing their annual revenue to unprecedented levels. With this in mind, I would not be surprised to see the MLB postseason expanded even further in upcoming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: baseball-reference.com, statista.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Fischer Sherrod</name></author><summary type="html">For many baseball fans, the MLB postseason&amp;mdash;the World Series in particular&amp;mdash;is the ultimate test of skill and teamwork. Over the course of a month, the best teams battle it out to become the World Series champion. Dating back to the first MLB postseason in 1884, the title of World Series champion has been the highest achievement that a professional baseball team can attain. Thus, the importance of the postseason to MLB teams and baseball enthusiasts alike cannot be understated. This, however, has not kept the MLB from changing the postseason format every 10 to 20 years. As expected, these changes are met with criticism and controversy, roster and strategy changes, and&amp;mdash;in rare cases&amp;mdash;MLB dynasties.</summary></entry></feed>