<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-04T19:50:11-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Coin Toss</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CoinToss" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Coin Toss" /><published>2020-03-30T00:41:53-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-30T00:41:53-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CoinToss</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CoinToss">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;width:47.83%; float: left;&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: neilleifer.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;width:52.17%; float:right&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: thebiglead.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Introduction&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A coin toss is just a flip of the coin, but in recent years-especially during the NFL playoffs-it has seemingly gained heightened importance. A prime example of this is the coin toss of the Super Bowl: in the early years, only the select few captains and a single referee met at midfield in a very quick exchange. Today, however, things are drastically different, as a small village of camera crews and important individuals accompany the captains to film the result of the coin toss. Moreover, mantras about which option to choose (&quot;tails never fails&quot;) have emerged, the coin is specially engraved for the occasion, and Las Vegas sportsbooks create a prop bet on whether the result of the coin toss will be &lt;i&gt;heads&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;tails&lt;/i&gt;, indicating the grandiosity of what should be an insignificant event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These decisions, in turn, have led to an increase in the talk about &quot;coin toss strategy,&quot; if such a thing even exists. We wanted to see if there is any validity to this talk, or if people were just blowing smoke. The coin toss doesn't seem like the type of event to make or break a game, so we were wondering why people pay so much attention to its outcome and their team's decision. For the purpose of this article, we have limited the games we will be investigating to the playoff games between the 2002 and 2019 NFL seasons to impose &lt;i&gt;somewhat&lt;/i&gt; of an equal playing field (i.e. there are no 0-15 teams facing a 13-2 team).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason we chose to compare the 2002-2006 era to 2015-2019 was because coin toss data was not easy to find before this era.  In addition, deferring seems to have become the prevalent choice in recent years, but was this the case 18 years ago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;NFL Playoff Coin Tosses:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown by the graph above, when comparing the results of the coin toss decision (defer vs. receive) between two different eras (2002-2006 and 2015-2019) for the NFL Playoffs, the percent of decisions resulting in a deferral drastically increased, from around 5% to around 85%. In fact, when performing a test for difference of proportions with a null hypothesis of no difference and an alternative that there is &lt;i&gt;a&lt;/i&gt; difference (either positive or negative), we obtained a p-value of , indicating that we would reject the null hypothesis. It appears that the percentage of coin tosses that resulted in a deferral decision has statistically significantly increased from the era of 2002 - 2006 to 2015 - 2019, as we expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to 2002 playoff games, we calculated the overall deferral percentage in the playoffs for that year and compared it to the win rate of the teams that deferred to understand if there was a correlation between deferring the coin toss and winning the game. On the x-axis we plotted the year up to the 2019 season and on the y-axis the win rate as a proportion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of deferral percentage, the data plotted clearly suggest an upward trend in recent years. In fact, to our surprise whereas up until 2006 no team deferred more than three times, in recent years no team has received more than three times. Perhaps misleadingly, the win percentage for those years is either at 1.0 or 0.0 as there was not a large sample size of defers to choose from, thus polarizing the figures. Interestingly, as the deferral percentage among teams rises, the win percentage caps at roughly 0.5. In the early years of the deferral revolution (2010-2012), winning percentages see a significant increase -- perhaps suggesting that deferring contributed to a team's overall success in the game. However, as the trend takes off from 2015 onward, nearly every team defers if they win the toss. Consequently, the win percentage tumbles, before leveling off around 0.5. This is because teams today no longer have an advantage when every single team is doing the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To confirm this belief we took to plotting the opposite trend: going back to 2002 playoff games, we calculated the overall receive percentage in the playoffs for that year and compared it to the win rate of the teams that recieved. While the receive percentage is simply the inverse of the deferral percentage plot (blue), the receive win percentage draws on a whole new sample size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming the previous hypothesis is correct, it is expected that from 2002-2006 while the receive percentage is at a league high, the win percentage should be stagnant around 0.5. However, from 2010-2012, the percentage should be lower, as teams transition into a new meta of deferring before finally jumping between the two extremes of 0.0 and 1.0 with a small sample size of teams receiving from 2015 onward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting the hypothesis, the 2002-2006 sector corroborates the idea that when all teams are doing the same thing, in this case receiving, the win percentage is roughly even. The year 2010 illuminates seemingly a major turning point for the league. Recall that in 2010 60% of teams deferred and of those teams they won 40% of their games. However, of the teams that received (the remaining 40%), they won 0% of the games for the only time in the 18 year window. Additionally, skipping to 2015 when all the teams begin to defer, this leaves a small group going against the grain by receiving. Just as in the defer group from 2002-2006, this group of those who receive from 2015 onward have an average 0.8 win rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this point we've proven that from the years 2002-2006, NFL teams were likely to receive should they win the toss. Moreover, from 2015 onward, the reverse is true: NFL teams are more likely to defer than to receive. We decided to plot the deferral rate as a proportion on the timeline by round. We expected that as the games got &quot;bigger,&quot; the teams would become more likely to either receive or defer -- dependent on what was in style at the time. In other words, from 2015 onward, it's assumed that the deferral rate should increase from the wild card to the super bowl -- not only because the games are more important but also due to the sample size. On the x-axis we plotted the year and on the y-axis the deferral proportion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, in those two major time periods, the trend is true: for all ten of those years in the conference championship and super bowl, teams picked the popular trend at the time (meaning 30/30 times the team picked the popular choice). Additionally, for the last decade the team that has won the toss at the super bowl has chosen to defer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, we wanted to see &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; teams switched from receiving the football to deferring to the second half upon winning the coin toss. Was it because that strategy was &quot;better&quot;? Bill Belichick is renowned for deferring to the second half, as it provides his team with the opportunity to &quot;double up&quot; just before and just after half time: if his team can score at the end of the first half, then, by receiving the ball to start the second half, they have the chance to score again; this provides the team with the chance at a big momentum swing of up to two possessions (i.e. sixteen points). By considering this strategy, it would appear that deferring is the better decision and that the teams which defer would be expected to have a higher win percentage than the teams which receive after winning the coin toss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above bar graph displays the win percentages for teams that won the coin toss separated by their decisions to (1) defer and (2) receive for all years in the data set (2002 - 2019). As depicted, there was no significant difference in win percentage between teams that deferred versus teams that received &lt;i&gt;on the whole&lt;/i&gt;, indicating that the sole decision of deferring versus receiving does not help a team in the playoffs. However, as some of the graphics displayed earlier in the article convey, this percentage could vary depending on the year and whether deferring was considered &quot;popular&quot;. When further looking at the data, it is interesting to note that the win percentages hover around 0.45 for teams that won the coin toss regardless of decision, leading us to wonder whether teams that won the coin toss in the playoffs had a statistically lower win percentage than teams that lost the coin toss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/coinToss/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When comparing the win percentages for teams that won the coin toss against teams that lost it, we performed a hypothesis test for difference of proportions to see whether the observed difference was statistically significant. Since the p-value for this two-sided test was 0.0562, at the significance level, we fail to reject the null hypothesis that the percentages are different. What this means is that the likelihood of observing this difference of win percentage in a sample given that there really is no difference in the population is 5.62%; since our cutoff for that assumption being wrong is 5%, we say that we cannot reject the statement that the win percentage is different for these two categories. However, this p-value is still pretty low (almost significant), so we may want to investigate this issue further. While winning or losing the coin toss will not &lt;i&gt;directly&lt;/i&gt; determine whether or not a team wins the game, there could be confounding variables inherent to the data and to playoff games that could impact the relationship between the coin toss outcome and win percentage. One such example would be overthinking, as the team which won the coin toss would overcomplicate the decision and ultimately make a poor one. Another potential confounding variable would be the peril of herd mentality: as more and more teams are opting to defer, they may be opting to defer for the sole reason that other teams are making the same choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams have increasingly analyzed the coin toss and its effect on the game, in turn flipping the script from almost every team receiving the ball to almost every team choosing to get the ball in the second half. This change has become so prevalent that many football fans are outraged when their team &lt;i&gt;doesn't&lt;/i&gt; defer after winning the coin toss. However, blindly choosing to defer has its own pitfalls: teams are not thinking about their decision at all but merely going with the flow, which could have negative consequences if they are not prepared. Just like football, making a decision from the coin toss is dynamic and adaptive: each opponent is different, each team is different, and each game is different. Making the decision just because everyone else does it has perils of its own, and when looking at the data, the teams that generally saw an increase in their success were the ones that began this deferral trend and deferred when all anyone considered was receiving the ball and having the first possession. Maybe with an increasing number of teams choosing to defer, the right decision is to go against the grain and choose to receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then again, it's all just the flip of a coin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: ESPN, Pro Football Reference&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ethan Allavarpu</name></author><summary type="html">A coin toss is just a flip of the coin, but in recent years-especially during the NFL playoffs-it has seemingly gained heightened importance. A prime example of this is the coin toss of the Super Bowl&amp;colon; in the early years, only the select few captains and a single referee met at midfield in a very quick exchange. Today, however, things are drastically different, as a small village of camera crews and important individuals accompany the captains to film the result of the coin toss. Moreover, mantras about which option to choose (&quot;tails never fails&quot;) have emerged, the coin is specially engraved for the occasion, and Las Vegas sportsbooks create a prop bet on whether the result of the coin toss will be heads or tails, indicating the grandiosity of what should be an insignificant event.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Team With the Best Clutch Gene</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ClutchGene" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Team With the Best Clutch Gene" /><published>2020-03-30T00:11:10-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-30T00:11:10-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ClutchGene</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ClutchGene">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: wallpapersafari.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2013 NBA Finals, Ray Allen hit arguably one of the most significant shots of the decade. With the rival San Antonio Spurs just seconds away from another NBA championship, Allen converted an offensive rebound into a 3 point shot to tie the game, send it to overtime and eventually secure a vital win. The Heat ended up winning the series and the championship and as a result, Ray Allen's three became one of the most memorable shots in recent history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only did that shot change the outcome of the series, but it also fundamentally altered the narrative surrounding Lebron James &quot;taking his talents to South beach&quot;, creating the Big three, and marking the beginning of the superteam era. Without that shot, that &quot;superteam&quot; , having already fallen short once to an underdog Dallas Mavericks team, would once and for all have been labelled an underwhelming, failed endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NBA games consist of 2 and 3 point shots, but the context and time at which these shots are taken play a crucial role in determining the idea of clutch. According to the NBA, &quot;clutch time&quot; is defined as the last 5 minutes of a game in which the point differential is 5 or less. While discussions on the topic of clutch are usually centered around individual players, we shift our focus to teams and their ability to close out games in crunch time. We will spend more time discussing the teams' overall statistics during clutch time rather than specific plays made by individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Absolute vs Relative Clutch Win Percentage&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1 - Absolute Clutch Win Percentage&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2 - Relative Clutch Win Percentage&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 shows the value of a team's win percentage in clutch games subtracted by its overall win percentage. This is essentially the change in a team's win probability as they enter clutch time. A positive value would indicate that the team usually performs better in clutch situations than in regular games while a negative value would suggest that the team typically performs worse in clutch games. This method allows us to figure out which teams truly excel in clutch time by adjusting for their typical win percentage. For example, if we only look at the Charlotte Hornets's win percentage in the clutch, they come in at the middle of the pack at 51.9%. However, if we compare this to their season win percentage at 33.3%, we can observe that the Hornets have high relative success in clutch games and are deserving of being considered as more than just your average team in the clutch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads us to the question of whether a team's absolute or relative clutch win percentage reveals more about the clutchness of a team. To start off, we will define a team's clutchness to be its ability to adapt and perform better in the final moments of a close game. By this definition, a very clutch team should be a team that is able to take advantage of the close game they are in and play more efficiently than in other situations. We believe that the relative clutch win percentage (RCWP) would be able to model this quality of a team better than the absolute clutch win percentage (ACWP) because the RCWP accounts for the fact that not all teams are equally skilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Toronto Raptors are currently 4th in the league with a season win percentage of 72.7%. They also happen to be 4th when ranked by ACWP at 64.3%, so does this mean that they are the 4th clutchest team in the league? Well, if we look at how they usually perform versus their clutch performances, we can see that their win percentage dips by 8.4% in the latter, which may suggest that they might not be as good in the clutch as we thought. It is clear that the Raptors are 4th in ACWP rankings primarily because they are a very skilled team and are usually able to win games. However, since their performance in clutch situations suffers a considerable amount relative to all other games, they should not be considered a top clutch team. By using the RCWP to rank our teams, we are able to assess how well a team is able to improve its chances of winning in clutch games by isolating its clutch factor from its regular performance. The point here is that the team that wins the highest percentage of clutch games is not necessarily the team with the best clutch gene. As long as teams perform better in clutch time than in other situations, they are candidates of being considered as one of the top clutch teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Adjusted Offensive Rating&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3 - Adjusted Offensive Rating&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offensive rating is how many points the team scores per 100 possessions. The adjusted offensive rating (AOR) is the value obtained when the clutch offensive rating is subtracted by the overall offensive rating. This value is basically how many more points a team scores in the clutch per 100 possessions than in other situations. The Charlotte Hornets lead this chart with a 15.2 point rating increase, and the Dallas Mavericks suffer the most with a 21 point rating decrease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Adjusted Defensive Rating&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4 - Adjusted Defensive Rating&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defensive rating is how many points their opponent scores per 100 possessions. The adjusted defensive rating (ADR) is the value calculated when the overall defensive rating is subtracted by the clutch defensive rating. This value is essentially the decrease in their opponent's points per 100 possessions, so the higher the value of this decrease, the better. The Atlanta Hawks lead this metric with a 17.4 point decrease and the Chicago Bulls' defense suffers the most in clutch with a 14.8 point increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Adjusted Net Rating&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 5 - Adjusted Net Rating&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The net rating is calculated by subtracting the defensive rating from the offensive rating, with a higher offensive rating and a lower defensive rating being desirable. Applying the same principle as the adjusted win percentage, we believe that the best metric to determine the team with the best clutch gene is the team with the highest adjusted net rating (ANR) during clutch moments. The offensive rating and defensive rating are essentially measures of a team's efficiency. By using this metric instead of the adjusted win percentage, we are not discounting any losing teams who may have had a great performance in the clutch. Since we previously defined clutch to be a team's ability to perform well in clutch moments, a measure of their improvement in efficiency dictated by the points scored by both teams, whether they won or lost, would best fit our definition to determine the team with the best clutch gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Relative Clutch Win Percentage Based on Number of All-Star Appearance&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(excluded players with less than 10 games)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/clutchGene/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While looking at contributing factors for clutchness, we wanted to see whether the amount of talent or star power plays a role in a team's ability to close out in the clutch. We tested this by plotting the total number of All Star appearances for each team against their win percentage in &quot;clutch time&quot;. From the graph, most of the teams with a high clutch win percentage are heavily on the left, with fewer All Star appearances. This shows that teams' wins in the clutch aren't impacted by an individual star's performance; it is independent of how much talent an individual player may have. A possible explanation could be that overall team performance in clutch time overshadows individuals' performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the relative clutch win percentage, we can see that the Charlotte Hornets' win percentage in the clutch increases by 18.6% when compared to their overall win percentage, the highest improvement in the league. This was followed closely by their change in field goal percentage. With an increase of 6% in the clutch, this was also the best improvement among all NBA teams, with the average change in field goal percentage being a 3.81% decrease in the clutch. However, since we want to look at each team's performance during clutch time rather than if they just won or lost, we should look at their adjusted offensive and defensive ratings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Charlotte Hornets still lead the league with an adjusted offensive rating of 15.2 with the Oklahoma City Thunder following closely behind at 13.9. These two teams' AORs are more than double the value of any other team, making them top contenders to be the top clutch team. If we move to the teams' adjusted defensive rating, we can observe that the Atlanta Hawks are at the top with a score of 17.4, but since their AOR is a -13.4, they are not a top candidate. The Milwaukee Bucks are at second in ADR rankings at 16, and the Thunder and the Philadelphia Sixers are tied in 3rd place at 13.3. The Hornets' ADR rank at 11th at 6.4, which severely hurts their contention of being the best clutch team. Finally, if we look at the adjusted net rating, the Thunder come out on top with a score of 27.3 and the Hornets place second with a score of 21.6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these observations, we have come to the conclusion that the Oklahoma City Thunder are deserving of being named the team with the best clutch gene. Even though the Hornets perform very well offensively and are able to improve their win percentage greatly in clutch moments, their defensive performance hinders their stock of being the top clutch team. The Thunder have the greatest overall improvement in efficiency during clutch time as they have the best offensive efficiency and the third best defensive efficiency. In contrast, the Dallas Mavericks is the team with the worst clutch gene based off adjusted net rating, which is also reflected in their last place standing in adjusted win percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An assumption we made to arrive at our result was that during clutch moments, all teams face the same advantages and disadvantages against all opponents. However, this is unrealistic as this would change with each match. For example, a team with bad perimeter defense would be at a bigger disadvantage if the opponent specializes in 3-point shooting. Had they not faced a team that specializes in 3-point shooting during the clutch, their defensive rating might have been better. Given this assumption, we found that the Oklahoma City Thunder have the best ability to adapt and perform better in the final moments of a close game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: stats.nba.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Wilson Yu</name></author><summary type="html">In the 2013 NBA Finals, Ray Allen hit arguably one of the most significant shots of the decade. With the rival San Antonio Spurs just seconds away from another NBA championship, Allen converted an offensive rebound into a 3 point shot to tie the game, send it to overtime and eventually secure a vital win. The Heat ended up winning the series and the championship and as a result, Ray Allen's three became one of the most memorable shots in recent history.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Legacy of Michael Phelps</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/MichaelPhelps" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Legacy of Michael Phelps" /><published>2020-03-29T23:34:39-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-29T23:34:39-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/MichaelPhelps</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/MichaelPhelps">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: mensjournal.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 28 Olympic gold medals, 27 World Championship gold medals, and 16 Pan Pacific Championship gold medals, Michael Phelps is the most decorated swimmer of all time. But Phelps' medals are just the beginning of his legacy. He has attended 5 Olympic Games, been named World Swimmer of the Year 7 times, and has set 39 world records--4 of which still stand today. His list of achievements goes on and on. In fact, many have acclaimed Phelps as 'the greatest swimmer of all time'. With his retirement in 2016, however, his achievements have flatlined. Now more than ever, the door is open for a new star to top his records and steal his title. The question is: Who could possibly rival Michael Phelps and the legacy that he has created?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this question, let's first take a more in-depth look at Michael Phelps' life to see how he was able to accomplish such impressive feats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Career&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Phelps began swimming competitively when he was in high school. It was during these years that he met his lifelong coach, Bob Bowman. Bowman quickly recognized Phelps' talent and soon began training him. By 1999, Phelps qualified for the U.S. National B Team. Just a year later, Phelps' time in the 200m Fly earned him a spot in the 2000 Summer Olympics. At the age of 15, Phelps was the youngest male swimmer to race in the Olympic Games in 68 years. Shown below is a table that documents Michale Phelps' placement races throughout his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in the year 2000, Phelps raced in every Olympic Games, World Championship, and Pan Pacific Championship until 2012. At the World Championship in 2001, Phelps brought home his first international gold medal. From this point on, Phelps went on a hot streak, taking home medal after medal--more often than not, gold medals. Michael Phelps' peak was likely the Olympic Games of 2008. This year, Phelps quite literally swept the field; he brought home a gold medal in every race that he participated in. Phelps' dominance continued until his retirement in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Physique&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While much of Phelps' success can be attributed to his work ethic, biology has nonetheless played a role. Michael Phelps' body is rather disproportionate; take his wing span for example. The average person's wingspan is about the same as his/her height. Phelps' wingspan, however, at an enormous 6' 7&quot;, is three inches longer than his height. His abnormally large wingspan allows him to generate more power with each stroke. While wingspan data doesn't exist for all professional swimmers, especially for those who raced in the twentieth century, we can take a look at how Phelps' wingspan stacks up against a few top-level competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among professional swimmers, an abnormally long wingspan is ironically all too common. While Phelps' wingspan is average, his ape span--the difference between one's height and wingspan--is among the highest in the group. With a large ape span, Phelps is reaping the benefits of a large wing span without the increase in weight that it typically comes with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: forbes.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to his wingspan, Michael Phelps has disproportionately small legs and a long torso. According to sports biographer Colleen de Bellefonds, &quot;Phelps has the torso of a man who's 6 feet 8 inches tall... and the legs of a man 8 inches shorter&quot; (bibliography.com). This means that his legs produce less drag than other swimmers of similar stature. The abnormalities continue with Phelps' hyperextended, size 14 feet. His feet are essentially flippers, working to propel him through the water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we know a little bit more about Michael Phelps and his career, let's see if any current swimmer has a chance to rival his legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Analysis&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Michael Phelps is such a well-rounded athlete, with medals in four stroke categories--freestyle, butterfly, medley, and backstroke--it would be unfair to judge the entirety of his career based on his success in one of these groups. Instead, this analysis will take a more holistic approach, comparing swimmers based on their success in international championships&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Olympic Games&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Micheal Phelps is perhaps best known for his performances in the Olympic Games, collecting 28 Olympic medals in five appearances. In 2016, when Michael Phelps retired from professional swimming, his medal count was unprecedented. Before Michael Phelps, the most decorated Olympian was Larisa Latynina, a Soviet gymnast of the 1960s who won a total of 18 medals. To get an idea of the success of Olympic swimmers before Michael Phelps, let's take a look at the graph below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many of these swimmers are amongst the 20 most decorated Olympians of all time, their medal counts pale in comparison to that of Michael Phelps. Furthermore, because all the swimmers on this list are retired, with the exception of 35 year old Ryan Lochte, none of them have a chance to surpass Phelps' medal count. But what about the younger generation of Olympic swimmers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any current Olympic swimmer were to break Phelps' record, he/she would have to be very young--no older than 25. The 20+ medal count advantage that Phelps has over any current swimmer would take many years to overcome. This swimmer would also need to have a few Olympic medals by now. Below is a table of all the current Olympic swimmers who fulfill these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of these 7 candidates, Katie Ledecky and Penny Oleksiak have the best chance of challenging the 28 medal record. Let's first talk about Katie Ledecky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: espn.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many followers of the professional swim scene consider Katie Ledecky to be the best female swimmer in the world. In her most recent Olympic appearance, Ledecky earned 5 medals. But she wasn't just placing top three in her events, she was winning them and often doing so by a significant margin. For example, in the 800m freestyle, she finished 12 seconds before the second place finisher! Katie Ledecky's dominance in events like these show her potential as an Olympic swimmer. As professional swimmers often retire in their early- to mid-30s, Ledecky will likely participate in four more Olympic Games. She will need to average approximately 6 medals per Olympics to tie Phelps' record. A challenging task, but certainly doable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: swimswam.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, Penny Oleksiak is a bit of a wildcard. In her first Olympic showing in 2016, Oleksiak won 4 medals--one gold, one silver, and two bronze. While Oleksiak walked away with only one medal less than Ledecky, her performance was far less convincing. Two of these medals were earned as a part of a 4 x 100m/200m team and her only gold medal was the result of a perfect tie. With this being said, Oleksiak is an incredibly young swimmer with plenty of time to improve. She is only 19 and could potentially compete in five more Olympic Games! With an average of 5 medals per Olympic showing, Oleksiak could become the most decorated Olympian of all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;FINA World Championships&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is more to swimming and an athlete's legacy than the Olympic Games. In the four years between one Olympic Games and the next, professional swimmers can compete in two World Championships and one Pan Pacific Championship. These events are a rare opportunity for professional swimmers to compete against their international competitors. As such, these competitions are taken very seriously. Because little data is available on the Pan Pacific Championship, we will focus on the World Championship in this analysis. Below is a table of the most successful swimmers in the history of the World Aquatics Championship (WAC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the Olympic Games, Michael Phelps' success at the WAC is unrivaled--for now. While Phelps is nonetheless the most decorated WAC swimmer, he has earned this title in a rather unconvincing fashion[b]. With 5 of the ten most accomplished swimmers of WAC history still competing, his title is far from safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shown above are the scatter plots and trend lines of the 5 active swimmers with the most WAC medals. The trend lines estimate each swimmer's potential medal count given their success in previous WACs and assuming he/she will compete until the age of 32. Let me use Caeleb Dressel's stats to explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/michaelPhelps/pic_11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: nbcsports.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, Caeleb Dressel competed in his first WAC at the age of 20, earning medals in seven different events. At the 2019 WAC, Dressel one-upped his previous performance, adding 8 medals to his collection. Because Dressel averages 7.5 medals per WAC and he is only 23, this model estimates that he will earn more than 50 WAC medals by the end of his career! It is important to keep in mind, however, that this model is imperfect. It doesn't account for factors such as the effects of age on performance or the possibility of injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of this model's imperfections, the graphs above give us a general idea of each swimmer's potential. Among this group, Caeleb Dressel and Katie Ledecky stand out. Their potential WAC medal count--52 and 42 respectively--are well above Phelps'. Even if these athletes retire early or experience a slight drop-off in performance, they have a good shot at taking Phelps' WAC medal count record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a 22 year old with 6 Olympic medals and 18 WAC medals, Katie Ledecky is a top contender to rival Phelps' legacy. Right now, Ledecky seems unstoppable. With every passing meet, she seems to outpace her competitors by greater and greater margins. It seems unlikely that any swimmer will be able to match Ledecky in the near future. If Ledecky continues her dominant run of form, she will certainly put Phelps' legacy to the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: swimswam.com, olympic.org, fina.org, and usaswimming.org&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Fischer Sherrod</name></author><summary type="html">With 28 Olympic gold medals, 27 World Championship gold medals, and 16 Pan Pacific Championship gold medals, Michael Phelps is the most decorated swimmer of all time. But Phelps' medals are just the beginning of his legacy. He has attended 5 Olympic Games, been named World Swimmer of the Year 7 times, and has set 39 world records--4 of which still stand today. His list of achievements goes on and on. In fact, many have acclaimed Phelps as 'the greatest swimmer of all time'. With his retirement in 2016, however, his achievements have flatlined. Now more than ever, the door is open for a new star to top his records and steal his title. The question is&amp;colon; Who could possibly rival Michael Phelps and the legacy that he has created?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Story of Kyle Shanahan’s Offense and Where He Went Wrong in Super Bowl LIV</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/KyleShanahan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Story of Kyle Shanahan’s Offense and Where He Went Wrong in Super Bowl LIV" /><published>2020-02-17T01:57:11-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-17T01:57:11-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/KyleShanahan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/KyleShanahan">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: San Francisco Chronicle&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing the 2016 season with 2 wins, the San Francisco 49ers decided it was time to try something new. They went into full-rebuild mode, giving six-year contracts to new head coach Kyle Shanahan and general manager John Lynch. Prior to their hiring, Shanahan was an accomplished play caller who was only 37 years old, while Lynch was a commentator for Fox Sports who had zero front office experience. It was certainly a gamble, but one that ultimately paid off as Shanahan and Lynch completely rebuilt the team from the ground up (46 of the 53 players on San Francisco’s roster were brought in by the new regime) and within three years, got the Niners to the Super Bowl for a shot at their sixth title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They ended up losing the game to Kansas City after holding a 10 point lead with under 10 minutes to play in the game, and blame has been thrown around various Niners players and coaches to explain the loss. But to truly understand what cost the 49ers the Super Bowl, it is important to know how this team really works and what makes it tick. Once you realize what this team really is, it becomes clear that it wasn't the defense or even the quarterback that cost the Niners the trophy; it was their play caller and head coach Kyle Shanahan himself. Let's look at Kyle Shanahan, the offense that he built in San Francisco, and what led to its fall in Super Bowl LIV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: New York Post&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle Shanahan is the son of Mike Shanahan, a former NFL coach considered by many to be one of the greatest offensive minds in NFL history (won Super Bowl XXIX with 49ers and XXXII and XXXIII with Broncos). Although Kyle played wide receiver at a Division-I school, he ultimately followed in his father's footsteps and became a coach in the NFL at a very young age. After spending years as an offensive quality control coach and quarterback coach with various teams, he got his first offensive coordinator job with the Houston Texans in 2008 at the age of 28. Over the next nine seasons, Shanahan served as the offensive coordinator for various teams and was incredibly successful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of the dysfunctional organization that is the Cleveland Browns, Shanahan was able to build all of his other offenses into Top-10 products. The 2016 Falcons were Shanahan's masterpiece; they displayed a surgical attack that scored the 7th most points in NFL history and netted quarterback Matt Ryan the league MVP award. They even took a commanding 25 point lead in Super Bowl LI before infamously blowing it and losing the game in the span of 22 minutes. The tough loss to end that historic season brings us to Shanahan's tenure in San Francisco as a head coach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Running Games Travel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Bleacher Report&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering his third season as the Niners head coach in 2019, after a couple of rocky and injury-riddled seasons to begin his head coaching career, Shanahan had finally put together the team he envisioned from the start in San Francisco. Despite coming off a previous job where he was known for his high-flying passing offense in Atlanta, he was still his father's son, and Mike Shanahan was known for finding unknown running backs and making them great behind a brilliant scheme. Kyle has been no different in San Francisco:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having three running backs, two of whom were not even drafted, in the Top-35 is a typical Shanahan staple. Mike Shanahan did this consistently in his time by having his backs play behind small but fast offensive lines. The goal was to open up gaping holes for the backs with speed and precision in blocking rather than pure power. The exact same philosophy went into the construction of San Francisco's offensive line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Niners have one of the NFL's best, if not the best, combination of light weight and speed in their offensive line. Having a line that gets downfield into the second and third levels of the defense faster than most allows San Francisco's running backs to gain huge chunks of yardage at a time and pick up tremendous speed while doing so. The average maximum speed by San Francisco's ball carriers on run plays this season was 13.27 MPH, the fastest in the NFL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 49ers rushing attack has Shanahan DNA smeared all over it, and Kyle Shanahan doesn't hesitate to make it the focal point of his entire offense. The Niners ran the ball on 51% of their offensive snaps this year, the second-highest clip in the NFL. But while the run game carried San Francisco to many wins, the other 49% of the offensive productivity was still important and proved to be the deciding factor in Super Bowl LIV. After all, Shanahan became a front-running head coaching candidate behind his creative aerial attack in Atlanta, which brings us to the hotly-debated man that Shanahan chose to be his quarterback in San Francisco: Jimmy Garoppolo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;What Do the Niners Have in Jimmy G?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: NBC Sports&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garoppolo receives copious amounts of criticism by most people who watch him, but he is in many ways exactly the quarterback that Kyle Shanahan wants to run his offense, and he put that on display in his first full year as a starter in 2019. To begin with, the beauty of Shanahan's offense comes on play action pass plays. His understanding of what defenders are instructed to do in certain situations combined with his running identity allows him to blow coverages wide open when he fakes handoffs and dials up plays downfield. This is what made Atlanta so deadly in 2016, and Garoppolo's ability to make splashes off of play action has allowed Shanahan to do the exact same thing in San Francisco:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garoppolo is given play action calls at the third-highest rate in the NFL, and while his overall passer rating is nothing special (101.8), play action Jimmy G. is the third-highest rated quarterback in the NFL (113.4). Shanahan dials up play action often, and Garoppolo gets the job done with incredible efficiency. On third down, Garoppolo's passer rating of 101.9 is also very solid. Moreover, Garoppolo does not throw the ball deep very often. In fact, his lack of deep ball throwing coupled with his tendency to throw the ball up for grabs every once in a while is what makes many critics lack faith in him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it appears that Garoppolo may be a poor deep ball thrower, his passer rating when going downfield is 105.2, almost 20 points above the league average and actually higher than Garoppolo's overall passer rating of 101.8. It's not that Garoppolo can't throw deep; Shanahan simply doesn't dial up such throws for him. Instead, Shanahan focuses the passing game on something else that explains Garoppolo's above-average rate of turnover worthy plays: the middle of the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Draft Kings Nation&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there's one statistic that the Niners offense is known for above anything else, it's YAC: Yards After the Catch. The way that Shanahan generates the YAC is by designing his plays to target the middle of the field, allowing his receivers to catch the ball with plenty of momentum and a lot of real estate around them so they can carry on for another chunk of yards before being tackled. This idea is well-reflected by Garoppolo's decisions on the field:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 70%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No quarterback in the NFL has a higher percentage of his targets go to routes that break inside than Garoppolo, as 50% of his throws go towards the middle of the field. Slinging the ball over the middle of the field constantly is surely dangerous, which explains Garoppolo's tendency to put the ball in harm's way more often than average. But Shanahan's philosophy is clear; he has built his passing game on the ability to gain YAC and, once again, Garoppolo has proven his ability to put that vision into action. Of the top 10 receivers and tight ends in the NFL for YAC, two play for the Niners:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shanahan brings in personnel based on his scheme that allows Garoppolo to thrive. Last year, when he was looking for a receiver, he could have easily drafted a monster like D.K. Metcalf who could out-muscle almost anyone, but he wasn't looking for size and strength. He instead drafted Deebo Samuel from South Carolina, a smaller player with speed, great hands, and fearlessness as a ball-carrier because those are the traits that make a great YAC receiver. George Kittle is no different at tight end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's clear that Shanahan has built every cubic centimeter of this offense the exact way that he wanted to. Garoppolo isn't asked to do too much thinking. Plays in the NFL where the quarterback doesn't have to make any read before throwing the ball (screen passes, etc.) are typically referred to as &quot;scheme&quot; looks. Garoppolo actually has the second highest percentage of such looks behind only rookie quarterback Kyler Murray:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 14&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing mysterious about Jimmy Garoppolo. The media wants to criticize him because he is not Aaron Rodgers or Patrick Mahomes, but Kyle Shanahan doesn't need him to be. He knows what he needs from Garoppolo and Garoppolo delivers it well: an efficient game manager who is good on third down and takes what Shanahan gives him down field. Sound familiar? There may be a certain six-time Super Bowl Champion quarterback with extremely similar traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the combination of a powerful run game and Garoppolo's efficiency in doing what Shanahan asks of him is what makes the Niners offense tick. This is the offense that Shanahan brought to the Super Bowl and ultimately failed with. The question we have finally arrived at is: what happened? The answer is rather complex, but can be simplified to one big idea. At the big moments in the game, Shanahan didn't become overly aggressive or even overly conservative. He instead became something worse than both of those things: scared and predictable. Chiefs quarterback Patrick Mahomes, with his ability to put up points in seconds, put enough fear into the 49ers play caller to the point that the flashy, quick, and creative Niners offense was reduced to a few predictable tendencies when it mattered most. As a result, Kansas City was able to pounce and take the trophy right out of Shanahan's hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Super Bowl LIV&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 15&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: The Mercury News&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a thorough understanding of San Francisco's offense, it's not hard to see that as they blossomed with Kyle Shanahan's play calling, they came crashing down just as fast when the puppet master himself made bad decisions. The Super Bowl started off fairly well for San Francisco; Shanahan opened the game with a couple of his classic reverse handoffs to Samuel and the Niners marched to the Chiefs' 20 yard line, where they ultimately settled for a field goal. After Kansas City responded with a touchdown, Garoppolo made his first big mistake of the game: an ill-advised floating ball right into the hands of Chiefs defensive back Bashaud Breeland. Kansas City consolidated the pick with 3 more points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, having a young quarterback that just threw an interception in a big game would cause a head coach to dial the offense back a little to let his guy get into a rhythm again. But Garoppolo has a quality that allows Shanahan to pretend as if the interception never happened; he is beyond excellent on drives following an interception:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_16.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 16&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Garoppolo right after throwing a pick is the best quarterback in football. Shanahan was well aware of this and did not hold back on the next drive. Along with a couple of great running plays, post-interception Jimmy G. went 3-for-3 for 42 yards and a touchdown to fullback Kyle Juszczyk. The first throw was a scheme play to Samuel and the next two were off play action to the middle of the field: a textbook Kyle Shanahan drive to tie the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shanahan's first big blunder came at the end of the half. The game was tied at 10 and the Niners stopped Kansas City with about 1:45 left in the half; instead of calling a timeout, Shanahan decided to let the clock run down to start his drive with 59 seconds left. After a few plays, the Niners had the ball at their own 45 yard line with just 14 seconds left, but Shanahan had something in mind. One of his specialties is his ability to exploit mismatches at opportune times and embarrass defenders. In this case, he had the perfect mismatch dialed up to justify his tanking of 40 seconds just a minute ago. Kansas City came out with six defensive backs. Two safeties were about 11 yards off the ball and Shanahan had his three wide receivers (and thus three Chiefs cornerbacks) lined up to Garoppolo's left, leaving tight end George Kittle isolated with backup safety Daniel Sorensen on the right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 17&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 110%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
		Source: NBC Sports&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely enough, Kittle got separation and Garoppolo dropped the ball right in his hands for about 40 yards. Unfortunately, Kittle pushed off on the play even though he didn't need to, and the play was nullified due to the penalty. With just six seconds left, the first half, and thus the Niners' drive, came to an abrupt stop. Shanahan later admitted that he tanked the 40 seconds because he did not want to risk Kansas City getting the ball back with enough time to score, in case they stopped him deep in his own territory. He made his decision out of fear of what the Chiefs were capable of and as a result, he put all of his chips in on a play that was neither creative nor clever but rather reactive and forceful. He could have taken the timeout and had plenty of time to engineer a proper drive, but fear made him waste a potential scoring drive and cost San Francisco a halftime lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shanahan came out strong in the second half. The Niners kicked a field goal on the opening drive and after Mahomes threw an interception, got the ball back in good field position. Garoppolo fired another three lasers over the middle of the field, two of which were off play action, for 52 yards and San Francisco found the endzone. This would be the last time they scored all night. Kansas City eventually scored a touchdown with 6:13 left in the game and cut the lead to 3 points, 20-17. The next two San Francisco drives contained a sequence of events that made Shanahan look silly and won Kansas City the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the drive following Kansas City's score, on a 2nd down and 5, Garoppolo fired a ball that was intended for Kittle short in the middle of the field, but Chiefs defensive tackle Chris Jones jumped up and swatted the ball with perfect timing. The drive ended after Kansas City blitzed on 3rd down and Garoppolo launched the ball out of harm's way. Then, with 2:44 left in the game, Kansas City scored a touchdown and took the lead. San Francisco came back onto the field and on 1st and 10 at midfield, Garoppolo fired a ball to Deebo Samuel over the middle that was blocked by Jones &lt;i&gt;again&lt;/i&gt;. What was going on? It's extremely difficult for a defensive lineman to block a throw, let alone do it twice in the span of two drives in a Super Bowl. The answer lies in the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_18.gif&quot; alt=&quot;picture 18&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: NFL Films (Youtube)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both of the plays that Jones swatted the ball, Garoppolo's intended receivers (Kittle and Samuel) were lined up in the slot to his right. Garoppolo's average distance of throw in 2019 to each of these receivers was 6.1 and 7.6 yards respectively. Based on his 2019 targets, Garoppolo's probability of throwing inside on routes within that range is almost twice as high as his probability of throwing outside (29% vs. 15% respectively). But that's not all. Kittle and Samuel are Garoppolo's favorite targets by a mile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_19.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 19&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 40% of his completions go to these two receivers, and among his pass catchers who aren't running backs, Kittle and Samuel are in the top 3 in terms of the speed at which Garoppolo gets the ball out of his hands. The moment Kittle and Samuel lined up in the slot on their respective plays, Chris Jones knew two things: this receiver is going to break into the short middle of the field and the ball is coming out &lt;i&gt;fast&lt;/i&gt;. What Shanahan thought were high-percentage plays were actually the most predictable sequences of the game. Jones was simply timing Garoppolo and throwing his hands up to block the passes; Shanahan's plays in crunchtime were undone not by brilliant coverage, but by a defensive lineman that just did his homework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the play immediately after the blocked pass to Samuel, Shanahan tried to mix it up a little with a deeper throw over the middle to Kendrick Bourne. Jones didn't get the block, but at this point the Chiefs secondary had a feel for what was going on. Safety Kendall Fuller simply sat on the route, dove into the passing lane, and nearly got an interception. On 3rd down, Shanahan took a shot to the endzone to Emmanuel Sanders (the exact same play that won San Francisco their week 16 game vs. the Rams) and Garoppolo overthrew the ball. By 4th down, the Niners offense had lost all its energy from the previous three plays and Garoppolo inevitably took a sack. With 1:25 left in the game, the Super Bowl was over. Kansas City put the icing on the cake with a final touchdown and the game ended with a score of 31-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kyleShanahan/pic_20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 20&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Sports Illustrated&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's ridiculous to blame Garoppolo for missing on a 49 yard bomb to the endzone on 3rd down in a Super Bowl with under 2 minutes to go. It's equally ridiculous to blame San Francisco's defense when they were getting almost zero rest due to their offense's lack of productivity the entire fourth quarter. The fact of the matter is that in the moments of truth, Shanahan worried so much about getting a single first down at a time that he lost sight of how to break the defense over a sequence of well-arranged plays, and instead went for seemingly high-percentage calls that Kansas City had studied all week. When his team needed to move the football more than ever, he lost his identity and let them down. Heading into the Super Bowl, everybody fully expected Kansas City's defense to commit to stopping the run and force Garoppolo to make some plays, and Garoppolo did what was expected of him. If the Niners had won, he would have been the MVP. He took what was given to him by his coach as he had all year. His coach was simply not giving him the right stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Super Bowl LI and now Super Bowl LIV, Shanahan and Super Bowls have become a dynamic duo in all the wrong ways. He's only 40 years old and he will likely be coaching for decades to come. He's too good not to. He's built a culture in San Francisco that any team would die for. He has his players playing selflessly and his coaches believing in everything he does. The way that NFL executives speak of him would have you believe that he is the second coming of Bill Belichick. Kyle Shanahan will win a Super Bowl someday, but until then, he's officially got a monkey on his back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: Pro Football Focus, ESPN, pro-football-reference.com, playerprofiler.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kathir Ilango</name></author><summary type="html">After finishing the 2016 season with 2 wins, the San Francisco 49ers decided it was time to try something new. They went into full-rebuild mode, giving six-year contracts to new head coach Kyle Shanahan and general manager John Lynch. Prior to their hiring, Shanahan was an accomplished play caller who was only 37 years old, while Lynch was a commentator for Fox Sports who had zero front office experience. It was certainly a gamble, but one that ultimately paid off as Shanahan and Lynch completely rebuilt the team from the ground up (46 of the 53 players on San Francisco’s roster were brought in by the new regime) and within three years, got the Niners to the Super Bowl for a shot at their sixth title.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Sustainability of Lamar Jackson’s Production</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sustainability of Lamar Jackson's Production" /><published>2020-02-01T17:44:24-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-01T17:44:24-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/LamarJackson">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: miro.medium.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When tasked with winning football games, every head coach in the NFL talks about establishing an identity, as all the best teams have one. The 49ers are winning off of a multi-dimensional running game and a ferocious defense that gets to the opposing quarterback. The Saints are winning off a dink-and-dunk quick-hitter offense. The Chiefs are winning with speed on the outside and a lethal deep-ball passer. The Patriots have been &quot;doing their job&quot; for the last 2 decades. But out of all the teams in football, there's one team's identity which stands out as the most established, physical, and against-the-grain in all of football&amp;colon; the 14-2 Baltimore Ravens, the best team in the league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all starts with their stifling defense which, once again, is a contender for the league's best. While they have a good defensive line, where they really shine is at defensive-back, where they have the league's deepest and most dangerous group. Headlined by the elite ball-hawking Earl Thomas and suffocating Marlon Humphry, the Ravens also have three other feisty cornerbacks in Brandon Carr, Jimmy Smith and Marcus Peters. On the other side of the ball, the Ravens run the rock up the opposition's throat, with a rock-solid offensive-line anchored by Ronnie Stanley and the ageless Marshal Yanda, premier blocking tight-ends in Mark Andrews and Nick Boyle, and one of the league's angriest runners in Mark Ingram. But these assets aren't what makes the Ravens special; they've been this type of team for a long time.  The addition of one piece has made their offense go from byzantine to innovative, from stagnant to electric. This one piece is arguably the best mobile quarterback in NFL history: Lamar Jackson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2013, the last time the Ravens won the Super Bowl, the NFL was a very different place. For starters, the team they faced in the Super Bowl, the 49ers, had Colin Kaepernick installed as their starting quarterback following an electric run to the big game. Kaepernick was one of the hottest young quarterbacks in the game because of his legs, having gashed the Packers in that very same playoff run for 181 yards and 2 touchdowns on an 11.3 yards per carry clip. This performance set the record for most single-game rushing yards by a quarterback not only in the playoffs, but in any game in NFL history, a record that still stands today. On top of that, the Rookie of the Year that season was none other than current Ravens back-up, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap1000000134287/article/robert-griffin-iii-wins-offensive-rookie-of-the-year&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robert Griffin III&lt;/a&gt; (RG3), who capped off a historic rookie season with 815 yards on the ground, a number that ranks 7th all time for quarterbacks. Another rookie that season was Russell Wilson, a player whose best rushing season ranks one rung above RG3's, at 849 yards. All of this is to say that the last time the Ravens were dominant, rushing quarterbacks were a trend. Since then, mobile quarterbacks like RG3, Kaepernick, Marcus Mariota, Tim Tebow and Johnny Manziel have flamed out, while remaining players with this skillset like Russell Wilson and the younger Deshaun Watson rely more heavily on their passing ability than their legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this trend slowly dying out, Lamar Jackson was a polarizing prospect when he finally hit the NFL draft in 2018. Michael Vick, the consensus greatest mobile quarterback of all-time before Lamar Jackson, endorsed him as a better runner than himself, but due to the decline of this skill's usage, many teams didn't even view Jackson as a quarterback prospect. Hall of Fame General Manager Bill Polian referred to Jackson as &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2760372-bill-polian-says-lamar-jackson-is-short-should-move-to-wr-in-the-nfl?source=post_page---------------------------&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;too slight for the position&lt;/a&gt;, not enough of a thrower, and stated that he should switch to a position such as wide-receiver, which is more reliant on speed. Jackson ended up being selected 32nd overall in the NFL draft, and is currently revitalizing speed for his position. His 1206 rushing yards through 15 games this season is an NFL record, shattering Michael Vick's previous high of 1039, and making him a surefire bet to win the MVP. After seeing this historical production, I wanted to measure Jackson's improvement since his rookie season, see how he stacks up to past quarterbacks in this department, and decide how sustainable his current level of production is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, through 7 starts in his rookie season, Lamar Jackson had 556 yards on the ground, an average of 79.4 yards and 17 attempts per game. Despite the excellent production, 17 rushing attempts is an unsustainable number for a quarterback. To make this number tangible, look no further than this year's leading rusher Derrick Henry. Henry is &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.redd.it/fq9o7krtz9d11.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;built like a truck&lt;/a&gt; and led the league in rushing this season. Despite all this, Henry averaged a hair under 19 carries a game (18.93), less than 2 carries per game more than Jackson in his 2018 season. The Ravens knew this had to change too, and hired Kaepernick's former offensive coordinator, Greg Roman, to run the offense. This season, Jackson averaged an even better 80.4 yards per game over a 15 game sample, but averaged under 12 attempts (11.7) per game on the ground, a much more sustainable number. To put Jackson's production in context, Ezekiel Elliott, who had the 4th most rushing yards in the league this season, rushed for 1357 yards in 16 games, which averages out to 84.8 yards per game. He did this in 125 more attempts than Jackson. Obviously, Jackson has the element of surprise on his side, and defenses crowd the box on Zeke, but still, a quarterback rushing for close to the same yardage per game as the highest paid running-back in the league is just absurd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph displayed below shows Lamar Jackson's per-game stats as a rookie compared to other notable running-backs' in 2018. This dot-plot includes every single 2018 pro-bowler at the position, as well as a few other notable players, such as Mark Ingram, Leonard Fournette and Jordan Howard. Despite the smaller sample size, the fact that he ranked 3rd in carries and 4th in yardage per game from the quarterback position over his last 7 games is eye opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jackson's development as a passer has been the key difference that has allowed him to drastically improve his production on a per-carry basis, as it doesn't allow defenses to blitz and key off on his running ability. At the end of last season, many were calling Lamar Jackson more of a running back than a quarterback. NFL.com's QB Index wrote that while Jackson arguably added more value as a runner in half a season than any quarterback in NFL history, his errant throws and league-leading 12 fumbles (in 7 games) kept his value in check, ranking Lamar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001007337/article/qb-index-patrick-mahomes-leads-yearend-rankings&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;23rd in the league&lt;/a&gt; out of 32 starting quarterbacks. At the end of this season, he was the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001091708/article/qb-index-week-17-patrick-mahomes-vaults-russell-wilson&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;consensus number 1&lt;/a&gt; and an MVP shoo-in. What parts of his passing game improved? According to Pro Football Reference (PFR), his ANY/A (Adjusted Net Yards per pass Attempt) has gone up from 5.99 to 8.19, his completion percentage has gone up from a terrible 58.2% to a much better 66.1%, and his sack percentage has gone down from 8.6% to 5.4%. To rationalize this data, when analyzing PFR's passing index, where a score of 100 is league average and anything higher is better, Jackson has gone from below average values hovering in the 90s range to above average values in the early 100s in every notable passing stat, among them ANY/A, Touchdown Percentage (TD%), Interception Percentage (INT%) and Completion Percentage (CMP%). His touchdown percentage, in particular, was tops in the league, as he had a league-leading 36 passing touchdowns on the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stats show his increased mastery of the passing game, which increases the opportunity to make misdirection plays and establish a dominant running-game for the Ravens. The opposing defense must respect the pass and can no longer crowd up the line-of-scrimmage to stuff the run. The ANY/A in particular is telling, as this statistic has a strong correlation with offensive production. It is essentially a formula which takes passing yards, adds the number of touchdowns times a multiplier, subtracts the yardage lost due to sacks and the number of interceptions times a multiplier, then divides the total by the sum of the passing attempts and number of sacks taken. While this sounds like complicated jargon, it's essentially just calculating the average yards per play with touchdowns and interceptions thrown factored in. Thus, the ANY/A is an effective way to see how well a quarterback is able to lead his offense to points. This and the rest of Jackson's passing statistics help explain why his yards-per-attempt while rushing the football was substantially higher this season, sitting at 6.9 yards-per-attempt this year compared to last season's 4.7 average. It also helps explain how the Ravens as a team set the NFL's all time record for rushing yards in a season, with their 3296 yards on the ground breaking a mark that stood for 41 years prior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Lamar Jackson's improvement as a passer has fueled his and his team's improved statistical performance, I wanted to see just how sustainable this improvement truly is. Visually, Jackson's uniqueness is obvious. Lamar is just built different. He has unreal speed, better shiftiness than most running-backs, and touch on his passes. But, we've seen players like Kaepernick and RG3 take the league by storm in the past, just to regress to league average or worse in their next season. In order to gain statistical insight on what level of regression to expect, I recorded the statistics of a group of mobile quarterbacks in their first full season as a starter, and compared this to their statistics in their next full season accrued as a starter, attempting to see whether defenses figured them out. Players like Lamar Jackson and Colin Kaepernick had seasons where they started 7 games before their first full season, so I set the threshold of a full season as a starter to be a Week 1 starter who played at least 14 games. In order for me to consider the quarterback mobile, I wanted them to average at least 3 carries per game in their first season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to conduct this experiment, I gathered the statistics in major passing and rushing metrics for 10 mobile quarterbacks in the 2000s. This group consisted of Colin Kaepernick, Robert Griffin III, Marcus Mariota, Mitchell Trubisky, Russell Wilson, Cam Newton, Michael Vick, Daunte Culpepper, Dak Prescott and Deshaun Watson. While many of these players obviously play differently from Lamar, I believe most of these players are more than capable of running the football. Mitchell Trubisky and Marcus Mariota have shown commendable speed rushing the football, while Vick, Culpepper, Griffin and Kaepernick have had huge games on the ground. Newton, Wilson, Watson and Prescott have all had spurts of MVP play and have shown the ability to run and pass effectively throughout their careers. When collecting data, I once again started off by focusing on the Pro-Football-Reference metrics for ANY/A, Completion Percentage, Touchdown Percentage and Interception Percentage, four of the most important statistics for a quarterback. I found the Pro-Football-Reference metric valuable because it measured a quarterback's statistics in these categories relative to their peers in that given year, providing a standardized metric that adjusts for the changes in the passing game from Vick and Culpepper's eras to the present. Regardless, I found that all the players in the sample, on average, had above average statistics in their first full season as a starter. In their next full season, after an entire offseason of defenses keying in on their tendencies, this population of quarterbacks, on average, was slightly below league-average. Considering that the list contains a handful of MVP level talents, the observation that these quarterbacks went from close to the top 10 players at their positions to barely average is shocking. Obviously, there were some exceptions, but almost all the quarterbacks showed a slight regression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, wanting to also look at raw statistical change, I compared the raw values of each of these quarterback's rushing attempts, yards, ANY/A, TD% and INT% to see the noticeable per-player changes in each statistic. To do this, I found each of these quarterback's statistics in their first full year, and either found a proportional change (ANY/A), percentage change (TD%, INT%), or the raw change (rushing yards and attempts per game) in their statistics the next-season. This thus calculates the average individual performance decrease, regardless of a player's talent, as the player is now only being compared with himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/lamarJackson/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings proved to be insightful. Firstly, most quarterbacks kept rushing the football the same amount, with around the same number of production. Exceptions included Trubisky and RG3, who both saw their number of rushing attempts decrease by over 1 attempt per game, as well as Culpepper, who saw an uptick in usage and production. The rushing attempts and yards per game of the average player remained almost the same, decreasing by a miniscule 0.16 attempts and 0.95 yards per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the Adjusted Net Yards per Attempt (ANY/A), the ANY/A value in the following year was 0.84 times the value in the first year. Thus, the regression was 0.16 multiplied by the ANY/A in the first year, with the proportional decrease displayed. Essentially, all that means is that these players were 16% less efficient in using their arm to gain yards and lead their offense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the touchdown percentage dipped by 1.1%, meaning 1.1% less of these quarterbacks' throws resulted in touchdowns. Culpepper had the most jarring drop in touchdown percentage, with 3.2% less of his passes ending in paydirt. Only two players had their touchdown percentages go up: Deshaun Watson and Michael Vick. On the flipside, the interception percentage went up, with these quarterbacks throwing picks, on average, on 0.58% more of their throws. Watson and Dak Prescott had the most sizeable increase in picks thrown, with 1.8% more of their passes winding up in the opposition's hands. That adds up to almost an extra 1 out of 50 passes ending up in a turnover. The average quarterback throws over 30 passes per game, so this number is significant over an entire season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does all this mean in-terms of Lamar? If we go by the raw average changes calculated, Lamar's ANY/A will go down to 6.88, his league-leading touchdown rate will go down to 7.9%, and his interception rate will go up to close to 2.1%. The data also indicates that his rushing attempts and yardage per game would remain somewhat similar. But, as we all know, all players are different, and even with these statistics factoring in an expected regression, Lamar Jackson would still be a player capable of wrecking games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Lamar Jackson is still going to be a game-changer, and the Raven's defense is still going to be suffocating. Regardless, I would expect defenses to catch on to Jackson to a certain extent, and I expect his statistics next season to hover closer to the numbers listed above than to those he recorded in his 2019 MVP campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking for a team to compare this Ravens group to, it's hard not to go back to the last time the Ravens hoisted the Lombardi Trophy and see parallels to the team they beat that fateful day. Both the 2019 Ravens and the 2013 49ers had a dynamic quarterback who took the league by storm, a stifling defense stacked with difference-makers, and most importantly, a Harbaugh at head coach.  Regardless of the similarities between Lamar's and Kaepernick's supporting casts, one of these players is the presumptive league MVP, and one of them has never made a Pro-Bowl. Despite this season's disappointing end, I expect Lamar Jackson and the Ravens to keep on flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: pro-football-reference.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vishal Sundaram</name></author><summary type="html">When tasked with winning football games, every head coach in the NFL talks about establishing an identity, as all the best teams have one. The 49ers are winning off of a multi-dimensional running game and a ferocious defense that gets to the opposing quarterback. The Saints are winning off a dink-and-dunk quick-hitter offense. The Chiefs are winning with speed on the outside and a lethal deep-ball passer. The Patriots have been &quot;doing their job&quot; for the last 2 decades. But out of all the teams in football, there's one team's identity which stands out as the most established, physical, and against-the-grain in all of football&amp;colon; the 14-2 Baltimore Ravens, the best team in the league.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Brief History of MLB Postseason Format Changes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Brief History of MLB Postseason Format Changes" /><published>2020-01-25T13:53:48-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-25T13:53:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/MLBpostseason">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: cnycentral.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many baseball fans, the MLB postseason&amp;mdash;the World Series in particular&amp;mdash;is the ultimate test of skill and teamwork. Over the course of a month, the best teams battle it out to become the World Series champion. Dating back to the first MLB postseason in 1884, the title of World Series champion has been the highest achievement that a professional baseball team can attain. Thus, the importance of the postseason to MLB teams and baseball enthusiasts alike cannot be understated. This, however, has not kept the MLB from changing the postseason format every 10 to 20 years. As expected, these changes are met with criticism and controversy, roster and strategy changes, and&amp;mdash;in rare cases&amp;mdash;MLB dynasties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the MLB postseason was first introduced to the professional league in 1884, it was very simple. After a few years of simple exhibition matches, the MLB decided on a postseason format that consisted of only one series&amp;mdash;later to be called the World Series. In this format, the top-seeded teams from the American League and the National League would face off in a single best-of-seven series (in 1903, 1919, 1920, and 1921 a best-of-nine was played). This oversimplified version was used for nearly a hundred years before it was modified. In 1969, when each of the MLB leagues were split into two regions, the postseason was extended to become a two round best-of-seven series. In this format, the top teams of each league would compete against one another in the ALCS and the NLCS before advancing to the World Series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: britannica.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a new region was again added to each MLB league in 1995, a third round, this time a best-of-five was added to the postseason. To accomodate for the odd numbers, a wild card team was added to each league; the wild card team would play the divisional champion in the best-of-five Division Series. Finally, in 2012 a second wild card was added to each league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you have probably concluded, the MLB's postseason format quickly became one of the most variable in all of American sports history. The ramifications of these changes were felt far and wide among the baseball community. One of the most direct impacts of these changes was on match variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before 1969, when the MLB postseason was comprised of a single series, match variation was nonexistent. At the end of each season, the top-seeded of the American League or the National League was guaranteed to win the World Series. However, as the MLB postseason was extended to accommodate for internal league changes, more and more teams gained access to the once elite MLB postseason. Resultantly, the World Series became unpredictable. As of 2019, ten teams participate in the MLB postseason, each fighting for the title of World Series champion. No teams are guaranteed a spot in the World Series, or even the ALCS and NLCS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any advantage that top-seeded teams once had in the MLB postseason is slowly diminishing. Let's take a look at how the probability of a top team winning the World Series has changed since 1969.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, these results are fairly straightforward. As the leagues split into more distinct regions and wild card teams were added to the MLB postseason, the top-seeded teams struggled to stay consistent. If more spots are made available in the MLB postseason in the future, this trend will likely continue; the title of top seed will lose the little competitive edge that it now provides. Even if the current format remains unchanged for years to come, the spike seen in the 2012-2019 seasons will likely drop off as more data is made available. But what does this trend mean for MLB fans and teams today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For casual fans, this trend is nothing but beneficial. The expansion of the MLB postseason has provided baseball fans with content that was previously unavailable. Furthermore, the changes made to the MLB postseason have made the games more enticing&amp;mdash;no games are unwinnable and no spots are secure.  The MLB postseason can take any number of turns before a World Series champion is crowned, as the Washington Nationals showed us this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: washington.org&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For MLB teams, things are a bit more complicated. In recent years, the postseason format has come to influence team play styles and strategies. Due to the expansion of the MLB postseason, many teams have attempted to adopt a more conservative, consistent play style. In today's three round best-of-seven series format, consistency is more important than ever. To win the World Series, a team must be able to play at the highest level at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the format changes have resulted in an extended MLB postseason, they have not always resulted in the most competitive games. When wild card teams and the Division Series were first introduced to the postseason in 1995, competition levels took a turn for the worst. Under this new format, the wildcard teams&amp;mdash;often considered the underdog teams of each league&amp;mdash;would immediately face off against the top-seeded divisional champion of their respective league. In recent years, these matchups have given top teams an easy route to the ALCS or NLCS. Consequently, many top-seeded teams arrive to the ALCS or NLCS unprepared for the competition and pressure that the series will surely bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the differences may be subtle, they cannot be ignored. For the ALCS and the World Series, there is little to be said. The average number of games played per series has remained relatively constant, despite postseason format changes. The NLCS, however, brings up questions for concern. From 1985 to 1993, the average number of games played per NLCS was 6.3. In today's postseason format, this number is almost a whole game lower at 5.5. In a simple best-of-seven series, this change is quite drastic. Although we cannot be sure what brought about this change, it is likely that MLB postseason format changes&amp;mdash;specifically the addition of wild card teams&amp;mdash;had a direct impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how could something as impartial as format changes possibly have such an impact?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation is the prevalence of baseball dynasties or 'dream teams' in recent years. As the postseason format has changed over the years, so has the importance of consistent play. When the postseason was first introduced to the MLB, inconsistent teams won the World Series quite frequently. However, in today's three round best-of-seven series, consistency is more or less a requirement. Thus, as consistent play gradually became more and more important, select teams were able to find their niche among a particular postseason format. The result was an absolute domination of MLB league and postseason play. Let's see if any baseball dynasties formed from 1995 to 2011 in which the three series best-of-seven (with one wild card team for each league) format was used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the New York Yankees were able to find great success in the MLB postseason throughout these years. Whether or not this success was due the postseason format cannot be known for sure. However, the history of the New York Yankees and their performance in previous MLB postseasons support the claim that the postseason format played a major role in their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 1985 to 1993, when the postseason was a two round best-of-seven series, the New York Yankees were unable to win a single World Series. When this format was changed, however, the Yankees looked like an entirely new team. In the early years of this new format, the Yankees were unstoppable; they were crowned World Series champion three years in a row, beginning in 1998. Without the postseason format change of 1995, it is unlikely that the Yankees would have been so dominant in these years. When the postseason format was changed in 2012, their success came to an end. Since these changes, the New York Yankees have not won, or participated in, the World Series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many professional baseball teams and fans dream of a time when the MLB stops altering the postseason format, it is unlikely that this dream will come true any time soon. While previous format changes have resulted in lower levels of postseason competition and occasional dynasties, the MLB has only benefited from the changes. By extending the postseason format and introducing wild card teams, the MLB is raking in more cash than ever. The MLB has no reason to halt the postseason changes that they have profited so greatly from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mlbPostseason/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2001, the MLB has seen annual increases in revenue. In more recent years, this trend has only become more apparent. Every year, the MLB seems to outperform themselves, pushing their annual revenue to unprecedented levels. With this in mind, I would not be surprised to see the MLB postseason expanded even further in upcoming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: baseball-reference.com, statista.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Fischer Sherrod</name></author><summary type="html">For many baseball fans, the MLB postseason&amp;mdash;the World Series in particular&amp;mdash;is the ultimate test of skill and teamwork. Over the course of a month, the best teams battle it out to become the World Series champion. Dating back to the first MLB postseason in 1884, the title of World Series champion has been the highest achievement that a professional baseball team can attain. Thus, the importance of the postseason to MLB teams and baseball enthusiasts alike cannot be understated. This, however, has not kept the MLB from changing the postseason format every 10 to 20 years. As expected, these changes are met with criticism and controversy, roster and strategy changes, and&amp;mdash;in rare cases&amp;mdash;MLB dynasties.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christian Yelich and the Rise to Stardom</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ChristianYelich" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christian Yelich and the Rise to Stardom" /><published>2020-01-15T10:30:55-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-15T10:30:55-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ChristianYelich</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ChristianYelich">&lt;p&gt;Drafted as a Florida Marlin 23rd overall in 2010, Christian Yelich was a very highly touted prospect with loads of potential. As predictions usually go for players drafted in the first few rounds, he was expected to eventually reach the Major Leagues and be a top of the order bat, hitting in a fierce and intimidating Marlins lineup (80-82, 3rd in NL East in 2010) that was supposed to include Giancarlo Stanton, Hanley Ramirez, Emilio Bonifacio, Cameron Maybin, and eventually Marcell Ozuna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.minorleagueball.com/2012/5/23/3037479/prospect-of-the-day-christian-yelich-of-miami-marlins-scouting-report&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A scouting report compiled by John Sickles on minorleagueball.com&lt;/a&gt; in 2012 stated that Yelich has a &quot;decent feel for the strike zone and is tapping into his natural power with greater efficiency. Although he isn't likely to develop into an overwhelming home run masher, Yelich should hit for average, get on base at a good clip, and produce above-average power.&quot; Florida (then Miami after the 2012 season) began it's rebuild late into 2017, sending both Stanton and Ozuna away. In early 2018, Yelich was traded to the Brewers in exchange for a plethora of top prospects, including outfielder Lewis Brinson, the Brewers top prospect at the time. The Brewers, anticipating a leadoff man in return from Miami, were actually in store for much more than they bargained for. Yelich became one of the most dangerous hitters in the MLB, now a perennial MVP leader with a massive uptick in power and Batting Average, whos also one of the leaders in stolen bases in the National League. On July 19th, Yelich had batted 60 Home Runs and stolen 33 bases in his previous 162 games, the first MLB player to ever launch 60+ HR and swipe 30+ SB in that time span.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how was he able to do this? How did Christian Yelich change his approach at the plate, shifting him from a slightly above average MLB player with the Miami Marlins to one who is seemingly on track to become a first ballot Hall of Famer with the Brewers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we take a dive into the mind of Milwaukee's Starting Right Fielder, understanding the slight tweaks that have created such dominance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We begin with the way in which Yelich has changed his approach at the plate. Following the trade from Miami to Milawukee, the right fielder has decreased the average amount of pitches that he seen per plate appearance, with the number now falling under 4. A rate of less than 4 pitches per at bat means Yelich has clearly seen the ball better and attacked early, not letting himself get too deep into counts, where he could be in danger of seeing tough offspeed pitches (sliders, curveballs, changeups) that are known for producing swings and misses. This strategy in the batters box is further evidenced by Yelich's 1st pitch swing percentage. His swing rate has shot up from an average of 19.4% over his 5 seasons with the Marlins to tallies of 28.8% and 29.7% respectively in his first two campaigns with the Brewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There simply do not exist enough players in baseball who swing on the first pitch, as most hitters take in order to get a sense of how the pitcher is throwing. However, a large portion of the time, when a pitcher hurls in his first pitch of an at bat, they do so with the intention of getting a sense of the strike zone. This is where hitters like Yelich have now begun to cash in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite his tendency to swing early and often, Yelich has also walked in a substantial 13.8% of his at bats, good enough for a rate that clocks in as the 14th highest in the Major Leagues. It certainly makes sense why this number is very high, as pitchers are scared to throw hittable pitches to the star right fielder. However, his slight adjustments in the off season prior to Milwaukee have clearly added an effective plate discipline to Yelich's aggressive approach, leading to the productivity that can be seen from his results at the plate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest contributors to Yelich's exponential boost in offensive production has to do with launch angle. It's a known phenomenon that an increase in launch angle has a positive correlation with an increase in extra base hits. Many thought that Yelich would regress slightly from his 2018 campaign, playing off his MVP season as a fluke, calling him a magician on the offensive side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Yelich has frankly gotten even better in 2019. In his 2018 campaign, his launch angle was ranked 445th in the MLB at 4.7 degrees. In 2019, he has more than doubled his launch angle degree to 11.2, a statistic that ranked him 278th in the MLB. An increase in launch angle leads to an increase in fly balls which leads to an increase in home runs and extra base hits. As we can see in the below graph, as his launch angle increased, his ratio of XBH to hits has also followed suit. Because of this, he has seen less of his batted balls hit the ground in comparison to the amount that are skyrocketed into the air. Yelich, in his MVP year, had 57 of the balls that he put into play hit the barrel of his bat (8.8%), ranking 18th in the big leagues. This year, in less games and 71 fewer at-bats, Yelich has had 59 of his batted balls hit the barrel of his bat (10.2%) ranking him 7th in the majors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Hosmer and Christian Yelich had once been very similar players based on their style of play and their approach at the plate. However, the reason that Yelich is accelerating into the peak and prime of his career and Hosmer is on the decline (his peak coming with the Kansas City Royals from 2013 to 2017) is because unlike Hosmer, Yelich has made the necessary adjustments to his launch angle (Hosmer ranks 451st in the MLB with an average launch angle of 2.1%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yelich is now hitting 3x the amount of homers as Hosmer and grounding into now about 2/3 of the amount of double plays as Hosmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the two graphs below, before joining the Brewers, Yelich didn't contribute much towards his respective teams' win rate as he was hovering around 50% for the majority of his career. However, largely contributed to his adjustments at the plate, since joining the Brewers, Yelich is hovering around a 55% win rate, so he is contributing to 5% more wins for a .500 team. A correlation can be drawn between the steady rise of Yelich's OPS and the fluctuations in the added winning percentage he brings to an average team. The raise in OPS seen in Yelich's stat line since joining Milwaukee can be attributed partially to his decreasing AB/HR rate, meaning Yelich is hitting with an increased amount of power as a result of the changes he has made to his swing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In talking about the Brewers as a team, Milwaukee finished the 2018 season at 95-67, 1st in the NL Central, advancing to the NLCS before losing the pennant in 7 games to the Los Angeles Dodgers, who eventually lost in the World Series to the Boston Red Sox. Now, in 2019, at the time of initial data collection, the Brewers stood at 78-69, 4.0 games off of the division lead, and tied with Chicago for the 2nd wild card spot. With Yelich's performance, it begs the question as to where the team would be without his production at the plate. Yelich's WAR for the 2018 clocked in at 7.6, and he had already accumulated a total of 7.1 up to August 10th, in about 15 fewer games, when he suffered a fractured knee cap, ending his season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing Yelich from the Brewers roster resulted in an NLDS lineup of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the WAR statistic as a numerical measure of how this team would perform, rather than just looking at the potential lineup and observing that the Brewers look much less threatening without Yelich, the Brewers would have finished last season around a mark of 87-75, and would currently be a sub-.500 team at 71-76 overall at this point in the year. This would have left the Brewers completely out of last year's playoffs (forget their first division title since 2011) and second in the last 36 years or their NLDS win, and near advancement to the World Series. This season, they would be 11 games behind the Cardinals at the top of the division, and another 7 games back of the wild card, clearly a seller at the trade deadline, and not a team that reached the NL Wild Card Game. His 0.543% Waa, which indicates the winning percentage of a .500 club if they added Christian Yelich to their roster, is a good representation of how just his bat alone can turn an average team into a contender. With Yelich locked up until the 2023 season, being paid just upwards of $7M annually, the Brewers have a considerable amount of money to work with to add in the missing pieces that are halting World Series contention. Consider the 6 position players, other than Yelich (#8) who landed within the top 10 for WAR last season:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/christianYelich/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 6, only 2 of them have also won an MVP like Yelich, while 4 of the 6 have higher salaries than the Brewers right fielder. The two who have lower salaries, Ramirez and Chapman, are both just coming off of, or still on their rookie deals which is why they haven't reached max salary potential yet. Yelich, who just exchanged his rookie deal for a 7 year, $49M offer, is considerably underpaid in comparison to the $20M to $35M range expected for a player of his caliber. If the Brewers choose to keep Yelich on the contract, they save a solid $13M to $25M that could be spent on improving other areas of need on the team. While the 2019 Brewers are in the top half of teams for most batting statistics (R, OPS, OBP, etc), they fall into the bottom half for both Starting Pitchers statistics and Reliever stats. Players such as Gerritt Cole, Madison Bumgardner, Zach Wheeler, Cole Hamels, Rick Porcello and Dellin Betances will all be free agents come this next offseason, and it is reasonable to think that with a maximum of $25M of wiggle room, just alone from Yelich's contract, to both complement a blooming Zach Davies and Chase Anderson in the starting rotation with a front end and back end of the rotation starter and a reliever to provide some bullpen depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christian Yelich has become one of if not the best players in the MLB following his trade to Milwaukee, and it is up to the Brewers to take advantage of that before his contract expires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: baseball-reference.com, mlb.com/stats and mlb.com/statcast.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Max Blane</name></author><summary type="html">Drafted as a Florida Marlin 23rd overall in 2010, Christian Yelich was a very highly touted prospect with loads of potential. As predictions usually go for players drafted in the first few rounds, he was expected to eventually reach the Major Leagues and be a top of the order bat, hitting in a fierce and intimidating Marlins lineup (80-82, 3rd in NL East in 2010) that was supposed to include Giancarlo Stanton, Hanley Ramirez, Emilio Bonifacio, Cameron Maybin, and eventually Marcell Ozuna.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analyzing Factors That Go Into a Fast Marathon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/FastestMarathon" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing Factors That Go Into a Fast Marathon" /><published>2020-01-14T18:36:08-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-14T18:36:08-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/FastestMarathon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/FastestMarathon">&lt;p&gt;On October 12, 2019, it was still early morning as the world watched as Elliot Kipchoge put one foot in front of another, gracefully passing the finish line and becoming the first person ever to run a marathon in under two hours. He finished in a blistering fast time of 1:59:40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many factors came together to shatter the two hour time barrier in the marathon. First and foremost, Kipchoge is the best marathoner in the world, as he currently holds the official world record at 2:01:39. He was close to closing in on the barrier, but not quite there yet. The race organizers (INEOS) needed a way to trim down his time by at least 1:40. That equates to about 6 seconds faster per mile than the world record. INEOS was able to accomplish this by having the following: an army of pacers to swap in and out every couple of miles, a car with a laser to keep the pacers in check, an unreleased pair of shoes Nike specifically engineered for the race, an extremely flat course with minimal turns, and an optimal temperature that was cool and not too humid. While most marathon runners cannot expect the same level of support that was made available to Kipchoge, the last two factors seem to be more variable to regular marathon runners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To investigate the effects of the elevation of courses and weather on marathon times, we will consider the results from the Boston, Berlin, and Chicago marathons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Effects of Weather&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To look at the effects of weather, it is best to look at the Boston marathon. The Boston Marathon is infamous for it's volatile year to year weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The median finishing times year to year are almost uniform except for a few standout years. The median finishing times in 2004, 2005 and 2012 are higher than those of the other years shown. During these years, races all share a common factor: the temperature at the starting time was in the 70s with the high of that day reaching the 80s and 90s. Another interesting year is 2013, where the median finishing time was well below the other years'. We can also see that the spread of the times was much lower than the rest of the other results; the starting temperature was 37 degrees and only went up to 55 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These observations from the graph are summarized when we place these race years in bins of categorical temperatures.  This presented a problem because in a 2+ hour race, the temperature did not remain constant throughout the race. The solution was to bin these races with &lt;a href=&quot;https://findmymarathon.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;FindMyMarathon&lt;/a&gt;, where it shows the temperature at the start of the race and the high for that day. The races were placed into three bins: cold, moderate, and hot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;		• Cold races indicate races with a start temperature below 59 degrees fahrenheit and the daily high below 60 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;		• Moderate races were a little trickier, where I considered starting temperatures below 59 degrees but also having a daily high over 60.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;		• Hot races had starting temperatures of over 70 degrees with daily highs of over 70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately, we see the difference of the means between the three bins. To verify that the difference is statistically significant, I ran an Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) test to find that the p-value was approximately zero. Therefore, the difference of means is indeed statistically significant. In other words, there is a very low probability that the difference in the means would appear by chance alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Effects of Elevation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the analysis of the effects of course elevation, it is important to clear up a common misconception. While the difficulty of running up hills is widely recognized, the challenge of running downhill must also be accounted for. Running downhill requires your legs to &quot;catch&quot; you at every step you take to prevent you from falling over. This creates more wear and tear on the leg muscles, which is especially prevalent in long races such as marathons. Thus, the optimal course is one that is as flat as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To look at the effects of elevation, we will look at the Boston and Berlin marathons, two drastically different race courses in terms of elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let's look observe the elevation maps of the respective courses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Boston Marathon Elevation&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see that the Boston Marathon experiences drops of elevation throughout the entire race, showing that the course is mostly downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Berlin Marathon Elevation&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see that the Berlin Marathon elevation is mostly consistent throughout the entire race, showing that it is a relatively flat course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fastestMarathon/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Berlin Marathon Times 2005-2013, Boston Marathon Times 2001-2014&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see that the Boston Marathon has a lower median, twenty fifth percentile, and seventy fifth percentile than the Berlin marathon. We can infer that the downhill course typically speeds up overall times in marathons. This is peculiar, as this same logic does not apply to elite runners, as they actually run slower on the downhill Boston course relative to the flat Berlin course. Perhaps this suggests a fundamental difference between the average runner and an elite runner when running uphill or downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from your individual fitness, the current weather and course itself does play a role in the finishing times. The ideal race temperature for when you're hoping to achieve a new personal best probably should be below 60 degrees. The fastest courses should also be those with the most downhill. However, with more data attributing other variables such as wind, splits and heart rate, we can find more specific relationships. But besides that, the next time you want to run a fast time, hope for a cool day and pick a downhill marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: FindMyMarathon&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Donald Chung</name></author><summary type="html">On October 12, 2019, it was still early morning as the world watched as Elliot Kipchoge put one foot in front of another, gracefully passing the finish line and becoming the first person ever to run a marathon in under two hours. He finished in a blistering fast time of 1:59:40.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Modern Fullback</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ModernFullback" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Modern Fullback" /><published>2020-01-14T17:01:27-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-14T17:01:27-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ModernFullback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ModernFullback">&lt;p&gt;When one hears the word defender, what comes to one's mind? A defender's main job is to prevent the opposition from scoring and stays back while the rest of the team attacks. Straightforward, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern fullback is way more than just a defender. Their duties and expectations have evolved as the game has changed over these past decades. Earlier, their main duties were to prevent opposition wingers from giving crosses, supporting the centre backs while defending and maintaining a good defensive shape. Fullbacks were famed by their defensive qualities and many greats such as Zanetti and Petit are still known for it. However, modern day fullbacks have to do all this and much more. They are now a vital cog to the team's attacking play, putting more emphasis on controlling the game in the attacking third and helping in the team's build up play. It is almost weird that sometimes their defensive duties become their second priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though there have been teams since the early 1950s who have been known for their attacking fullbacks, their importance and abundance has only grown in the past few years. One manager who was vital throughout this revolution was Pep Guardiola.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola has been a key figure for the tactical transformations which have happened in the past decade: one of them being the inverted fullback. He introduced this unconventional idea to the world with Dani Alves during his time at Barcelona and carried it on when he moved on to Bayern Munich. An inverted fullback is a fullback who essentially becomes a central midfielder during the team's build up play. David Alaba and Philipp Lahm flourished in this position and were vital to Bayern's domestic success. Seeing this, many of the top teams followed suite. In the coming years every top team in Europe has placed immense importance on fullbacks and has employed the role of an inverted full back to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This immense importance on fullbacks can clearly be seen in the recent years transfer market history.  Five of the eleven most expensive fullbacks were signed in the summer of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several teams have realized the important value of fullbacks and are ready to pay huge fees to acquire them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I talk about the modern fullback, I can think of 4 types of full backs which are commonly found in different tactical set-ups around the world. The most common one is the overlapping fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Overlapping fullback&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sport has become more tactically fluid over the past few years. Fullbacks started finding more opportunities to burst forward while wingers moved inwards to help create a numerical advantage against opposition defense. And, as the prominence of these narrow wingers grew, so did the presence and abundance of the overlapping fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overlapping fullback in the most simple words is the fullback who is continuously running back and forth, assisting in build up play and providing defensive cover every time the ball is lost. Hence, what this role requires most importantly is high fitness levels and a high level of athleticism. This is rare. A lot of players who attempt to play this role get defensively exposed as they cannot make it back in time to help with defense. This can lead to errors, goals, rash fouls and red cards too. But, if individuals are trained and taught correctly, the manager will be blessed with game-changing fullbacks. Two of the best overlapping fullbacks in the game play in the same team, under Jurgen Klopp; the iconic duo of Andrew Robertson and Trent Alexander Arnold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: David Rawcliffe&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking several records last season, notching 11 and 12 assists respectively, these two embody the role of an overlapping fullback and highlight a fullback's massive importance. Andrew Robertson, being the more defensively sound of the two, is an especially good example of what it really means to be an overlapping fullback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What one can see for Andrew Robertson and to some extent for Trent Alexander Arnold is a great balance between attacking and defensive output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Flanagan's statistics have also been added here to show the evolution of the game. Jon Flanagan, an ex-Liverpool right back, had mainly defensive duties and contributed barely anything to the team's attacking play. The very same position is now used by Trent Alexander Arnold, who under Jurgen Klopp's management has become one of the best attacking right backs in the game of football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is Liverpool's passing map for a game they played vs Watford last season. One can see how high Andrew Robertson and Trent Alexander are placed on the pitch. The size of the circles around them also shows how involved they were in the game. The more red the circle the higher their xG (Expected Goals) is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordi Alba is another example. An essential part to Barcelona's build up play is Jordi Alba's link up play with Lionel Messi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left back ended last season with 2 goals and 8 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another type of overlapping fullback is Aaron Wan Bissaka who gained fame last season and has now secured a $65 million move to Manchester United. Wan Bissaka, even though he notched up only 3 assists last season, put in eye-catching performances throughout last season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wan Bissaka managed to get a lot of defensive work done and also played an important role in dribbling and moving the ball forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not all teams are gifted with such amazing fullbacks who can contribute on both ends of the pitch. To prevent getting exposed when the fullbacks move up the pitch, teams have only one fullback join the attack at a particular time. But, more commonly the defensive midfielder moves in to a defensive role while the fullbacks move up, as seen with Fabinho or Milner at Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Inverted fullback&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guardiola's creation. When Pep moved to Bayern he realized the qualities of the world class wingers, Robben and Ribery, didn't quite match what he was gifted with at Barcelona. Robben and Ribery were not natural narrow wingers, like Messi and Pedro at Barcelona. They liked starting wide and then cutting inside to create more chances. Their starting wide, obviously limits the space for fullbacks to bomb up the pitch. Thus it made sense to have the fullbacks take up narrower positions and help the team structure in other ways.  Crucially, this allowed them to fill the gaps in midfield helped prevent counter attacks from sides that defended deep, possibly the only weakness of Guardiola's Barcelona team. Pep has used several of his fullbacks in different variations of this role; Alaba, Lahm, Delph, Walker and Zinchenko are few prominent names in recent years.Several other managers have also developed and use some amazing inverted fullbacks. Players like Joshua Kimmich and Alex Sandro are world renowned fullbacks in their roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle Walker's heatmap at Tottenham Hotspur:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyle Walker's heatmap at Manchester City:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in Walker's heatmaps before and after his move to Manchester City, he has played more centrally. Playing centrally allowed Manchester City's wingers to take up wider, more natural roles and flourish. Occupying this more central position thus allowed central midfielders David Silva and Kevin De Bruyne to push higher up the pitch and create more and more chances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Independent.ie&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Wingbacks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though these players aren't directly counted as fullbacks, many of the players who play in this role are fullbacks. Essentially wingbacks are found in 3 at the back formations (3-4-3, 3-5-2, 3-1-4-2, etc). Wingbacks are very attack minded fullbacks with reduced defensive duties. Using wingbacks allows team to have a more fluid structure and transition quickly between defense and attack. The perfect example of the impact of wingbacks were Chelsea's dynamic duo of Marcos Alonso and Victor Moses in the 16/17 season. The two were crucial to Chelsea's emphatic title win in Premier League.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consistently bombing forward, Alonso and Moses notched up some amazing numbers for a defender. Alonso ended the season with 6 goals and 3 assists while, Moses ended up with 3 goals and 2 assists. But this isn't all. Consistently going up the pitch, they provided an extra option to Chelsea's midfielders to play diagonal balls to. They created 2 v 1s versus the opposition fullback and made it that much tougher to defend and stop goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clip below highlights how Marcos Alonso's movement frees up space and allows the midfielders to play in diagonal balls to open up tight defenses :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9nffHeS_RfQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another team which uses its wingbacks very wisely is Wolverhampton Wanderers. After being promoted in the 18/19 season, they shocked a lot of viewers and teams not only with their counter attacking style of football but, also their defensive solidarity. Surpassing all expectations, they managed to finish 7th in the league and got into the Europa League. One player who played a key role was Matt Doherty. The right wing back was not only good defensively but was a vital cog in the attacking play. He ended the season with 4 goals and 5 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_13.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Independent.ie&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Defensive Fullback&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside the top tier of European teams, this is probably the most common type of fullback found. Teams need to concentrate on defending to stay alive in the league and to not be destroyed by the stronger teams. By doing so they give up on fluid, quick, attacking football and hence they do not need fullbacks who focus too much on going forward. Take a team such as Burnley for example. They are a defensive team with their attacking output mainly making use of long balls, aerials and the players' sheer physicality. This is their fullback, Phil Bardsley:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being able to do basic defensive tasks such as dominating in the air are also useful, so it's not shocking that all the radar shows him doing is winning aerial duels and not giving the ball away. If Burnley were to try and do anything more direct and attacking, Bardsley would be continually exposed, but as it is, he does what is required of him and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_14.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 14&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 65%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few more numbers which show the evolution of a fullback in the game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_15.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 15&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
	
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_16.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 16&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
	
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/modernFullback/pic_17.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 17&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fullback position has evolved so much in the past few years it is actually impossible to define the role of a modern fullback. It largely depends on how defensive, attacking, fluid, direct, counter-attacking or possession- based a team wants to play. And they are ready to splash out big money to get the correct fullback to meet their tactical preference. But, this is potentially the same for any position on the pitch, highlighting not only the importance of the modern fullback but the evolution of the entire game of soccer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: Statsbomb, Sofascore, The Guardian.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ishaan Shah</name></author><summary type="html">The modern fullback is way more than just a defender. Their duties and expectations have evolved as the game has changed over these past decades. Earlier, their main duties were to prevent opposition wingers from giving crosses, supporting the centre backs while defending and maintaining a good defensive shape. Fullbacks were famed by their defensive qualities and many greats such as Zanetti and Petit are still known for it. However, modern day fullbacks have to do all this and much more. They are now a vital cog to the team's attacking play, putting more emphasis on controlling the game in the attacking third and helping in the team's build up play. It is almost weird that sometimes their defensive duties become their second priority.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Evolution of the Free Throw</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/BSA_Writeup_The_Free_Throw" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Evolution of the Free Throw" /><published>2020-01-06T20:57:40-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-06T20:57:40-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/BSA_Writeup_The_Free_Throw</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/BSA_Writeup_The_Free_Throw">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/shaq_freethrow.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From Wikimedia&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Free Throw: the only shot in basketball that is theoretically free, but players continue to show that it's more difficult than it originally appears. In the early 2000's, the idea of &quot;hack-a-shaq&quot; was introduced. This strategy had players intentionally foul poor free throw shooters, such as Shaquille O'Neal to send them to the charity line. The hope: at least one missed free throw, and an opportunity to seize possession once more. However, as this strategy became popular, teams sent their poor foul shooters to the bench at late moments in a game. Fast forward to 2015: Stephen Curry became the eighth player to join the 50/40/90 club (50% field goal, 40% three-point, 90% free throw), and many shooters began to score at an all-time high rate. With shooting success becoming fundamental to an increasingly offensive game, we thought it would be interesting to look at how the free throw differs from years, stars, position, and three-point shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;PROCEDURE&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To evaluate and compare how the free throw differs from years, stars, position, and three-point shooting, we decided to look at the evolution of the free-throw percentage over two different three-year spans separated by nearly 20 years (2000-2003 and 2016-2019). The question: were players getting better at shooting percentages or was there simply a higher volume of shots and, importantly, how does that relate to the free throw? We compared each individual year of the three-year spans to one another, in order to get an idea of what year-to-year variation in shooting looked like. Next, we compared the two decades with one another to see how the game was truly changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, however, Stephen Curry and Shaquille O'Neal are very different players and should not be compared directly with each other--and thus should be categorized as such. To accommodate for this, we created groups in accordance with the main player's position (e.g. center, point guard).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we thought it would be worthwhile to delineate between the Matthew Dellavedova's of the world and the Lebron James' of the world--those that are high scoring versus those that are not. To do so, we looked at the variation between &quot;stars&quot; (defined as top 20 in points or top 10 in rebounds or top 10 in assists) versus the variation in non-&quot;stars&quot; (people who are not in any of the above categories).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From si.wsj.net&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During garbage time, the trailing team can sometimes rack up an unusually high tally of statistics, leading the respective box score to be misleading with respect to their actual game performance. To limit the players we are analyzing, we added the following caveats to exclude garbage time players: a player must play at least 20 games, average at least 10 minutes per game, have a minimum of one free throw attempt per game, and strictly shoot more than 0.5 three point attempts per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;OUR PREDICTIONS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, especially because of the &quot;hack-a-shaq&quot; era of the early 2000s, we anticipated a large discrepancy in the free throw percentage by position; we expected guards to have the highest percentage (~85%), followed by forward (~75%), and lastly centers (~65%). Furthermore, it seemed reasonable to conclude that if players shoot the three-point shot at a higher rate and percentage, then hopefully, those same players would spend equal time practicing the one shot they should be guaranteed to make every time: the free throw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we believe that non-stars will have less variation in free throw percentage, as stars don't need to focus on the free throw, given their tremendous impact to other facets of the game. Non-stars, however, have less room for error--and should practice, seize, and execute at an opportunity of free points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;DATA&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before crunching numbers, we noticed an interesting trend in the amount of players who qualified for our study over the years. For example, whereas the average number of centers who met our shooting qualification (as defined above) in the 2000's was 5.67, the average number of centers for the 2010's was 29.67. Likely, this can be attributed to centers shooting the three point shot more often as time went on, and thus, more qualified under the &quot;3PTA &gt; 0.5&quot; requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variation in the year-to-year data within the early 2000s--the first of two time periods in this article--remained relatively low, with the greatest variation across the three years occurring at the forward position, but it was still within 1% (76.88% to 77.72%). The data from the early 2000s also emphasizes the general trend which we expected, specifically, that centers had the lowest free throw percent (hovering around 74%), followed by forwards (~77%), and guards with the highest (~79.5%). Although the data did not have the percentages which we expected at the outset of the investigation, there was still a delineation between each position. Further, since the variability between these individual years remained low, any difference between these years and the decades could be attributed to a difference across basketball eras as opposed to the accumulation of annual differences; each position had a dip in free throw percentage either in the 2001-2002 season or the 2002-2003 season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the tail end of the 2010s--the second of two time frames studied in this article--the data appears murkier when comparing the positions. In terms of variation by year, each position still remained relatively steady with the largest range of ~3% occurring at the guard position (81.11% vs. 78.08%). Although the variation did increase--as shown through the higher standard deviations--the data remained constant enough to compare this time frame to that of the early 2000s to look for the desired change in free throw percentage, at least by position. The aspect of this table which surprised us was the free throw percentage of centers compared to forwards, as they were approximately equal, with centers having a slight edge, not forwards; the guards had a higher percentage than the other two groups but by less than earlier in the NBA's history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2000's v. 2010's:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To concatenate the data for the two basic time periods: 2000s and 2010s, we took an average of the three year periods we originally studied, for each decade period. This combined data is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data highlights the surprising lack of difference within each of the three positions from the early 2000s time frame to the late 2010s. In the 2000s, at least, the data appeared exactly how we expected: centers, then forwards, then guards, albeit at a lesser degree than what we anticipated; there was only a 2% difference when grouping by position as opposed to our expected 10% difference. However, in the 2010s, the data paint a distinctly different story, as the centers increased their free throw percentage, while guards and forwards actually had a decrease in their free throw percentages as a position group, making their free throw percentages all occur within a 3% range. Furthermore, the players during the 2010 era exhibited greater variation, as their standard deviations increased by about 1.5 percentage points: thus, players in today's NBA occur across a broader range of the spectrum, as there are some elite free throw shooters (e.g. Steph Curry, James Harden), but also some horrendous ones (e.g. Lonzo Ball).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;STARS v. NONSTARS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From NYDailyNews&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data shows that the stars in the NBA have a higher free throw percentage by a margin of almost 2% in both decades. Likewise, in both decades, the standard deviation for stars is less by a notable margin of at least 0.5%. Unexpectedly, both the free throw percentage of stars and nonstars went down by a factor of at least 0.5% from the 2000s to the 2010s. Moreover, shooters in the 2000's were much more consistent, as demonstrated by an increase of 1% in standard deviations from the players in the 2000s to 2010's.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;THREE POINT CORRELATION&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was our hypothesis that there would be a correlation between three point percentages and free throw percentages.  To show this correlation, we created graphs conveying each player as a dot, placed according to his free throw and three-point percentage. Additionally, we have created a line of best fit, showing the general trend for each decade in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2000's exemplify consistency. The line of best fit shoots a free throw possession from around 73% to up to around 82%. Additionally, there is a large clump of players all in the same spot. With few outliers, the data leads to the conclusion that the 2000's was very consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2010's are much more turbulent. This can likely be attributed to higher shooting volume. Here, the line of best fit for free throw percentage spans from as low as 60% to as high as 87%. This is a much different range than in the 2000's where the deviation is 9 points as opposed to the 2010's where the deviation is 27 points. Additionally, there are more outliers than the 2000's, as well as a generally larger clump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From NBC Pro Basketball Talk&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We overlaid the graphs, as shown below, to get a visual of what the two decades looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2000's seem more consistent, as the line of best fit seems to go from around 74% to up to 85%. However, as shooting as increased over the decades, the 2010's graph shows a different story. Not only are there more points in the 2010's--due to higher shooting volume--there is also more inconsistency. At the top end, in the 2010's, shooters have higher three-point-to-free-throw percentage ratio, such as Lonzo Ball. While the visual is an eye sore, it shows the correlation and development over the years; the game has progressed such that there is a higher volume of shooters, but with the increase in volume there is a much higher variance in percentages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/freeThrow/pic_12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;From i.pinimg.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our data paint a picture that is in stark contrast to our initial expectations. No single position has completely distanced itself from the other two in terms of free throw percentage; in fact, in today's game there is less of a difference in free throw percentage amongst different positions than there was in the 2000s. More variability in our data also emphasizes that, although we have better players at the line today, we also have worse ones. The average for guards and forwards decreased between the two time frames, while centers had an increase. These results lead us to question the &quot;hack-a-Shaq&quot; method which has become so renowned -- the fouling of big men in crunch time. Perhaps centers have responded to that method of &quot;bullying&quot; by bolstering their free throw percentage, especially when compared with players at other positions. Maybe the adage should simply be revised, as free throw percentage is not as position-dependent as it seems on TV. Maybe the adage for today's NBA should not be &quot;hack-a-Shaq.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it should be &quot;hack-a-Lonzo.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: NBA (NBA.com), ESPN (espn.com)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Ethan Allavarpu</name></author><summary type="html">The Free Throw. the only shot in basketball that is theoretically free, but players continue to show that it's more difficult than it originally appears. In the early 2000's, the idea of &quot;hack-a-shaq&quot; was introduced. This strategy had players intentionally foul poor free throw shooters, such as Shaquille O'Neal to send them to the charity line. The hope. at least one missed free throw, and an opportunity to seize possession once more. However, as this strategy became popular, teams sent their poor foul shooters to the bench at late moments in a game. Fast forward to 2015. Stephen Curry became the eighth player to join the 50/40/90 club (50% field goal, 40% three-point, 90% free throw), and many shooters began to score at an all-time high rate. With shooting success becoming fundamental to an increasingly offensive game, we thought it would be interesting to look at how the free throw differs from years, stars, position, and three-point shooting.</summary></entry></feed>